<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lab-notebooks on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/lab-notebook/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Lab-notebooks on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/lab-notebook/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Hugo and blogdown</title>
      <link>/2017/04/19/migrating-to-hugo-and-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/19/migrating-to-hugo-and-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>After OpenWetWare (2010), Wordpress (2010 - 2012) and Jekyll (2012 - 2017), I move platforms once again: now to Hugo. Why the move? As usual, this site remains a way for me to explore new technologies, but the cutting edge is by no means the allure which leads me to migrate. Rather, I find myself ever trying to move towards simpler platforms, what’s easier to maintain, free to host, easier to replicate, and what makes best use of the most widely available and well-maintained existing software and avoids unncessary custom hacks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative evolution: Is the data informative?</title>
      <link>/2010/12/31/comparative-phylogenetics-is-the-data-informative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 21:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/31/comparative-phylogenetics-is-the-data-informative/</guid>
      <description>Working on my SICB talk, going a little further into the example of fitting the lambda model on the Anoles data to illustrate the ways in which we may lack sufficient data for the question.
 The dataset may not contain adequate signal of the parameter / phenomenon in question
 The dataset may not be adequately large
  Anoles data set (23 taxa):
This first image shows the distribution of lambda values estimated from many datasets all simulated under a lambda = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic limits to evolutionary branching</title>
      <link>/2010/12/30/stochastic-limits-to-evolutionary-branching/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 22:12:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/30/stochastic-limits-to-evolutionary-branching/</guid>
      <description>My last post was a bit pessimistic, sometimes I can still miss the forest for the trees. Hidden in those figures, the main point has been staring me in the face. So let&amp;rsquo;s try this again.
Stochastic limits to evolutionary branching is the story of two dueling timescales. The first timescale is that of the evolutionary process: the frequency of steps (mutation rate, $ \mu$) and the size of the steps (mutation kernel standard deviation $ \sigma_{\mu}$), on top of which we add the selection gradient, created by the ecology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Notebook Science Abstract</title>
      <link>/2010/12/30/open-notebook-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 17:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/30/open-notebook-science/</guid>
      <description>In addition to my primary research categories, I make some entries in my lab notebook to document and reflect on my experiment in open notebook science. This includes my notes on tools I try out for open and collaborative science, including uses of social media, cloud computing, and scientific databases and repositories.
This serves as a cover-page for the open science entries in my notebook, displaying the most recent entries, articles, figures and code through rss feeds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameter exploration in adaptive dynamics branching</title>
      <link>/2010/12/30/parameter-exploration-in-adaptive-dynamics-branching/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 16:52:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/30/parameter-exploration-in-adaptive-dynamics-branching/</guid>
      <description>Ran a series of simulations overnight to explore aspects of time-to-branching at different phases of the branching process. Still using only 16 replicates per data point, though increased maximum time for a run another order of magnitude to avoid timing out runs influencing the dataset for the slow-rate parameters. Still seems to suggest a regime beyond which branching becomes completely improbable. Not clear that the transition is a sharp as the Arrhenius approximation might suggest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>adaptive-dynamics Simulations</title>
      <link>/2010/12/29/adaptive-dynamics-simulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2010 16:29:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/29/adaptive-dynamics-simulations/</guid>
      <description>Setting up some adaptive dynamics simulations to complete the parameter-space search. Currently the demo library contains two files, providing the coexistence-only tests and the full evolutionary simulation. This picks up from Aug 30/Sept 1 on coexistence times and Aug 12&amp;frasl;13 entries on waiting times until branching (while still on OWW).
coexistence times coexist_times.R creates contour plots of the coexistence time under demographic noise expected at a particular position of the pairwise invasibility plot (PIP).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DoE renewal and a year in review</title>
      <link>/2010/12/24/doe-renewal-and-a-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2010 03:24:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/24/doe-renewal-and-a-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>This time of year I have to file my renewal for my DOE Fellowship, including a statement of accomplishments and a summary of the computational aspects of my work. Seemed like a good idea to jot these down in my notebook as well:
synopsis of accomplishments over the year: In January I passed my qualifying exam, advancing to candidacy where my dissertation remains my only requirement. In March I attended the phylogenetics workshop in Bodega Bay, an internationally known week-long training program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing, Cloud Computing, and #scio11</title>
      <link>/2010/12/23/writing-cloud-hpc-and-scio11/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2010 19:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/23/writing-cloud-hpc-and-scio11/</guid>
      <description>Working on a few things in today&amp;rsquo;s lab notebook entry. Some more notes on exploring cloud computing tools, sketching out some ideas for my #scio11 science online panel discussion on open notebook science, and otherwise working on my phylogenetics mansucript.
Cloud Computing An interesting package was announced over the r-sig-hpc list today, creating an arbitrarily large Hadoop cluster out of Amazon EC2 instances directly from the R command line. JD Long has been very responsive to my naive questions on setting it up, so I was able to quickly activate an Elastic Map Reduce account via Amazon Web Services and run the example code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sun: Visualizing my coding over the past year</title>
      <link>/2010/12/20/sun-visualizing-my-coding-over-the-past-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2010 00:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/20/sun-visualizing-my-coding-over-the-past-year/</guid>
      <description>Not really working today, as holidays approach, but came across the Gource toolkit for creating video visualization from git development (inspired by the Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s example). So in the spirit of year-in-review reflections, here&amp;rsquo;s my development from the past year (just for the phylogenetic statistics work).
Quality is a little too poor to read file names, more entertaining than practical. Other user icons appear in December corresponding with my move to running the code from Amazon cloud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thurs: writing section on comparing to AIC</title>
      <link>/2010/12/16/thurs-writing-section-on-comparing-to-aic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2010 22:50:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/16/thurs-writing-section-on-comparing-to-aic/</guid>
      <description>Phylogenetics writing still continues.
AIC Error rates
Choosing by having &amp;lt; 5% probability of rejecting the simpler model when it is true.
Choosing the equal-likelihood division:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Example sets &amp; more EC2</title>
      <link>/2010/12/15/weds-example-sets-more-ec2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2010 16:24:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/15/weds-example-sets-more-ec2/</guid>
      <description>A bit delayed from having to rerun analyses on EC2 (still learning&amp;hellip;) More to run today (lambda trials for Anoles &amp;ndash; should really recode this in C!).
Trying to decide if its best to start off with the power curves and work backwards or build up from the basics. Probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter too much which. Also figuring out which examples to present first:
Where the painted trees are the following:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: evolution thoughts while writing...</title>
      <link>/2010/12/14/tues-phylogenetics-thoughts-while-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2010 17:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/14/tues-phylogenetics-thoughts-while-writing/</guid>
      <description>Again spending most of the day writing. (Maybe) processing some ideas in writing by writing in my notebook as I make my edits.
Ideas I&amp;rsquo;m trying to get across in today&amp;rsquo;s edits Parameter estimation is more demanding of the data than model choice. Knowing if a value is different from zero is easier than knowing what it is.
Code updates to-do  Need to add S3 wrapper functions for ouch so both can call montecarlotest() in the pmc package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/12/13/back-to-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 10:56:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/13/back-to-writing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citations</title>
      <link>/2010/12/11/citations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 07:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/11/citations/</guid>
      <description>This evening I&amp;rsquo;m testing extensions to find a better way to include citations in my entries. Thus far I&amp;rsquo;ve use Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s convenient copy-paste citation tool to paste the whole citation in, which I suppose could work reasonably smoothly with the nice footnotes plugin I recently adopted. However, this still requires a couple more steps than I need to cite in my LaTeX text editor or in OpenOffice.
Using the papercite plugin, I can add citations to posts in much the same way that I add them to my latex documents, using the citation key created Mendeley when it makes my bibtex file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>socialR: Reproducible Research &amp; Notebook integration with R</title>
      <link>/2010/12/11/socialr-an-r-package-to-track-the-status-of-computations-with-social-network-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 03:44:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/11/socialr-an-r-package-to-track-the-status-of-computations-with-social-network-tools/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve created an R package that uses social media tools for reproducible research. The goal of the package is this: whenever I run a code, output figures are automatically added to my figure repository (Flickr), linked to the timestamped version of the code that produced them in the code repository. Figures should be tagged by project and be embedded selectively or automatically into this lab notebook. The basic workflow of the notebook looks like this:[ref]Diagram of my notebook as presented at Science Online, 2011, see other slides in my entry on this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals manuscript</title>
      <link>/2010/12/10/warning-signals-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 21:10:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/10/warning-signals-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with Alan today to discuss outline. Came up with basic break-down of paragraphs:
 Intro/Abstract
 Scope: Previous work, scope simple example existence of warning signal/CSD is clear. Identifiability/Power not clear. Mention the issue of Replicates
 Nonlinearity not observed with infinite data
 reasons detection fails: Identifiability issue &amp;amp; Power issue. Example signal that exists but inadequate power to detect?
 Eigenvalue story
 Probability of data vs Probability of a statistic</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Power in Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2010/12/09/exploring-power-in-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2010 23:03:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/09/exploring-power-in-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Started trying to get the power curves for sample-size and rate of change. Currently focusing on the transcritical bifurcation model. This first pass uses just 100 replicates, which appears to be not nearly enough. Need some troubleshooting on handling to get power curves out. Scroll through, the set has 65 different images:
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;tag&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;stochpowercurvesslides&amp;rdquo;]
(code ids in image discription, compare to structured-popultions git log. )
Includes plots of the timeseries, giving a visual clue of how dramatic the warning signal is under each case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice SICB Presentation</title>
      <link>/2010/12/08/practice-sicb-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 22:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/08/practice-sicb-presentation/</guid>
      <description>Gave my practice talk for Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology in Wainwright lab this afternoon, after (not quite) finishing the presentation. Trying to figure out the best way to introduce these ideas to a broad audience (same challenge as with the manuscript).
Talk storyboard:
Looking at other talks in my session: Macroevolution I - Methods and Character Evolution, looks like a reasonably sophisticated group.
Good feedback from the Wainwright Lab:  Emphasize: Currently we worry that we don&amp;rsquo;t have the right models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping out SICB Presentation: Is your phylogeny informative?</title>
      <link>/2010/12/07/mapping-out-sicb-presentation-is-your-phylogeny-informative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2010 22:42:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/07/mapping-out-sicb-presentation-is-your-phylogeny-informative/</guid>
      <description>Assembling material/outline for my SICB presentation in January, will be giving a practice talk in the Wainwright lab on Wednesday. 15 minute presentation with 5 minutes for questions.
 Designing presentation in &amp;ldquo;storyboard&amp;rdquo; format in Inkscape. Will figure out if I convert to slides or not.
 Simulations under the Anoles dataset to show posterior distributions of lambda. Exploring the connection between the likelihood of a parameter under each model to that of the distributions of the likelihood ratio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>follow up from Fri discussions: Revisiting post-predictive evaluation</title>
      <link>/2010/12/06/follow-up-from-fri-discussions-revisiting-post-predictive-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2010 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/06/follow-up-from-fri-discussions-revisiting-post-predictive-evaluation/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, a seminar prompted me to take a closer look at a particular post-predictive evaluation technique applied reasonably often in our recent literature,see earlier entry. I think by phrasing the approach more concisely and precisely it will be clear what the difficulty is.
As usual, we consider some data $ \vec X$ and a set of $ N$ models specified by parameters, $ \lbrace \vec \theta_1, \vec \theta_2, \vec \ldots \theta_N\rbrace $, then we can express the likelihood of the model as the probability of the data under the given model and parameter values:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2010/12/04/identifying-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 22:41:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/04/identifying-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Updated methods for the Monte Carlo estimate of the distributions of likelihood ratios completed on Wednesday this week, modulo some troubleshooting of code. Now exploring the parameter range in which warning signals can be identified with accurate power. Individual power tests provide a good start, but remains to generate power curves for each bifurcation type by magnitude of the loss of stability, length/duration of the timeseries and the sampling frequency.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on the New Policies for Data Archiving at NSF and in Common Journals</title>
      <link>/2010/12/03/nsf-and-journal-data-archiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2010 19:08:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/03/nsf-and-journal-data-archiving/</guid>
      <description>This post is a work in progress, a scratch pad for me to start assembling what I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning about and resources pertaining to the new policies emerging from NSF and journals relevant to ecology and evolution. Hoping to highlight not only the policies, but the issues, opportunities, and concerns around them.
I am hoping to help organize a workshop to discuss these issues in my department this Winter. The Davis Open Science group, is planning a series of these workshops, hoping to work with departments, the libraries and the UC Davis Office of Research and its Responsible Conduct of Research  program (in compliance with NIH/NSF ethics requirements), as well as resident faculty and editors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPB : David Collar</title>
      <link>/2010/12/01/cpb--david-collar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2010 00:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/01/cpb--david-collar/</guid>
      <description>Identifying ecological constraint on morph and function using phylogenies. 2007 CPB grad, losos post doc, now postdoc w Rita.
Indep origin of &amp;lsquo;bass&amp;rsquo; cranial morph. Also unique patterns- stonefish. Phylo comparative methods to address why and how. Three types of factors on morphology: ecological, time!, intrinsic (genetic, behavior) constraints. Outline:
I. determinants of morph diversification.
II. Complex traits.
I. Diversification rate vary by habitat? (Dragon lizards- diverse morph, diverse habitat). Reconstruct history of habitat use (4 types), (assign discrete traits) then stoch character maps to reconstruct (paint) tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Fitting the limiting OU models to each bifurcation</title>
      <link>/2010/11/30/tues-fitting-the-limiting-ou-models-to-each-bifurcation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2010 22:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/30/tues-fitting-the-limiting-ou-models-to-each-bifurcation/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I derived the linearized SDEs for the saddle node bifurcation :
$$ dX = 2\sqrt{r(t)} (\sqrt{r(t)} + \theta -X) dt + \sigma \sqrt{\sqrt{r(t)}+\theta} dB_t $$
and the transcritical bifurcation
$$ dX = r(t) (K - X) dt + \sqrt{K} dB_t $$
Now to implement them for fitting by likelihood using generic $ r(t) $. I go back to the warning() model implemented in sde_likelihood.R code. We can just solve the odes directly:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further treatment of the limiting models</title>
      <link>/2010/11/29/further-treatment-of-the-limiting-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 19:01:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/29/further-treatment-of-the-limiting-models/</guid>
      <description>Have spent the last three days building and testing the infrastructure to fit the canonical form of a saddle-node (fold) bifurcation by likelihood. Actually I don&amp;rsquo;t use the canonical form straight up: $ dx/dt = x^2 +r$ cannot be fit directly in this manner, since it needs a couple scale transformations on the variables to get the units right (a multiple for the unit scale and an additive factor for the zero point), and more importantly, isn&amp;rsquo;t a stochastic model so cannot assign probabilities to the outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges in estimating phylogenetic signal</title>
      <link>/2010/11/29/challenges-in-estimating-phylogenetic-signal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 07:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/29/challenges-in-estimating-phylogenetic-signal/</guid>
      <description>Uncertainty in estimate of lambda illustrated by simulating 1000 data sets on the Geopsiza tree under a model with lambda = 0.62. Shows the high uncertainty in estimating lambda at all, despite the power in the estimate at this value.
(Code)
Will fill this out further later. Will be interesting to compare at different base values of lambda used for the simulation.
Have updated the codbase to provide bootstraps of parameters as part of the monte carlo output.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihoods for quadratic models cont</title>
      <link>/2010/11/28/likelihoods-for-quadratic-models-cont/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2010 21:14:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/28/likelihoods-for-quadratic-models-cont/</guid>
      <description>Considering the fits of the quadratic models from yesterday.
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;tag&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;quadraticfitslides&amp;rdquo; tag_mode=&amp;ldquo;all&amp;rdquo;]
Analysis of fits Of course these fits rely entirely on mapping the location of the stable point and the slope through that point, something they still cannot do all that well. In this parameterization the the stable intercept is $$ \hat x = \sqrt{r}+\theta $$ and slope at intercept is $$ \frac{\partial f(\hat x)}{\partial x} = -2\sqrt{r} $$ This creates a numerical optimization problem, since there is high importance on getting the mean right, and less on the variance, the routine tends to fix the combination of r and theta to get the mean right, and then cannot change r to get the slope correct without getting penalized for the loss of likelihood in changing the mean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing Likelihoods for quadratic models</title>
      <link>/2010/11/27/implementing-likelihoods-for-quadratic-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2010 11:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/27/implementing-likelihoods-for-quadratic-models/</guid>
      <description>Working from the quadratic model for the saddle node bifurcation rather than the linear (OU) model. Recall that the dynamics are:
$$dX = \left( r - (x-\theta)^2\right)dt + \beta \sqrt{X} dB_t $$
and the linear noise approximation gives a linear Fokker Planck equation such that the probability distribution is Gaussian with moments ((corrected from yesterday to scale noise, basically as pure-birth Poisson process))
$$\frac{d \hat{x}}{dt} &amp;amp;= r - (\hat{x}-\theta)^2 $$ $$ \frac{d \sigma^2}{dt} &amp;amp;= -2 (\hat x - \theta )\sigma^2 + \beta \left(r - (\hat{x}-\theta)^2 \right) $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tweets from an Ecology Field class </title>
      <link>/2010/11/25/tweets-from-an-ecology-field-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2010 02:06:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/25/tweets-from-an-ecology-field-class/</guid>
      <description>I just spoke with Professor Mau Stanton, a leading researcher in our field and an award-winning teacher, about the potential for using twitter in her field ecology course. Though never having used any social media before, Mau has both clear and clever idea of how she wants to apply it in this 15-student field class.
The challenge: Students don&amp;rsquo;t seem to read email as much any more, and are often not at a computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals: Likelihoods Straight-up</title>
      <link>/2010/11/24/warning-signals-likelihoods-straight-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 21:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/24/warning-signals-likelihoods-straight-up/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with Alan this morning. I haven&amp;rsquo;t solved likelihood of power spectra (previous couple entries in Stoch. Pop / warning signals), though after meeting with Sebastian (11&amp;frasl;9) probably the best method works from the correlation function. Define a new stochastic process Y $$ Y_1 = X_1 X_2 + X_2 X_3 + X_3 X_4 + \ldots $$ $$ Y_2 = X_1 X_3 + X_2 X_4 + \ldots $$ $$ Y_3 = \ldots $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in simple tests</title>
      <link>/2010/11/22/power-in-simple-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2010 08:00:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/22/power-in-simple-tests/</guid>
      <description>Exploring power in simple tree models. With the smaller tree from the _geospiza _dataset, (14 tips, left) is less than yesterday&amp;rsquo;s in the bimaculus Anoles (with 23 tips, right)
(code)
Also wrote the OUCH-based wrapper function to fit tree transformation parameters. Unfortunately it currently transforms from ape to ouch format repeatedly (in order to use ape&amp;rsquo;s tree transforms, need to write native ouch-format transforms), so it may not be any faster.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two questions</title>
      <link>/2010/11/21/two-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 21:53:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/21/two-questions/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about a few elements of the Monte Carlo approach that seem to be particularly subtle in interpretation. Thought I&amp;rsquo;d write them out here as a separate examples to help think through them. Thoughts?
Question 1 Should the Monte Carlo simulations use the maximum likelihood test and null model estimated from the data (as in McLachlan 1987, Goldman 1993, Huelsenbeck 1996) or draw from the distribution of model parameters for each simulation?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making R twitter?</title>
      <link>/2010/11/21/following-my-computer-simulations-on-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 21:28:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/21/following-my-computer-simulations-on-twitter/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m running quite a few of my analyses on my remote server, a 16 core, 32 GB ram, Ubuntu server with Tesla GPU, named &amp;ldquo;zero&amp;rdquo; (we&amp;rsquo;re creative folks). It&amp;rsquo;s easy to start lots of simulations (from ssh), harder to track when they are finished and verify results. No longer &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;zero&amp;rdquo; now uses social media to share what she&amp;rsquo;s up to. Find her on twitter: @tweeting_cpu
Social Computation  Provides automated updating of simulation status and error messages</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sat: evolution -- porting tree transformations to OUCH?</title>
      <link>/2010/11/20/sat-phylogenetics-porting-tree-transformations-to-ouch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 23:36:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/20/sat-phylogenetics-porting-tree-transformations-to-ouch/</guid>
      <description>The overnight runs yesterday using the geiger models bm and lambda on the (transformed) Anoles dataset don&amp;rsquo;t seem to converge, spooling jobs that continue running even when R exits &amp;ndash; probably that same problem in ape somewhere that was fixed by writing the tree out to Nexus and re-reading it, a very strange and subtle bug. Will try this and restart the runs. 
Ordered as: bm_v_lambda_origdata.png, delta_v_lambda.png, bm_v_lambda.png (data simulated under OU), each with 100 replicates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fri: extending Geiger to Monte Carlo method</title>
      <link>/2010/11/19/fri-extending-geiger-to-monte-carlo-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 19:51:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/19/fri-extending-geiger-to-monte-carlo-method/</guid>
      <description>Completing my extension of geiger into object oriented design whereby I can easily apply the Monte Carlo approach to test fits using function calls to model fits such as update() and simulate(). A quick convenient example: AIC would prefer (though not by munch) the delta transform model over the Brownian motion model; a conclusion not supported by the Monte Carlo test, which suggests there is not enough power to choose between these models:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thurs: evolution likelihood</title>
      <link>/2010/11/18/thurs-phylogenetics-likelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 20:05:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/18/thurs-phylogenetics-likelihood/</guid>
      <description>Back to writing for today. Working on discussion of non-nested models. Looking at the reverse comparison, can get the reverse p value. The case of OU.3 vs the OU.4 model doesn&amp;rsquo;t show either test to be significant at the 95\% confidence level,but the case of OU.3 vs OU.15 (lets every species in the top two clades be unique) does:
The reverse p value easily rejects this silly OU.15 model, though AIC vastly prefers it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds</title>
      <link>/2010/11/18/weds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 08:06:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/18/weds/</guid>
      <description>Great discussion in Monte Carlo Seminar with Rannala on the two rate estimation papers. See in-text notes, but focus on mechanisms of speciation and extinction as intrinsic (lineage specific) or extrinsic (perhaps spatially specific or global).
Calculation of the likelihood function for the rates seems straight forward. Start by imaging the pure-birth model, simply allow branch lengths as draws from the exponential distribution of parameter lambda. Allowing extinction: probability a lineage speciates (as before) and then survives to present day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues seminar</title>
      <link>/2010/11/16/tues/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2010 17:47:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/16/tues/</guid>
      <description>Sarah Dalrymple seminar. Rick Karban&amp;rsquo;s excellent intro: &amp;ldquo;unlike the rest of these seminars, Sarah will tell us something new.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Sarah&amp;rsquo;s really out there.&amp;ldquo; Also mentions TAC and art teaching.
Ants, Jeff pine &amp;amp; fire Fire suppression dramatic impacts. Prescribed under story burns work! ie Angora fire in Tahoe, 2007. Discover rings of unburned soil around base of tree, reducing damage&amp;hellip; undescribed!
More common in recently burned ( 30 yrs. What makes the rings?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution today:  Discussion groups, writing, etc</title>
      <link>/2010/11/15/phylogenetics-today-discussion-groups-writing-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 22:37:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/15/phylogenetics-today-discussion-groups-writing-etc/</guid>
      <description>Interesting discussion of a Lenski paper in Wainwright&amp;rsquo;s 270.
Barrick, J.E. et al. Genome evolution and adaptation in a long-term experiment with Escherichia coli. Nature 461, 1243-7(2009).
Seems to focus on surprise of continuing linear rate of increase in beneficial mutations, though statistics don&amp;rsquo;t seem to confirm. Curious about uncertainty in assay of fitness estimates (seem to go down at times, but surely not fixing deleterious mutations). General difficulties in setup of exponential growth with applications of classic constant population size, but maybe we&amp;rsquo;re all missing something.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: Post-predictive verification exploration; writing and figures</title>
      <link>/2010/11/11/thursday-post-predictive-verification-exploration-writing-and-figures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 20:47:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/11/thursday-post-predictive-verification-exploration-writing-and-figures/</guid>
      <description>On Post-predictive Verification Considering the kind of post-predictive verification I was discussing with Dan on Tuesday. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the simple birth-death branching process. Starting from the master equation, the linearity gives us an accurate model as a Gaussian process where the systematic van Kampen expansion gives us the Fokker Planck equation whose solution is completely specified by its first two moments:
[latex] \frac{dN}{dt} = (\lambda - \mu) N \</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution statistics </title>
      <link>/2010/11/11/phylogenetics-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 08:13:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/11/phylogenetics-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the best way for representing the Monte Carlo Likelihood approach visually, including comparison power and comparison to AIC.
Blue line is AIC, dotted red line is real data. Red line to the right of blue line indicates test model is rejecting the null model by AIC score. Solid distribution are likelihood ratios simulated under null, dotted are simulated under test.
The p-value is the integral of the null distribution lying right of the observed likelihood ratio in the real data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday - SDEs then back to phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/2010/11/10/tuesday-sdes-then-back-to-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2010 19:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/10/tuesday-sdes-then-back-to-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>Nice meeting with Sebastian this morning, reviewed my spectral approach problem (see anything in Stochastic Population Dynamics / warning signals in the past week) and the multivariate SDE problem Peter posed Oct 30th. No solutions yet but some ideas to get started.
With regards the SDE problem, note that it reduces to:
$$ dX_1 = B_2 d B_1 $$
and note also that if this were $$ dX_1 = B_1 d B_1 $$ this would be a classic exercise in intro SDEs we can look up in Oksendal,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday and some phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/2010/11/08/monday-and-some-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 22:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/08/monday-and-some-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>Working on paper revisions. Added a separate demo file just for generating the figures and analysis used in the manuscript, called likelihood_manuscript.R Need to clean and reorganize the package files and demos.
Added full species names and islands to the tip labels of the tree. Adjusting which example paintings/regimes to include, currently focusing on the original OU.LP model (now calling it OU.3 following Brian&amp;rsquo;s recommendation for simplicity), OU.4, (originally OU.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my Lab Notebook</title>
      <link>/2010/11/08/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 02:50:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/08/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: Not a Blog Welcome to my open lab notebook. This is the active, permanent record of all my scientific research, standing in place of the traditional bound lab notebook. It is a record of ideas, and intuitions; results and mistakes. Please bear in mind that the notebook is primarily a tool for me to do science, not communicate it. I write my entries with the hope that they are intelligible to my future self; and maybe intelligible to my collaborators and experts in my field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: Evolution reading, writing</title>
      <link>/2010/11/05/friday-evolution-reading-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 18:21:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/05/friday-evolution-reading-writing/</guid>
      <description>Read through the article for Monday&amp;rsquo;s PBG270, a 2009 Nature paper from the Plotkin lab on mutational robustness and the rate of evolution. They consider an interesting little setup. Start with a Moran model (individual born, may mutate, choses who to replace at random), but allow the following mutational structure (landscape). Of P possible genotypes, each can only move to one of K neighbors by a single mutation. Call the genotype(s) of optimal fitness C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2010/11/05/thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 18:08:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/05/thursday/</guid>
      <description>Wrote yesterday&amp;rsquo;s entry on power spectral analysis difficulties from yesterday. Why don&amp;rsquo;t I remember my physics training better? Bialek&amp;rsquo;s Phy562 notes still very helpful. No one else seems to write about this stuff clearly enough for me. Including me. 8a-11a
Catching up on reading. Good news and discussion items in Nature on publishing code and review materials, excellent piece on climate change scientists engaging media, climate high performance computing in Brazil; etc see headlines and links in my twitter feed archive for today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting the details right on the Fourier Transform approach to likelihood</title>
      <link>/2010/11/03/getting-the-details-right-on-the-fourier-transform-approach-to-likelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 16:28:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/03/getting-the-details-right-on-the-fourier-transform-approach-to-likelihood/</guid>
      <description>Recall that we consider the power spectrum of some measurable fluctuating quantity x(t), defined as
$$ y(\omega) = \int0^T dt e^{i\omega t} x(t) $$ $$ S(\omega) = \lim{T \to \infty} \frac{1}{2\pi T} \left| y(\omega)\right|^2 $$
A little work can show is equal to the Fourier transform of the autocorrelation function, $ \langle x(t) x(t&amp;rsquo;) \rangle = C(t-t&amp;rsquo;) $.
We evaluate the correlation function of their Fourier transform (note $ x (\omega) $ is really $ \tilde x(\omega)$, the new transformed variable, I&amp;rsquo;ve dropped the tilde only out of laziness):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviews, organization, rewrites</title>
      <link>/2010/11/03/reviews-organization-rewrites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 05:20:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/03/reviews-organization-rewrites/</guid>
      <description>Today&amp;rsquo;s a mixed bag of activities. Finished a journal review, comments confidential, recorded in my reviewed papers archive. I then organized documents library (more below) and then back to paper revisions.
The reference manager software Mendeley recently upgraded the way it handles groups and sharing, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been waiting to revise how it impacts my workflow around articles. Articles can be organized into folders (collections) or kept unsorted within the library, and can be part of as multiple collections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short note: Trait diversification rates controlled by other traits</title>
      <link>/2010/10/30/short-note-trait-diversification-rates-controlled-by-other-traits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/30/short-note-trait-diversification-rates-controlled-by-other-traits/</guid>
      <description>Peter posed an interesting question to me this afternoon: can we infer a model in which the rate of evolution in one trait (say, its Brownian diversification rate parameter) depends on the value of another trait (say, linearly and assume the other trait depends on Brownian motion). Without all those assumptions we write this generally as:
$$ dX_t = f_x(X_t, Y_t) dt + \sigma_x(X_t, Y_t) d W_t $$ $$ dY_t = f_y(Y_t) dt + \sigma_y(Y_t) d W_t $$ (subscripts do not imply derivatives in my notation)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new twist on the approach</title>
      <link>/2010/10/28/a-new-twist-on-the-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2010 16:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/28/a-new-twist-on-the-approach/</guid>
      <description>Matching the warning signal to different SDE models couldn&amp;rsquo;t retain the simplicity and generality needed, so I intend to work on the transformed data instead. Taking the power spectrum of the data, we have a new curve fitting problem:
(Code). This can be turned into a linear curve fitting problem by taking the log of the inverse Fourrier transform, then the slope is our stability parameter. Can we do this estimation by likelihood instead of least-squares?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Red Noise (aside exercise)</title>
      <link>/2010/10/28/red-noise-aside-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/28/red-noise-aside-exercise/</guid>
      <description>Consider the first-order autoregressive process: $$ X_{t+1} = \rho X_t + \sqrt{1-\rho^2}Z_t $$
Why the funny term at the end? This comes from normalizing the variance,
$$ \begin{multline} E( (\rho X_t + \sqrt{1-\rho^2} Z_t)^2 ) = E (\rho^2 X_t^2) + E(2 \rho X_t \sqrt{1-\rho^2}) Z_t ) + E( X_t^2 Z_t^2 (1-\rho^2) ) \end{multline}$$
by independence:
$$ = \rho^2 E(X_t^2) + 2 \rho \sqrt{1-\rho^2} E( X_t ) E( Z_t ) + E( X_t^2) E(Z_t^2) (1-\rho^2) $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals -- Where are we now?</title>
      <link>/2010/10/27/warning-signals-where-are-we-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2010 16:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/27/warning-signals-where-are-we-now/</guid>
      <description>The last few days have involved an investigation into the ability to capture the essential features of the dynamics leading up to a saddle node bifurcation as a linear stochastic differential equation. The warning signals question then becomes a model-choice problem between constant and time-dependent coefficients:
$$ dX_t = \alpha \left(\theta_t - X_t\right) dt + \sigma_t dW_t $$
and
$$ dX_t = \alpha_t (\theta_t - X_t) dt + \sigma_t dW_t $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correcting for the mean dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/10/26/correcting-for-the-mean-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2010 16:46:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/26/correcting-for-the-mean-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I began to address concerns of different models that have different mean dynamics, and how this influences the warning signals. This poses several kinds of issues.
 First, if the mean is changing, the model fitting must be appropriate to this &amp;ndash; either by fitting this rate of change or correcting for it.
 Second, the variance is expected to scale with the mean, and scale differently under different noise models (particularly environmental vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrong picture, wrong model: why warning signals don&#39;t look like rare events</title>
      <link>/2010/10/25/wrong-picture-wrong-model-why-warning-signals-dont-look-like-rare-events/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2010 23:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/25/wrong-picture-wrong-model-why-warning-signals-dont-look-like-rare-events/</guid>
      <description>Detecting a warning signal of collapse isn&amp;rsquo;t about detecting that a system is non-stationary, but more specifically, that the system is about to do something sudden. The classic saddle-node bifurcation example results in a picture like this:
A visible steady decrease interrupted by a sudden jump. The goal is to distinguish this from the case of a steady decrease that involves no loss of stability &amp;ndash; such as would be created by continually lowering the carrying capacity of logistic-model system at a linear rate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/10/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/21/</guid>
      <description>Trying to select clear examples of sufficient and sufficient power in detecting warning signals. Addressing a couple side issues today as well:
 Proper handling of trends
 Best model for eigenvalue change
  Computed an example with steeper nonlinearity to compare rate of change in lambda. Here&amp;rsquo;s an example with Hill coefficient of 5 (see code for details). Note that the plot simply shows whichever root the numerical algorithm converges to at the time, should modify to express all roots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Warning Signals, power, etc</title>
      <link>/2010/10/21/spatial-warning-signals-power-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/21/spatial-warning-signals-power-etc/</guid>
      <description>Noam gave an interesting presentation in our lab today, prompted me to do a little experimentation. Weakening stability across a set of coupled patches should result in increased autocorrelation. Decided to test this with a little visualization with help of a quick R script. Time progresses across the x-axis, 1-D space (on S1) across the y-axis. Each patch suffers a slow loss of stability, resulting in a clearly visible increase in autocorrelation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/10/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/20/</guid>
      <description>Adaptive dynamics is a set of recently developed techniques for understanding phenotypic evolution, using a dynamical systems approach to concepts from evolutionary game theory. In contrast to population genetics, this approach tends to explore richer ecological interactions and simpler genetic assumptions, with significant controversy. My own work has focused on a particular element of the theory known as the canonical equation, a macroscopic equation describing the deterministic rate of evolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ecology Abstract</title>
      <link>/2010/10/20/ecology-abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/20/ecology-abstract/</guid>
      <description>Ecological population sizes fluctuate not only in response to environmental fluctuations but because of the stochastic nature of natural births and deaths. While in very large populations these fluctuations have negligible impact, ecology rarely obliges us by satisfying this limit. Age and stage structure in populations serve to amplify the effect, where the fate of the population is determined by a smaller subset of, say, the fecund adults alone. Demographic noise is probably responsible for the ultimate extinction of many populations once reduced to a small size.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab Notebooks</title>
      <link>/2010/09/07/lab-notebooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2010 08:23:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/07/lab-notebooks/</guid>
      <description>I strive for a transparent and reproducible research process. My lab notebooks are kept on an open wiki (via OpenWetWare). I curate the literature I read into several public lists (Mendeley), maintain my research source code and simulations on a collective database for open source development (Github), and am active on academic forums and mailing lists. These web-based tools make a largely automated, interlinked archive of my work I can search, update and share easily.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution Research Abstract</title>
      <link>/2010/09/04/hello-world-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2010 16:51:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/04/hello-world-2/</guid>
      <description>Comparative methods in evolutionary biology use phylogenetic trees to explore the origins and maintenance of biodiversity. I develop methods to extend the kinds of questions we can ask and also to test the statistical limits of our ability to make evolutionary inferences through such a periscope into the past. I am particularly interested in detecting evolutionary regime shifts &amp;ndash; locations in evolutionary history where the governing rules or parameters shift suddenly &amp;ndash; as well as more general questions of model choice, informativeness &amp;amp; identifiability in phylogenetic inference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPB thesis proposal</title>
      <link>/2010/01/10/cpb-thesis-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2010 14:07:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/01/10/cpb-thesis-proposal/</guid>
      <description>In the spirit of archiving work in the lab notebook, this was my PhD dissertation proposal, a requirement to advance to candidacy submitted before our oral defense in the second or third year. Following some excellent advice, this is focused more narrowly than my actual dissertation. As a historical note, I started keeping an open lab notebook the month following this, on OpenWetWare (so work leading up to this isn&amp;rsquo;t archived, though admittedly first two years were largely coursework).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description> Embedded versions of my summary sheets for the Population Biology graduate group core course, organized by faculty member&amp;rsquo;s section.
Schreiber: Single species population dynamics Schoener: multispecies population dynamics Stachowicz: Community ecology Sih: Animal behavior Turelli: Population genetics and speciation Wainwright: macroevolution and comparative phylogenetics </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Clash of Old and New Today was my day to facilitate for a graduate student discussion seminar. The seminar is well attended by quite a handful of faculty and post-docs, some thirty people. The discussion is almost always dominated by a few faculty, which is a great source of information but offers little opportunity for students to ask questions or wrestle with ideas themselves. To get at this, I tried breaking the class into small groups for the first half and passing out different sets of discussion questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Early Warning Signals to Regime Shifts Seminar  I was just responsible for covering a relatively technical paper on the idea of detecting early warning signals to regime shifts. This is a class of about 10 people. First half we took turns on the board, relying entirely on graphical analysis, and going from a birth death model through stability analysis to illustrate bi-stability to the bifurcation diagram and the energy landscape representation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Regime Shifts Seminar take two  Today I was again up for the regime shifts class to cover the details Alan&amp;rsquo;s Ecology Letters paper. Board lecture style on content I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable with, so enjoyable for me but hardly much of an experiment in effective teaching. Still, something that can be done well or poorly, so I think today went well. Began with individuals at the board to review the four principle figures from the previous class &amp;ndash; birth rates and death rates, difference in rates, the bifurcation diagram and the potential landscape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Faculty Mentoring Faculty Presentation &amp;ldquo;Short Cuts to Excellent Teaching: A Primer&amp;rdquo;  by James Shaffrath, from Exercise Biology, The Department of Neurobiology, Physiology and Behavior  Just saw this presentation in the Faculty Mentoring Faculty program. Good program, though pretty basic, not really touching on peer learning but focusing on lecture content and style. Things like rolling lexicon (using both jargon and simple phrases), being present, being engaging. The broad introduction was definitely the best part, and an inspiring view about the role of education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>GTC Session: Student Centered Learning: Successes, Failures and Strategies  Gabrielle and I facilitated a GTC section on Student-Centered learning. Details in the GTC blog post. Small group of about a dozen of us, still worked to break into four groups for the discussion section. Overall went very well, don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of comments to add about the experience or things I&amp;rsquo;d do differently. Did get some positive feedback and comments that we could have used much more time to explore these ideas!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>1-2pm
 Discussion of reasons early warning signals fail   Insufficient signal-to-noise ratio for early warning Ensemble vs time average &amp;ndash; satisfying ergodicity assumption? Role of bifurcation type. existing literature focuses mostly on 1D saddle node. Role of chaos (certainly frustrates warning signals, but not required).   How general are warning signals? Normal forms of bifurcations. Fitting a good model vs. general warning signals. Problem of extrapolation. Classification scheme of warning signals &amp;ndash; TREE paper(?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Evolution of Mimicry &amp;amp; Levels of Selection  Today my turn to help facilitate in Begun&amp;rsquo;s Monte Carlo on designing a course on evolution for non-majors. Worked with Elizabeth on an interactive case study teaching levels of selection through the example of mimicry in butterflies. Following a brief introduction, we gave a pilot run of a hands-on activity to explore population dynamics in a predator-control-model-mimic (jay-cabbage-monarch-viceroy) system. Here&amp;rsquo;s the description.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Research Labrid Paper Outline Biology Letters format, 2500 words, 2 figures.
Fig 1?
Fig 2?
 Title: Phylogenetic Evidence for Multiple Morphological Niches in Coral Reef Fish Summary (&amp;lt; 200 words)
 We present phylogenetic evidence for two distinct evolutionary optima in the fin morphology of Labrid Fish.  Keywords: Evolution, Phylogenetics, Comparative Methods, Labrids, Multiple Niches
 Introduction
 Labrid Fin Morphology Is clustering in Trait space evidence of Selection or Phylogenetic Inertia?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Research  Wrote summary function using bootstrap confidence intervals for the bootstraps of the likelihoods directly. On interpreting the bootstraps of likelihoods directly:   The extent to which the distributions themselves are distinct provides an indication of the ability to distinguish between models on the given phylogenetic tree and the actual data. For instance, if the tree was a star tree and the data produced by either BM or OU1, then all distributions would fall on top of one another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Notes potentially for my EDG talk.
&amp;ldquo;Keeping Up&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a talk to EDG? Science is growing. Fast. Number of papers published. Genomes on Genbank. Software on CRAN. Everyone&amp;rsquo;s felt the pressure. So what do we do? Keeping with tradition, I&amp;rsquo;ll present my own work in developing comparative phylogenetic methods to identify niche differentiation in Labrid fish. I will try and use this context to pose the question &amp;ndash; what do we do about this information explosion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Misc / Notes  Starting to prepare for GTC sections  Technology and Education  Open courses backed by learning research: Carnegie Mellon Wallwisher online notice board example Open education featured in NY Times  Assessment  XP instead of grades? Lee Sheldon system another Sheldon method post</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>GTC: Assessment  Today I&amp;rsquo;m facilitating the GTC session discussing Assessment. Here&amp;rsquo;s our VUE map of the activity.  
What better way to begin a discussion about assessment than with an assessment? We began with a somewhat tongue-in-cheek quiz about the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to conduct an assessment, modelling some common faults in poor assessments while also serving as a brainstorm to get some ideas out there. We presented some background theory on assessment, drawing from the excellent text: Handelsman, J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Graduate Teaching Community &amp;ndash; reflections on teaching Haven&amp;rsquo;t made a lot of entries in this notebook as I&amp;rsquo;m not teaching regularly at the moment, though am still attending meetings of the Graduate Teaching Community, a record of which can be found on our GTC blog. But today in GTC we are thinking about reflections on teaching, and starting with a little bit of journaling, so this seemed like a good place to do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description> Working examples  kendall.R example of kendall&amp;rsquo;s correlation test on standard warning signal indicator being misleading.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Actually starting at Arkin Lab</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/actually-starting-at-arkin-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/actually-starting-at-arkin-lab/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with M. Samoilov  Kurtz Theorems: two limits, timescale and system size, often taken in the wrong order in practice. Einstein-Smoluchowski debate regarding Langevin correspondence to Ito vs Statonvich representations resolved: [theorem]. (Statonvich is the more natural interpretation of the way in which we measure data to compare to Langevin. Of course Ito and Stratonvich can be mapped back and forth anyway). Of course this difference doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, and nothing goes wrong / no stochastic surprises if dynamics are linear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Wrapping up paper on waiting time to branching in adaptive dynamics. Cleaning up code from summer. Now in a local git repository in adaptiveDynamics/code Moved ensemble parallelization to higher level, so parallelization can be performed in R or C. Adding documentation  Current status  Calculates the waiting time to complete phase 1, phase 2, and phase 3 successfully from individual-based simulation.  Phase 1 ~ Completed when 2 branches exist over threshold Phase 2 ~ Completed when a third population has established over threshold exterior to a stable pair Phase 3 ~ Completed when two populations over threshold are separated in traitspace by more than finishline units</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>compiling with R and C and parallel computing  Problem: cannot get the R code to take advantage of parallelization via openMP.
 Solution:
  C++ file mangles names in .so, changing the .C call. to get the object name:
objdump -x file.so  Carl Boettiger 03:01, 25 May 2010 (EDT): More standard solution: enclose cpp code in
 extern C {  
 Problem: Trouble getting R to export the C library to all nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Computing Challenges  10 - 1p Adding solutions to yesterday&amp;rsquo;s puzzles, see Yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Entry The random number generator solution is imperfect, as it limits the total number of seeds to 1e9 since coercing to an integer will create NAs with larger numbers.  
 seeds &amp;lt;- 1e9*runif(reps) out &amp;lt;- sfSapply(1:reps, function(i){ branch_simulation(seed=seeds[i]) })  Analytic Solutions Git Log  Created commit da58a6e: random number seeds now set to avoid parallel cores running with same seed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Matching theoretical approximations to simulation:
 Implemented the first analytic approximation, calculating the waiting time to complete phase 1. Established dimophisms are often still lost, hence the first successful completion of phase 1 (dimorphic population in coexistence region with each above threshold size) doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the time of the last completion of phase 1. Phase 2, an established third population seems to happen soon after the last successful phase 1, giving the illusion this step is easy rather than the reality that this process requires fast traversal to persist past the coexistence time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Manuscript writing.  Phylogenetics Submitted Lightning talk to iEvoBio
PDG group will be discussing
 Rabosky DL and Lovette IJ. .&amp;rdquo;) pmid:18611849. PubMed HubMed [1]  tomorrow, along with critique and response.
 Waiting to hear back from Peter on manuscript. Should follow up with Ralph on likelihood ratio discussion with Ethan. Transcluding exploratory work on primate phylogeny data:  Embedded:

Primate Phylogeny Carl Boettiger 00:37, 30 April 2010 (EDT):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Modified code phase definitions: phasetime[0] is the first time dimorphism is established. Dimorphism may be lost and restablished, last (most recent) time it establishes is phasetime1. Other times are still the most recent time at which the phase was accomplished.
 Fiddling with analytic approximations. These shouldn&amp;rsquo;t integrate to evaluate at each value, but should be done in a fully discretized system. Prototyping in R, the discrete version is probably fast enough to handle in scripted code alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Working on simulation based approach to summarize distribution of waiting times across different phases. What to do about zeros in phase two (when first dimorphism survives long enough to be invaded&amp;hellip;) Quantify number/distribution of failed attempts at each phase? How to represent these distributions across a parameter space in sigma_c, sigma_k, sigma_mu, and mu?  library(BranchingTime) sim &amp;lt;- branching_time(rep=1000, cpu=8) save(file = &amp;quot;run1.Rdat&amp;quot;) pdf(&amp;quot;distribution.pdf&amp;quot;) m &amp;lt;- max(sim$data) plot(density(sim$data[1,]), xlim = c(0,m), col=&amp;quot;black&amp;quot; ) lines(density(sim$data[2,] ), col = &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;) lines(density(sim$data[3,] ), col = &amp;quot;green&amp;quot;) lines(density(sim$data[4,] ), col = &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;) legend(&#39;topright&#39;, c(&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;2&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;3&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;4&amp;quot;), col=c(&amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;green&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;), pch = 15) dev.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Wide gap, flat landscape  Waiting times on a flatter landscape: sigma_c ~ sigma_k. Waiting times are dominated by the number of times phase 3 collapses: the established invader in a dimorphic population (right panels). Collapse of phase 2: collapse of the dimorphism before third population can establish is much rarer (about an order of magnitude).   from the run3 dataset, with parameters.  Narrower gap, steeper landscape  with sigma_c &amp;lt;&amp;lt; sigma_k, branching is easy, neither phase is particularly limiting, though single collapses from both phases are very common.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Public code hosting  Project code now available through Github. Advantages to public hosting: Replication of adaptive dynamics simulations can be difficult, particularly in matching various nuisance parameters. While there is certainly much pedagogical value in individual researchers implementing their own simulations, verification and reproducibility of scientific results would be greatly facilitated by adapting an accepted open source code base and adding branches, etc. Researchers could much more immediately benefit from the work of their colleagues and spend more time implementing novel research and less reproducing it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Adding demos directory for the simulations to create the figures in User:Carl Boettiger/Notebook/Comparative Phylogenetics/2010/05/03 and User:Carl Boettiger/Notebook/Comparative Phylogenetics/2010/05/04 Updating the contour plot figure as per suggestions by Rupert and Ulf:  Branching times, original figure
 use more points for the simulation, and don&amp;rsquo;t put them on a regular grid, but maybe draw them from a uniform distribution, so as not to create spurious impressions of symmetry. You could then maybe also use the tripack package to draw colored Voronoi cells instead of same-sized symbols.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Created plotting functions for:   waiting time distribution by phase, (cumulative and difference), distribution of number of failures before invasion of dimophism can occur and after it has occurred (indicating if mutational rate is more limiting or mutational step size (selection gradient). Adding to the pairwise invasibility plot the locations where dimorphism collapses, color coded by the time of collapse.  Exploring branching time distributions in different regimes by phase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Wrote the code for a better interface to simulate coexistence times and creating contour plots from the results.  see code</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Simulation Results (code)  Analytics (Analytics code)
Notebooks and files Looking at a better way to get figures into my online notebook. I often run simulations that generate figures which I look at, make some adjustments to the code based on the figure, and then delete or overwrite the figure without uploading it to my notebook, because it isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;finished&amp;rdquo; and uploading takes a lot of clicks, particularly when the code generates 36 figures in a run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics Updates</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics-updates/</guid>
      <description>The numerical coexistence time simulations are still running, (Server rest brought down these runs two weeks ago, and they take a few weeks to do all the replicates) meanwhile here are the rest of the analytic set (and one simulation that finished). See code for parameters etc. (Below in frame)


EVE Seminar: Brad Shaffer A rather good talk on the California Tiger salamander, emphasizing intersection of ecological and evolutionary investigation in a conservation, management-oriented context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</guid>
      <description>From 03/31, see below for more!
Outline Title
On the ability to detect leading indicators of catastrophe in unreplicated time series
Introduction Background on Warning Signals
 literature Saddle Node bifurcation Detecting decreasing stabilization &amp;ndash; gradual vs changepoint estimation  Reasons detection can fail:
 Ergodicity: ensembles vs single instances Sufficient statistical power Appropriate dynamics  Methods
 Defining an indicator &amp;ndash; significant Kendall rank correlation coefficient τ as in doi:10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Goals next week: Bob &amp;amp; Brian beetle data: what an analysis would be with complete stochastic description. Compare models with different  Full model: Parameter list from current code:
/* Biological Parameters. eggs and pupa can get canibalized */ double b = 5; /* Birth rate (per day) */ double u_egg = 0, u_larva = 0.001, u_pupa = 0, u_adult = 0.003; /* Mortality rate (per day) */ double a_egg = 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Updates  Likelihood calculation for beetle model. Proposed model and calculations Linear parameter change for warning signal model. Results in a few test cases. Likelihood methods within SDE framework, an outline of methods. Subtle problems, good approximations, powerful approaches.  
Questions  LPA vs ELLPA model Defining state space in individual-based model vs stage based model, setting initial conditions? Conclusion: Means non-Markovian system, so likelihood isn&amp;rsquo;t determined in one step approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual Progress Report</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow will be meeting with my dissertation committee: Alan Hastings, Peter Wainwright, and Brian Moore. This provides a good opportunity to summarize the status of my current projects and my principle accomplishments for the year. Will try a tex&amp;rsquo;d document as I&amp;rsquo;ve done in previous years but here&amp;rsquo;s for some preliminary brainstorming.
 Summary: In the past year, I&amp;rsquo;ve published one paper, given 4 talks (CPB, NIMBioS, Berkeley, IIASA), read 144+ articles and wrote 9000+ lines of code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Batch Data</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/batch-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/batch-data/</guid>
      <description>Some of the nexus files don&amp;rsquo;t seem to read into R. Opening and saving the file in figtree solves this.  Data Sets Labrid traits &amp;ndash;Carl Boettiger 00:52, 11 August 2010 (EDT) Note: labels on parameter bootstrap distributions have reversed wrasses and parrotfish. I&amp;rsquo;ve updated the software so that the plotting function takes care of the labeling automatically (when these were made it had to be added manually, while the automation of the data conversions and the painting by clade reversed the label assignments).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beetle dynamics exploration &amp; adjustments</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/beetle-dynamics-exploration--adjustments/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/beetle-dynamics-exploration--adjustments/</guid>
      <description>Adjusted individual based Crowley model to follow same parameterization as the macroscopic model. IBM rules had divided b and c by K in the dynamics while the macroscopic was just using rescaled dynamical rates. Now both use the rescaled rates as parameter values while the equations match.
 Variation in the Crowley model agrees between individual-based simulation and the equations.
  Code troubleshooting  openmp private declarations perform allocs without frees!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beetles workshop Day 2</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/beetles-workshop-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/beetles-workshop-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Goals  van Kampen expansion of LPA model, maximize noise in L while keeping A robust?   Indiv. heterogeneity issue: dividing larval class into a smaller, highly-cannibal and remainder of more weakly cannibalistic. Pulse dynamics &amp;ndash; interspike interval, magnitude?  Potential Data  1995 Dennis et al. &amp;ndash; 5 replicate populations (2-cycle dataset), 5 age-cycles. eight-year chaotic time series Strawbridge daily samples (single replicate), occasional disease in lines though.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Picture Comparative Phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/big-picture-comparative-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/big-picture-comparative-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>A Task View on Phylogenetic Comparative Methods (in R on CRAN) has been released today, maintained by Brian O&amp;rsquo;Meara. Quite thorough and concise.
 Follow-up discussion on:
 List is useful, but would be nice to be able to expand / collapse the list to see more / less details about the functions available. More detail makes it harder to maintain, perhaps get the developers involved? List is also quite provocative source to realize what&amp;rsquo;s missing (there&amp;rsquo;s no way to estimate ancestral states under OU using existing software?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Phylogenetics Workshop Day 1</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Lecture notes for the phyolgenetics workshop. These are taken in real time, so may contain errors. I&amp;rsquo;ll see if I keep this up throughout the course. See course website.
Huelsenbeck 9a-11a
 Parameters θ Observation X p(X | θ) is known as the likelihood. Adjust parameter to maximize likelihood. Coin toss example  θ = prob of heads on a single toss of a coin, X is # of heads observed on n tosses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Phylogenetics Workshop Day 2</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Marine lab researchers are back, and network speeds have just about given up (down to bytes/s). This post is composed offline and will be uploaded to the notebook. Details are well logged on the Bodgea Phylogenetics Wiki so these are reasonably sketchy with my comments.
My Updates to Bodega Phylogenetics Wiki Made several contributions to the Bodega Phylogenetics Wiki today:
 User page Phylogenetics on Linux Becoming a Programmer Edits on Advice for Aspiring Phylogeneticists  Today&amp;rsquo;s agenda  BEAST continued.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Phylogenetics Workshop Day 3</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-3/</guid>
      <description>Rich Glor, Character Evolution Official slides and tutorial
 Weakness of ancestral state reconstruction
 Cunningham 1999 Losos 1999  Testing hypotheses with ancestral reconstruction
 Parsimony Farris method. Downward/upward pass. Gives a maximum parsimony reconstruction. May miss other ones. Apparently this Parsimony analysis can be done for continuous traits as well, needs a measure of distance Likelihood Pagel 1994 Schluter 1997   R tutorial (see anolis_cheat.R)
 Discrete trait ancestral state reconstruction</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Workshop Day 4</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bodega-workshop-day-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bodega-workshop-day-4/</guid>
      <description>Morphological Evolution Day:
 Peter Wainwright Sam Price Johnathan Eisen  We have the afternoon session off for field trips and research.

Peter Wainwright, Comparative Analysis of Morphological Diversity  Fantastic diversity in morphology, corresponds to niche! But morphological diversity isn&amp;rsquo;t evenly distributed across tree of life. (See slides, parallels Peter&amp;rsquo;s section on core and gives the best biological coverage we&amp;rsquo;ve had this week).  What changes morphological diversification rate</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Workshop Presentations</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bodega-workshop-presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bodega-workshop-presentations/</guid>
      <description>Final day of Bodega Phylogenetics workshop: a full day of student presentations. (High resolution images for the trees available by clicking on them)
Principle figures from my investigation of the Labrid data. While morphospace doesn&amp;rsquo;t present an obvious clustering, it can be effectively divided by my maximum likelihood partitioning scheme on fin angle. A smoothed density plot of fin angle alone reveals two identifiable modes in the traitspace.
Based on the discretized partition, ancestral states are reconstructed under both the equal rates and independent rates model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping Likelihood ratios</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bootstrapping-likelihood-ratios/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bootstrapping-likelihood-ratios/</guid>
      <description>Bootstraps of the likelihood ratio, holding the parameters fixed, finally completed.  Anoles: Summary Anoles table:
&amp;gt; summary(anoles_boots) [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4] [,5] [1,] 0.500000000 0.981399498 0.26514573 0.06668672 0.018154938 [2,] 0.009580545 0.500000000 0.15610274 0.04819938 0.011616566 [3,] 0.039233893 0.075349644 0.50000000 0.05699877 0.005443493 [4,] 0.004211230 0.004592917 0.01389950 0.50000000 0.006648916 [5,] 0.173457542 0.198303402 0.38893099 0.33891430 0.500000000 &amp;gt;  Labrids: &amp;gt; summary(labrid_boots) [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4] [1,] 0.5000000 6.036842e-05 0.0000000 0.0 [2,] 0.5424613 5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping the independent alpha-sigma models</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bootstrapping-the-independent-alpha-sigma-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bootstrapping-the-independent-alpha-sigma-models/</guid>
      <description>I compare in a robust framework the likelihood that species mean trait values are generated by Brownian motion, a single peak OU model, or a model with different regimes (postulated in the literature) in which the selective strength (alpha) and diversification rate (sigma) are fixed across the entire tree or allowed to vary by selective regime. (Regimes are defined as branches with different values for the selective optimum).
The parametric bootstrap of the likelihood ratio statistic provides a rigorous way to quantify the probability that the model choice is correct: the probability that the data was produced by the test model vs the null model is assured by the Neyman-Pearson lemma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bug fixed!</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/bug-fixed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/bug-fixed/</guid>
      <description>Wasn&amp;rsquo;t taking the Jacobian of the transition terms. Fixes the unstable behavior and disagreement between simulations and theory. Other note: the &amp;ldquo;hastings.c&amp;rdquo; model can trivially be obtained from the standard crowley-form metapopulation model by taking b_1 = 0.  For the crowley class of models at least, seems that while the two-step vs one-step involved different dynamics, this difference exists only in transients while equilbrium covariances agree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference Day 2</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/csgf-conference-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/csgf-conference-day-2/</guid>
      <description>DoE CSGF Conference, Day 2
Conference Agenda

Fellows Poster Session Photo credit Michelle King, Krell Institute. Others in the photo are: Devin Matthews, University of Texas at Austin, DOE CSGF fellow (dark blue CSGF shirt) and Jeff Lewandowski, Computational Science and Discovery Magazine.


Presented my poster which qualified as a finalist in the competition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference Thursday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/csgf-conference-thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/csgf-conference-thursday/</guid>
      <description>Conference Agenda</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference- HPC Workshop</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/csgf-conference--hpc-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/csgf-conference--hpc-workshop/</guid>
      <description>I found the breakout sessions in the afternoon particularly fascinating for their paradigm-breaking look into the future of high performance computing. While FLOPS become free, huge scale and ultra-low-power devices (little voltage difference to identify bits) make error handling a topic of major concern, and the idea of &amp;ldquo;wasting&amp;rdquo; processors to perform redundant calculations to avoid errors becomes quite serious. Other ideas, like moving computation around the memory instead of the reverse, the rise of large data and questioning the role of GPU and other novel architecture was also an important theme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference- Tuesday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/csgf-conference--tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/csgf-conference--tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Conference Agenda

HPC Survey Results Presented the results of my survey of the computational habits and tools of CSGF fellows and alumni. See my Survey summary. Slides, data, etc available on my github repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Survey</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/csgf-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/csgf-survey/</guid>
      <description>Wrote survey. Getting feedback and will send out this week.  previous comments
Wiki Tricks Exploring use of mvs to download and upload entries from openwetware. The mediawiki client is easy to install as described in the link. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have a tool to grab everything in my Notebook namespace, but with a little bash script I can grab all the entries in a particular notebook:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cetartiodactyle data</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/cetartiodactyle-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/cetartiodactyle-data/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the cetartiodactyle data (unreleased) Nelder-Mead fails to converge or improve upon the hansen model. Likelihood scores differ little:  &amp;gt; bm@loglik [1] -362.6228 &amp;gt; ou1@loglik [1] -364.9039 &amp;gt; ws1$loglik [1] -362.7616 &amp;gt; ou2@loglik [1] -361.6976 &amp;gt; ws2$loglik [1] -361.2542  See Cetaceans code.

Fig. 1 The Brownian Motion model is preferred to the OU.1 model (left). Two separate optima are supported over a single optima (right).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code Development for Exploring Regimes Shifts</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/code-development-for-exploring-regimes-shifts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/code-development-for-exploring-regimes-shifts/</guid>
      <description>Just committed changes to the google project. warning_signals.c now provides a fully functional, ensemble enabled simulation written with functional API for general Gillespie simulations (at last! I&amp;rsquo;ve come quite a way in my C coding from those early Gillespie simulations for adaptive dynamics two years ago). Still need to pull the API out of the single file. Doxygen-compatible literate programming included, but needs significant expansion before it can really be used effectively as an API for other users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Phylogenetics Talk</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/comparative-phylogenetics-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/comparative-phylogenetics-talk/</guid>
      <description>Practice talk in Wainwright lab meeting next Weds. 12 minutes.
 Introduce question: Inferring the number of regimes Context relative to existing methods Statistical challenges &amp;ndash; model-dependent phylogenetic signal problem Labrid example  Frameworks for approaching regimes question  wrightscape phylogenetically corrected clustering
 speed/feasibility concerns, rate limiting steps.
 model realism / representation concerns
 statistical concerns
  Returning to Wrightscape approach Haven&amp;rsquo;t worked on the full problem of inferring multiple peaks directly from comparative data using the joint probability calculation since the beginning of this notebook, so about time to return to the direct problem and compare with the more heuristic approach of &amp;ldquo;phylogenetically corrected clustering&amp;rdquo; and also synthesize the work on uncertainty which has been a dominate theme thus far (add category label for this group!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing to Analytic Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/comparing-to-analytic-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/comparing-to-analytic-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Goal for today: implement analytic calculations for warning signals.
 10am-12pm  Abstraction/functionalizing code.
 4pm-7pm  Implement GSL ode solvers for linear noise approximation:
Recall our dynamics are d(n) = *e*n + a
and defining the jump moments (van Kampen) α~1~(n) = b(n) − d(n)
α~2~(n) = b(n) + d(n)

recall that we have a linear Fokker-Planck equation whose solution is Gaussian and specified by the first two moments:  These are implemented in code using GSL ode library.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/computing/</guid>
      <description>Exploring parallel computing options. OpenMP for distributed memory applications. learning git &amp;ndash; need to get used to the branch and merge, install on one.  Research The failure of the Anoles data set to robustly select the more common model can easily be explained by the likelihood distribution: Not surprising since this dataset consists of only 23 taxa. The Labrid tree of 114 taxa clearly resolves the difference between the different models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conference call w- Bob and Brett</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/conference-call-w--bob-and-brett/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/conference-call-w--bob-and-brett/</guid>
      <description>So far no large noise in larval class alone, several potential mechanisms we may have missed so far:  Getting large noise in larva  Noise from egg class (due to nonlinear dynamics) Nonlinearity in larval class due to large larva eating smaller ones Unknown effect of more realistic aging/stage transitions. Long transients? &amp;ndash; Experiments start with larva, pupa, adults to speed up transient period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Format functions</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/data-format-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/data-format-functions/</guid>
      <description>Spent much of the day trying to code an intelligent data-preprocessing function. Seems to mostly be working now, see github for details. Testing on a variety of datasets.
 Currently the function assumes paintings can be specified by common ancestors of a set of tips, assumes non-overlapping clades. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t error-check for this either.
 should also have more output processing functions, particularly to return a &amp;ldquo;phylo&amp;rdquo; object together with paintings (see earlier existing code in my Comparative-Phylogenetics repository).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demographic Noise</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/demographic-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/demographic-noise/</guid>
      <description>Crowley Model  Exploring the extent to which demographic stochasticity in a key class can reverberate through the entire population dynamics. Starting with a simple test case of a modified Crowley model:   Model is implemented on a branch of the warningSignals package. Model in crowley.c, Depends on modified gillespie.c library in this package. Branching necessary as implementation simplifies the gillespie function dependencies, but these changes would break compatibility with warning_signals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective warning signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/effective-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/effective-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Predicting variance of variance by direct calculation &amp;ndash; still need to crunch some math for the expected convergence.
 Still, the approach should be able to do more than describe single points as unexpected deviates. Still need to address gradual change vs change point analysis. Essentially the same as the phyolgenentic problem &amp;ndash; one rate vs two rates. Model selection approaches? So far theory is essentially built on a model selection between linear models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble simulations of beetle dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ensemble-simulations-of-beetle-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ensemble-simulations-of-beetle-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>code Fig 1
code Fig 2
code Fig 3
Exploring full ensemble simulations of beetle dynamics. Linear noise approximations (Fig 2) show divergent noise under oscillating conditions (Fig 2 lower panel), though this may be an artifact of the approximation, which applies only for finite time calculations.

Note that mean dynamics agree, and oscillations damp out, Fig 1 simulation means (circles) fall exactly on predicted lines. Variance dynamics do not agree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/entry-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/entry-title/</guid>
      <description>Insert content here&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/entry-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/entry-title/</guid>
      <description>Insert content here&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/entry-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/entry-title/</guid>
      <description>OWW was down, notebook embedded from springnote:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/entry-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/entry-title/</guid>
      <description>Automated scripts for image uploads. Tag-based generation of a slideshow:


Running the script:
 ./flickr_slideshow *.png  Creates the html code that can be embedded into the notebook for a slideshow those images. Images only get the date-time tag as a unique id.


This one uses the mediawiki plugin. More formatting options could be incorporated of course. (Creates the thumbnail images down the right-hand side).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2010</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/evolution-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/evolution-2010/</guid>
      <description>Carl Boettiger A new phylogenetic comparative method: detecting niches and transitions with continuous characters  My slides:
A new phylogenetic comparative method: detecting niches and transitions with continuous characters
View more presentations from cboettig.
 Joe Felsenstein A comparative method for discrete and continuous characters using the threshold model
 Lynsey McInnes: Deep-time changes to equilibrium diversity &amp;ndash; a simulation study of th power to detect rule changes from reconstructed phylogenies</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2010 Day 2</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/evolution-2010-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/evolution-2010-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Clay Cressler : Can you trust evolutionary parameters estimated by complex phylogenetic comparative methods? A simulation study with OUCH
 Jeet Sukumaran (Mark Holder lab) Performance and robustness of phylogeographic analytical studies
  Tests common macroscopic models of inferring population structure (i.e. via coalescent) an individual based simulation model.
 Graham Slater, Luke Harmon, Liam Revell, Marc Suchard, Mike Alfaro. Estimating rates of phenotypic evolution and speciation from incomplete trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2010 Day 3</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/evolution-2010-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/evolution-2010-day-3/</guid>
      <description>Chris Martin: Trophic innovation drives exceptional rates of morphological diversification in two adaptive radiations of Cyprinodon pupfishes  Fantastic story of exceptional rates of evolution and trophic novelty in two tropical lakes. (8:45, Adaptation 9, talk 097002)
 David Plachetzki: Deep homology and the evolution of animal senses: insights from Cnidaria  Cnidarians have homologous proteins to opsins and taste receptors!
 Jeremy Yoder: Coevolution and gene flow in obligate pollination mutualism  Two species of joshua tree each with its own pollinator yucca moth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary Regime Shift examples</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/evolutionary-regime-shift-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/evolutionary-regime-shift-examples/</guid>
      <description>Time to get more data and examples to start testing methods, particularly for cases in where regime shifts are hypothesized by painting a tree. Starting a Mendeley public collection for the literature in Web of Science that actually applies either the OUCH or Brownie framework to identify shifts in rates of continuous trait evolution.
Research collected using Mendeley

now I&amp;rsquo;ll have to see how hard it is to obtain both the trees and trait data&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Difficulties with Existing Methods</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods/</guid>
      <description>Model choice plays an increasingly dominant role in comparative phylogenetics. The software OUCH of Butler and King (2004) is built around the model comparison framework and returns a variety of information criteria for choosing between different models fitted to the tree.
 I&amp;rsquo;ve written a short R script to explore how robust these inferences are, and the results are rather surprising. None of the inferences holds up to the classical P value standard of 95% probability of being right, and the inference can be wrong more often than it is right &amp;ndash; a coin flip out-performs the model choice method based on these information criteria in certain cases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Difficulties with Existing Methods continued</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods-continued/</guid>
      <description>Working on manuscript for this today, hope to have a draft soon.
 Just added a basic example using a star-burst tree to illustrate the challenges associated with this kind of model choice inference.
 Sent draft to Brian and Peter, and Wainwright lab.
 Still needs a figure explaining the BM, OU(1) and OU(LP) models for those not familiar with Butler and King 2004 paper, general polishing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Follow-up on Parametric Bootstrapping</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/follow-up-on-parametric-bootstrapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/follow-up-on-parametric-bootstrapping/</guid>
      <description>Continuing on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s discussion of parametric boostrapping implementation. Peter sent some very helpful comments and agreed to having them here for reference; I&amp;rsquo;ve added some links.  &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve read up a bit on the bootstrap just now. First off, although parametric and nonparametric bootstrapping has always seemed very different to me, they fit in the same natural framework. The general idea is that in reality, there&amp;rsquo;s some real parameters x and some probability distribution P that&amp;rsquo;s given us some data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/friday/</guid>
      <description>Not much chance for progress.
 11-noon (I was interviewed by Science Careers reporter). noon-1 Lunch w/ John Huelsenbeck. Good perspective on having formula representation of models rather than on/off switch for parameters! Will have to implement eventually in the phylogenetics project. 1-1:30 Wainwrighters lunch meeting. 1:30-3:30 prep Monte Carlo for teaching non-majors evolution course &amp;ndash; case study on mimicry and levels of selection. Presenting Monday, we&amp;rsquo;ll see how it goes in [User:Carl_Boettiger/Notebook/Teaching] 4-6 Phylogenetics discussion group (followed by CPB happy hour = more phylogenetics discussion).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/friday/</guid>
      <description>11a Sebastian Meeting (see Stochastic Population Dynamics Notebook)
12p - 1p
 Lunch talk in joint lab group (Schreiber Coop Moore Rannala Eisen) on coalescents for wARG. Remember to check out kcachegrind as interface to valgrind and profiler, and also mauve as a dynamic sequence alignment display tool.  Comparative Phylogenetics Discussion group 4-5p. Discussing:
 Van Bocxlaer I, Loader SP, Roelants K, Biju SD, Menegon M, and Bossuyt F.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gamma Waiting times on individual level</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/gamma-waiting-times-on-individual-level/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/gamma-waiting-times-on-individual-level/</guid>
      <description>Wrote the proper record structure into C code to handle reporting to R, including ensemble data. Wrote the R interface to the dynamics. Needs exploration.  Version-stable code for parameters. Run using defaults, graph as:
png(&amp;quot;ibm_gamma.png&amp;quot;) o &amp;lt;- gamma_beetles_ibm() plot(o$times, o$mv[[1,1]], type=&#39;l&#39;, col=&amp;quot;yellow&amp;quot;) lines(o$times, o$mv[[1,2]], col=&amp;quot;yellowgreen&amp;quot;) lines(o$times, o$mv[[1,3]], col=&amp;quot;lightgreen&amp;quot;) lines(o$times, o$mv[[1,4]], col=&amp;quot;darkgreen&amp;quot;) dev.off() o$parameters b ue ul up ua ae al ap cle cap 5.000 0.000 0.001 0.000 0.010 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>General matrix form and correcting equations</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/general-matrix-form-and-correcting-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/general-matrix-form-and-correcting-equations/</guid>
      <description>Pursuing a matrix form, seems I had missed some terms in the covariance equations Friday, which are suggested by the nice symmetry of this representation: (sometimes chalk and a camera are faster than tex).
This suggests the general form looks like
*dM* = *JM* + (*J*M)^T^ + g
Where M is the covariance matrix and J the Jacobian of f as before. dM is the matrix of derivative terms, though clearly not a rigorous notation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the multi-type OU process- continued</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/generalizing-the-multi-type-ou-process--continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/generalizing-the-multi-type-ou-process--continued/</guid>
      <description>Efficiency updates:
 As expected, calculating the last common ancestor on the fly was responsible for a significant (&amp;gt;50%) fraction of the computational effort, so it&amp;rsquo;s worth calculating this once for the tree and storing the information. Current profiling table:   % cumulative self self total time seconds seconds calls us/call us/call name 57.14 0.08 0.08 1604986 0.05 0.05 calc_gamma 35.71 0.13 0.05 802493 0.06 0.16 calc_var 7.14 0.14 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/goals/</guid>
      <description>Model choice exercise with sdes general likelihood calculation from simulation  Test Case *dX*~t~ = α~t~(θ − X~t~)*dt* + σ*d*t
*d*α~t~ = − β

Approach  The linear approximation to the warning signals dynamics can be captured by the OU process, look for changing α SDE models will also provide some of the coarser approximations for the structured population dynamics. Formulations of these still to do.  Conditional probability Solution to the time dependent OU process, see Gardiner 4th ed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graham &amp; Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/graham--peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/graham--peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussed inverse problem approach. Discussed bootstrapping likelihoods directly vs bootstrapping likelihood ratio Integrating over uncertainty in the likelihood assignment  
Research Progress  Completed writing the bootstrapping function for the partition scheme, ouch2ape function completed for converting ouch tree formats back to ape. modifies code from r-forge More details and log on the repository  Goals for Wainwright meeting tomorrow  Repeat Labrid Fin analysis with tripartition Bootstrap likelihood ratio functions</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graham &amp; Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/graham--peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/graham--peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Fantastic meeting with Graham and Peter today, covered a lot of ground.
MNV I briefly sketched the multivariate normal solution for joint probability across the tree under the regimes model. The original regimes approach did not take advantage of the fact that the solution to the joint probability across the tree is multivariate normal given the painting. This allows the calculation to be partitioned as outlined in Saturday&amp;rsquo;s entry:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hastings Beetle Workshop</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/hastings-beetle-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/hastings-beetle-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Bob Costantino and Brett Melbourne are joining us for the next two days to talk about stochastic population dynamics in Tribolium.
 Morning Session, 9a - 11a
 Outline the individual based model, toolbox  Group lunch, noon-1:30
 My lab Presentation, 2p-3p
 Present multidimensional linear noise approximation approach to characterizing the demographically stochastic key class.  Afternoon session, 3p-4p
 Follow-up on understanding noise propagation in age structure dynamics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hastings Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/hastings-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/hastings-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with Dr. Alan Hastings soon to discuss progress on this project. We&amp;rsquo;ll also see what he thinks of the open lab notebook. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot I want to cover in this meeting.  Warning Signals  Tomorrow I&amp;rsquo;m leading a discussion in seminar on regime shift literature, so I need to review major ideas of the paper with Alan. Particularly need to be clear on the role of dimensionality and if/when the population dynamics lack an appropriate Hamiltonian and whether that&amp;rsquo;s an important part of the argument.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hastings Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/hastings-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/hastings-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of cases where variance decreases before crash &amp;ndash; misleading warning signals. Schreiber 2003 Aaron King and Bill Schaffer JMB Hamiltonian vs Dissipative/gradient systems. Are Hamiltonian systems non-biological? Follow up with Darren  Reasons Warning Signals fail  Present (saddle-node model) but insufficient sensitivity to detect (lack ensembles, lack sampling frequency) dissipative but warning signals are backwards (other higher dimensional bifurcations, limit cycles &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; no potential) Hamiltonian instead of dissipative (centers, stochastically become random walks)  Code Updates Early warning signals code now does ensemble averaging, which works!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing an example of low and high power trees</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/implementing-an-example-of-low-and-high-power-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/implementing-an-example-of-low-and-high-power-trees/</guid>
      <description>Code implementation in felsenstein_tree.R
 I consider a star tree and a Felsenstein tree each of N nodes; M = (N+1)/2 tips. I consider an uncorrelated data set of M normal random variables, such as would be generated by either BM or OU models on the star tree. I produce a correlated data set such as would be generated by Brownian motion on the felsenstein tree. I generate 8 model fits &amp;ndash; fitting BM and OU to each tree under each data set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing the new approach</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/implementing-the-new-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/implementing-the-new-approach/</guid>
      <description>Spent just about the entire day off and on implementing the approach described in yesterday&amp;rsquo;s entry. Code includes the more direct implementation of the likelihood by generating trees from the process and averaging, as well as by weighting trees by their probability. Methods appear to agree reasonably well. The second approach should generate a wider variety of trees instead of using those produced by the first method. This could be done by varying the parameters of the transition rates to populate the collection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing warning signals metrics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/implementing-warning-signals-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/implementing-warning-signals-metrics/</guid>
      <description>The code now contains implementation of the basic warning signals metrics computed over a given window size into the past.
 mean variance skew lag-1 autocorrelation lag-n autocorrelation  These are implemented through the fixed interval sampler function. Recall that the Gillespie simulation API permits two kinds of events, random events occurring with exponential time distribution and events occurring at fixed (scheduled) times, which can be used for discretizations of deterministic continuous time dynamics (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Individual based simulation with gamma waiting times</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/individual-based-simulation-with-gamma-waiting-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/individual-based-simulation-with-gamma-waiting-times/</guid>
      <description>Began implementing the individual-based simulation of gamma waiting times by subdividing the first three age classes into K subclasses. Required rewriting gillespie function so as to intelligently calculate rates rather than writing 3K+1 functions. This leads to an alternative gillespie simulation interface that takes a function to calculate rates, producing cumulative sum (though perhaps that step should be moved into the raw gillespie code) of rates for each event, and an outcome function that will execute the outcome of each of those events.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LR Manuscript</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/lr-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/lr-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Still writing. Working on the comparisons to AIC section. Things to think about adding: Explicitly show p values on bootstrap What are we calling this thing anyway? After Hulsenbeck &amp;amp; Bull, 1996: ``likelihood heterogeneity test All-different seems to have some stability/convergence problems, perhaps a less aggressive example would be better? &amp;ndash;Carl Boettiger 19:46, 5 October 2010 (EDT) Stability issues resulted from different fitting methods in initial fit vs. bootstraps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Intrinsic Noise</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/large-intrinsic-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/large-intrinsic-noise/</guid>
      <description>Modified Crowley model Realizing Arbitrarily large demographic noise systems??
Consider the Crowley model from last week which I&amp;rsquo;d implemented as an individual birth-death model: (x is the better competitor, y the better colonist)
I&amp;rsquo;ve implemented the linear noise approximation for this model as a system of coupled ODEs:
And solved numerically (R code, links directly to this version and can run stand-alone from the package) using parameter values matching the individual based simulation (C code from warning_signals package).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Calculation</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/likelihood-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/likelihood-calculation/</guid>
      <description>Direct Calculation of the Joint Probability Fig 1 Sample tree
 This is the approach implemented in the wrightscape project matrix_method.c. Consider an example phylogenetic tree (Fig 1) over which a stochastic process describes the evolution of trait x, defined by the transition probability rate w. Then the joint probability for a set of observed traits under this process can be written:   The transition density from any state to any state can be represented as a matrix over the domain of the integral.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Ratio Manuscript</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Graham &amp;amp; Peter Meeting Some comments on Neyman Pearson and approaches &amp;gt; In the phylogenetics world, Huelsenbeck has a paper doing this: &amp;ldquo; A Likelihood Ratio Test to Detect Conflicting Phylogenetic Signal&amp;rdquo; and there&amp;rsquo;s a good introduction to the paper.
This is great, nice to know there&amp;rsquo;s a basis for it.
&amp;gt; I see that in the paper John references, &amp;ldquo; Statistical tests of models of DNA substitution &amp;ldquo;, they call what you&amp;rsquo;re doing &amp;ldquo;Monte Carlo&amp;rdquo;, and refers to some sort of resampling-the-data equivalent as the bootstrap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Ratio Paper</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-paper/</guid>
      <description>Higher resolution power plot for Anoles tree Figure (below right) shows power for increasing alpha in the Anoles tree. The vertical line shows the estimated value of alpha for the body-size data &amp;ndash; unlikely that a tree of this size can detect selection that is this weak even if it were present. Consequently, this fit should not be taken as evidence that BM is a better fit than the OU, but rather that the data is insufficient to inform this analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Ratio Paper- Power in Trees</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-paper--power-in-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-paper--power-in-trees/</guid>
      <description>Power in Trees tests (Results from single OU simulation per alpha, run yesterday) 2000 replicates gives a cleaner picture of the critical alpha, though with low alpha values the estimates of p are quite variable. Also more variable on the smaller trees. Even arbitrarily large alpha aren&amp;rsquo;t significant on the 5-taxa primate tree. On the small geospiza tree (13 taxa) from the geiger package we find:
0.5735 0.29 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood calculation</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/likelihood-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/likelihood-calculation/</guid>
      <description>Implemented the likelihood calculation in simulate.R code. See today&amp;rsquo;s revision changes via github beetle_sim() updated to return the full simulation to R. likelihood calculation by simulation done in parallel  library(beetles) sim &amp;lt;- beetle_sim() L &amp;lt;- likelihood(par=sim$par, X=sim$state[,2:6], Dt = sim$state[2,1]-sim$state[1,1] ) -sum(log(L))  Decent estimates of likelihood may be challenging: Modifying default settings for longer tome series:
&amp;gt; sim &amp;lt;- beetle_sim(dt = 7, T = 500) &amp;gt; L &amp;lt;- likelihood(par=sim$par, X=sim$state[,2:6], dt = sim$state[2,1]-sim$state[1,1], reps=100 ) &amp;gt; L2 &amp;lt;- likelihood(par=sim$par, X=sim$state[,2:6], dt = sim$state[2,1]-sim$state[1,1], reps=100 ) &amp;gt; -sum(log(L2)) [1] 2132.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood ratio ToDo</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-todo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-todo/</guid>
      <description>Inclusion of power figure, discussion of power. (include comparison to smaller trees?)  Code ToDo  Fix parallelization &amp;ndash; lower-level parallelization in LR_boot function seems to have high memory and processing overhead. Parallelize over alpha only. Funny that sfSapply at lower level conflicts when inside an upper-level sfSapply call? Can the lower level be put into sequential mode? Requires more experimenting, probably with simple test functions.
 Create package around power analysis, including ability to test bootstraps</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood ratio update</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/likelihood-ratio-update/</guid>
      <description>Sent drafts of Likelihood ratio paper to Peter Wainwright (Sunday 08/08) and Graham Coop (Monday 08/09)  Wrightscape  Sent Peter more information on the release of constraint results in the Labrid system. Starting wrightscape manuscript.  Changes to wrightscape.R  added a tree plotting function to the wrighttree class. labels on parameter bootstrap distributions for labrids in last week&amp;rsquo;s entry reversed wrasses and parrotfish. I&amp;rsquo;ve updated the software so that the plotting function takes care of the labeling automatically (when these were made it had to be added manually, while the automation of the data conversions and the painting by clade reversed the label assignments).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lunch with Wainwright Lab</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/lunch-with-wainwright-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/lunch-with-wainwright-lab/</guid>
      <description>Friday lunch with Wainwright lab continues to be a very useful chance to bounce ideas off of lab members with an excellent grasp of both the models involved and the real biology, morphology and evolution in question. Today&amp;rsquo;s discussion hit several topics.
 Should regime transitions be restricted to nodes? The general consensus was No. On one hand, the position of nodes may contain information about the timing of an actual environmental change responsible for a regime shift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MATICCE</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/maticce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/maticce/</guid>
      <description>Testing out Andrew Hipp&amp;rsquo;s maticce package, doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp625. Goal of package is to model-average over trees and regimes. Takes a brownie approach to regimes, identifying nodes at which a transition may have occurred.  
The Approach Takes a brute force approach to avoid user-defined paintings in the ouch framework. Users identify nodes of interest, software tries combinations of possible shifts.
runBatchHansen()  User identifies a set of nodes of interest, and optionally a maximum number of transitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making slides for Evolution meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/making-slides-for-evolution-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/making-slides-for-evolution-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Anoles LP model vs BM
Anoles LP fits vs OU1
Anoles Neyman-Pearson model selection
Visualization of transition matrix</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting/</guid>
      <description>Basically I want to apply central limit theorem for stationary processes (accounts for covariances), assuming mean zero  where
 Discussion of Freidlin-Wentzell theory in connection to Arrhenius law and the well-defined stochastic tipping point which occurs before the branch point. Kurtz results don&amp;rsquo;t really help in the case of ergodicity, can make statements about the (even non-stationary) ensemble limit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting Goals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting-goals/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of information in phyologenetic trees analysis  Review manuscript outline. More examples of comparisons? Sequence of presentation? Parametric bootstrapping approach; see this entry. Quantifying information in a tree a priori to any trait data Stationary distribution fits vs full model fits as measure of phylogenetic signal  Discussion of Regimes model  Review project status of implementing the more complicated regimes model, discussed here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting w- Alan</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting-w--alan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting-w--alan/</guid>
      <description>Weekly check-in, following up on last week&amp;rsquo;s meeting.  Goals for meeting  Discuss goals for regime shifts seminar tomorrow Discuss my manuscript outline on detection limits for early warning signals Discuss energy model formulation for analytic approximations to Tribolium model.  Meeting Notes  Early warning signals - starting in simple models, proof of principle. Discuss three challenges to detection:   ergodicity sensitivity complexity   Eventually develop robust tools to give confidence estimates (parametric bootstrap) on potential early warning signals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting with Alan</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting-with-alan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting-with-alan/</guid>
      <description>Some discussion of references  ﻿ Ovaskainen O, Meerson B. Stochastic models of population extinction. Trends in Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution. 2010;(Box 3):1-10. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2010.07.009.  ﻿* Goel NS, Richter-Dyn N. Stochastic Models in Biology. The Blackburn Press; 2004:269. Available at: http://www.amazon.com/Stochastic-Models-Biology-Narendra-Goel/dp/193066592X.
 Bjørnstad O, Finkenstädt B, BT. Dynamics of measles epidemics: estimating scaling of transmission rates using a time series SIR model. Ecological Monographs. 2002;72(2):169-184. Available at: http://www.esajournals.org/doi/pdf/10.1890&amp;frasl;0012-9615(2002)072%5B0169%3ADOMEES%5D2.0.CO%3B2072%5B0169%3ADOMEES%5D2.0.CO%3B2&amp;rdquo;). Grenfell BT, Bjørnstad ON, Finkenstädt BF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting with Graham and Peter</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting-with-graham-and-peter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting-with-graham-and-peter/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of Model Comparisons Primary focus of today&amp;rsquo;s discussion was rooted in Sunday&amp;rsquo;s entry
 On plotting quirks, haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out lattice but here&amp;rsquo;s yet another newer plotting engine for R I need to revisit how OUCH computes likelihood ratios and P values. Since some parameters are bounded to the positive real line (and may be small) the standard chi square isn&amp;rsquo;t correct. I should repeat the AIC-style analysis for likelihood ratios, though this is just a shift of where I put the zero line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting with Sam</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting-with-sam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting-with-sam/</guid>
      <description>Discussing elements of likelihood ratio manuscript and review results from release of constraint data. Figure out what to include in one manuscript, what order to present elements in, and what examples are necessary.
 Phylogenetic Signal introduction. Need for examples? A good example where phylogenetically independent contrasts is misleading, but lambda/K definition of phylogenetic signal is also misleading. Power in phylogenetic tree:  Likelihood ratio and model choice: Monte Carlo LR approach, support in the literature http://openwetware.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meetings</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meetings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meetings/</guid>
      <description>Theory Coffee 10-11a: Varied discussion, including NEON project and future of large data.
 Hastings Lab Meeting 2-3p: David Kling presents bioeconomic model on assisted migration. Model focuses on dynamic and spatial aspects, reflects pattern of dispersal common in ideal free distribution with dynamic carrying capacity, adds linear and quadratic costs.
 (Fire alarms in Wickson Hall don&amp;rsquo;t make for a productive day).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/monday/</guid>
      <description> Not a very successful day research-wise. Begun&amp;rsquo;s Monte Carlo and then my facilitation at GTC seminar went well though.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/monday/</guid>
      <description>7:30 &amp;ndash; 8:30 Read ﻿article for Wainwright&amp;rsquo;s 270:  Streisfeld, M.a. &amp;amp; Rausher, M.D. Population Genetics, Pleiotropy, and the Preferential Fixation of Mutations During Adaptive Evolution. Evolution no-no(2010).doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01128.x
Interesting approach, methods description a little light and both prediction and interpretation of pattern of mutations in coding, cis-reg, and transcription factor sites seems a little loose. Detailed notes on article in Mendeley. More comments after the discussion section at 1pm today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multitype OU Processes with varying alpha and sigma</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/multitype-ou-processes-with-varying-alpha-and-sigma/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/multitype-ou-processes-with-varying-alpha-and-sigma/</guid>
      <description>Been meaning to sit down and work this one out for a while; somehow travel and conferences helped out with that &amp;ndash; now I only have to transcribe some dozen messy hotel notepad sheets to get the calculations into this lab notebook. Meanwhile, 15 hours on a train from Portland was just the right amount of time to code up the approach, which is now implemented at the C level for the Anoles dataset; code in the wrightscape project on github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multitype OU process interfaces</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/multitype-ou-process-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/multitype-ou-process-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>Removing old implementations from the R package, so will need to grab them from the version history from now on to access the original linear implementations.
 Nelder-Mead simplex algorithm seems quite sensitive to starting conditions. Seeding it with values fit from the hansen algorithm (global alpha and sigma), it rapidly improves the log likelihood score (going up from 25 to 30, which is just barely significant according to AIC).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multivariate normal random variables</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/multivariate-normal-random-variables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/multivariate-normal-random-variables/</guid>
      <description>GSL lacks a multivariate normal random variable option, so have implemented one using the eigenvalue decomposition (default method in the R function rmvnorm). Function should consider doing error handling (i.e. warning if covariance matrix isn&amp;rsquo;t positive definite or if the vectors given don&amp;rsquo;t match dimensions), though these may be mostly unnecessary cost. Also uses a general blas matrix multiplication when one of the matrices is just sqrt(eigenvalues) on the diagonal, so this could possibly be sped up considerably using the correct blas matrix multiply.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noisy Beetles</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/noisy-beetles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/noisy-beetles/</guid>
      <description>Goals  individual-based simulation via my gillespie C library with 2-step transitions.
 Integrate the function definitions from R? Use of R formula language? Conversely, have the R code use the C functions?  Handle population-size scaling correctly
 Methods write-up, read/compare to other examples.
 Exploration/demonstration of the significance of two-step process vs two one-step processes. Highlight which examples will show largest differences, and in which terms (means vs variances/covariances, etc).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noisy beetles</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/noisy-beetles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/noisy-beetles/</guid>
      <description>Fig 1: Noise in lavae dominate
Fig: 2 lower mortality, higher noise
 Success! My first full implementation of the four stage (EPLA) beetle model, so far without any adaptation, and the noise of the larval class dominates (Fig 1). Without the time delays the stationary dynamics are stable nodes, at least in this part of parameter space, with a large adult class clamping tightly down on the other classes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/open-science-summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/open-science-summit/</guid>
      <description>First day of the Open Science Summit, began with excellent panel discussion including Cameron Neylon, Victoria Stodden, Peter Murray-Rust and Jason Hoyt. Followed by great lineup of short talks, but behind schedule and no breaks.
 Conference Schedule Backchannel twitter archive A neat backchannel question proposing site used for the conference.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit Day 3</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/open-science-summit-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/open-science-summit-day-3/</guid>
      <description>see previous day for links to more details on summit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit day 2</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/open-science-summit-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/open-science-summit-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Full day (really &amp;ndash; no breaks, lunch served during talks) of talks at the open science summit&amp;hellip;
Amazingly well web-captured conference, in addition to streaming on fora.tv, complete transcripts of talks are available thanks to someone with fast fingers.
Also through the back-channel, particularly the links it shares:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organizing analyses, data, codes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/organizing-analyses-data-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/organizing-analyses-data-codes/</guid>
      <description>Codes  Should have a suite of likelihood tools as a package Suite of data manipulation functions, mostly to and from ape/ouch  
idealized workflow:
 Read in nexus file and csv data. Call model fit for each model to be tested (BM, one peak, multiple peaks, multiple peaks with independent selective forces)  
 A function checks tree and data for matches, discards those without match. This could be done automatically by the model fit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel R</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parallel-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parallel-r/</guid>
      <description>Parallelized LR_bootstrap_all() and model_bootstrap_all() bootstrapping functions. Lets the bootstrapping of different models (or LRs between models) to be performed on different machines. Using the snowfall package in R for easy parallel computing. The parallel loop is done through the sfLapply() function. Had to get libraries and functions exported to all loops using sfLibrary() and sfExportAll(). R-sig-hpc mailing list was very helpful at getting this up and running at 4am.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel at last</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parallel-at-last/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parallel-at-last/</guid>
      <description>svn revision 27 should have functional parallel code! Certainly I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten much better at openmp in the past few days. Difficult to maintain a general API that is agnostic to the model details and still knows enough about the data formats to declare them appropriately for each thread. My lesson for my future coding: by writing with parallelization concepts in mind from the start I should be able to significantly reduce the overhead time when I go back and add openmp directives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing Code</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parallelizing-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parallelizing-code/</guid>
      <description>A solution!  After a good bit more exploring permutations of openmp commands and experimenting with code (should have been done in a branch version so would be in the version management, instead done in my local experimental sandbox so will have to implement and merge into real code still!) was able to understand the root of my problem and pose a coherent question. Posting that question on stack overflow solved my problem in under an hour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameter Estimates for Labrid-Parrotfish model</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parameter-estimates-for-labrid-parrotfish-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parameter-estimates-for-labrid-parrotfish-model/</guid>
      <description>See fast_boot and plot.wrightscape functions in code. Gape size

See fast_boot and plot.wrightscape functions in code Jaw Protrusion
Figures show strong evidence for the relax of constraint hypothesis, as the strength of selection (alpha parameters) appears to have substantially weakened in both morphological traits in the parrotfish clade relative to the wrasses clade. The wrasses show strong preference for OU model with substantial stabilizing selection, while the Parrotfish estimate almost zero stabilizing selection (Brownian model, clear phylogenetic signal).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parametric bootstrapping</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parametric-bootstrapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parametric-bootstrapping/</guid>
      <description>There are several ways we can frame the bootstrapping question. What is the probability that we see a given likelihood ratio statistic (that the log likelihoods differ by a certain spread) just by chance? We have two versions of chance &amp;ndash; the chance we see this ratio when model a is correct and the chance we see this ratio when model b is correct. We simulate 2000 data sets under each model, generating a distribution of likelihood ratio scores for each data set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parrotfish Model choice</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parrotfish-model-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parrotfish-model-choice/</guid>
      <description>code, Gape data
code, Protrusion data
For both the gape data and the jaw protrusion data, the model treating parrotfish clade as a separate regime using ouch (differing optima) is not supported (even though it does have better AIC score for the protrusion data). The model using my new method allowing alpha and sigma to differ is strongly supported, providing support for the &amp;ldquo;release of constraint&amp;rdquo; hypothesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parrotfish-Wrasse example</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parrotfish-wrasse-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parrotfish-wrasse-example/</guid>
      <description>Painting the tree with parrotfish as a separate regime from wrasses, I find significant support for a model with separate optima with differential strengths of selection and diversification as well with respect to fin angle.  code
The painting for this tree (click for larger and zoom in):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussed potential solution to the model choice scenario:
 Consider an ordered list of models, A, B, C, D Then the Neyman-Pearson Lemma (see earlier entry on this) lets us walk through the list in the following fashion: We generate the simulated data sets under model A and compare likelihood ratios in each case. If the likelihood ratio of the observed data falls outside the 95% confidence interval, than it with this confidence that we are saying the data justify the alternate model (model B).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>SICB conference  Abstract &amp;ndash; sent   Phylogenetic comparative methods have become all but ubiquitous in only a few decades, forcing us to reconsider if information from a phylogenetic tree can justify the results. Existing approaches to this question have been inadequate and do not scale with tree size or the ability to resolve branches. For instance, selection between phylogenetic models typically based on information criteria fails to adequately reflect this uncertainty, and can lead to preference for arbitrarily complicated models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetic Tree formats</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/phylogenetic-tree-formats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/phylogenetic-tree-formats/</guid>
      <description>Consider a tree with N nodes. has tips and internal nodes.  ape Format: class &amp;ldquo;phylo&amp;rdquo;  Elements of the data structure: phy$edge &amp;ndash; Topology. 2 by N-1 matrix. First column has internal nodes only, each node appearing twice. Internal nodes range from 1+(N+1)/2 to N-1, while the tip numbers go from 1 to (N+1)/2. Each node appears once in the second column, and is a child of the node identified in the first column.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetics Workshop Day 5</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/phylogenetics-workshop-day-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/phylogenetics-workshop-day-5/</guid>
      <description>Last day of lectures: Lineage Diversification
Brian Moore: Rates of Lineage Diversification Bodega Wiki slides &amp;amp; tutorial
 Detecting significant diversification rate variation across tree locate shifts along branches and through time (niche-filling, density dep models?) correlates of differential rates parameter estimation speciation/extinction  correlates of differential rates  Apply Felsenstein pruning algorithm to calc likelihood and hence fit model this is just the definition of a joint probability! Use this to estimate the model, then do rejection sampling to create the tree painting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-Workshop</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/post-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/post-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Working on a couple new ideas:
 Multiple partitions Community phylogenetics nulls Diversification rates w/ stationary distributions  Tools exploration  Finding my forum a very useful tool for recording and organizing around idea. Nice complement to this notebook which helps me organize temporally instead. Becoming convinced I should transition from svn to git. Created a git-hub account and have started learning the basic git commands. The Git community book and the website video tutorials have been very helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in Trees</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/power-in-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/power-in-trees/</guid>
      <description>Following up after yesterday&amp;rsquo;s meeting, I am working on implementing the confidence interval analysis and quantifying information in trees. This second point I will develop by comparing the Felsenstein example tree (information-rich) to the star tree (uninformative), and develop this discussion in the context of assessing the importance of phylogenetic corrections and phylogenetic intertia (my original theme again: noise or data??).
Primate Brain Morphometry Daniel Mietchen contacted me through openwetware 11 days ago with interest in applying phylogenetic comparative methods to Primate Brain Morphometry data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in trees</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/power-in-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/power-in-trees/</guid>
      <description>Back to Phylogenetics after a week with only population dynamics.  Exploration  data created by brown simulation on the star tree in ouch matches the expected variance, σ^2^t. This variance is slightly reduced when simulated on the Felsenstein tree, as might be intuitively expected due to the increased correlations. The degree of decrease should be analytically attainable, but isn&amp;rsquo;t obvious to me at the moment. Example using functions in felsenstein_tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in trees continues</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/power-in-trees-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/power-in-trees-continues/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of power in trees need a counterpoint to the example of the star tree as being devoid of information content. The best example here is probably the example tree used in the introduction of Felsenstein 1985: two star trees sharing a common ancestor. Implemented the basic creation of a balanced tree of arbitrary depth having this structure. The balanced tree has 2^h^ − 1 nodes, all internal nodes occuring at time = 1&amp;frasl;2 and all tips at time = 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power plots</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/power-plots/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/power-plots/</guid>
      <description>Testing power code. currently null and test distributions of likelihood scores are distinguishable even for small beta on the long time scale. See code for run.
 running on shorter timescale. Note that parameters match but small code differences in repository code on the last commit since I committed the version on the local machine (my laptop, for development) but ran a slightly tweaked code (typo in reps vs nboot, .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primate chronogram</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/primate-chronogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/primate-chronogram/</guid>
      <description>From User:Daniel Mietchen/Notebook/Evolutionary MRI/2010/04/12:
 Jinchuan Xing recommended New perspectives on anthropoid origins whose Fig. 2 goes into our direction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primates</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/primates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/primates/</guid>
      <description>Primates project now has a Github repository. Updates are embedded from here.
 Experimenting with distributing code and data effectively. Pluses and minuses of three options:
   zipped file with R code and data. Requires setting working directory, harder to update. Subsequent uploads must include all the data, rather than incremental. Directly grab repository over github. Simple to update and access, stores only incremental changes. Requires knowledge of git R package: Nicely integrates data, code, and documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Puzzled over the two-step jump process results</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/puzzled-over-the-two-step-jump-process-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/puzzled-over-the-two-step-jump-process-results/</guid>
      <description>The variance dynamics are slightly different if the continuous time Markov process allows events to contain two steps (such as a transition of an individual from one age class to another, or one patch to another, etc) as well as one step birth/death) transitions. *V*τ~*i*j~(X / V) to represent the rate of transitions from state i to state j. We change variables for our state space from the discrete count state variable X by dividing by the system size (volume) V, to obtain the continuous, mean-field approximation of the density p = X/V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Questions</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/questions/</guid>
      <description>Current population dynamics model macroscopic equations:
Interpreting μ terms as death events, b as birth, and the a terms as transitions between age classes gives a natural form for the master equation.
Divergent Solutions to the linear noise approximation? Breaking the age classes into k subclasses makes waiting time within an age class gamma instead of exponential, which better matches observation. Also allows sustained oscillations. The numerical solution to the linear noise approximation shows divergent variance dynamics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R-sig-phylo</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/r-sig-phylo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/r-sig-phylo/</guid>
      <description>A couple interesting discussions on R-sig-phylo   estimating alpha and sigma reliably, knowing when you hit a likelihood ridge. See discussion. strange behavior in ace. Tried new ace function, same problem.  
Research  Working on logs paper Waiting on Primate data Waiting on feedback on Labrids paper  
DoE Conference Registration  Submitted Poster title and abstract corresponding to my iEvoBio proposal.  Reading  podcast on the Science Careers story.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/reading/</guid>
      <description>Trying to make this show reading of the day, the script below shows only current reading:
Friendfeed discussion on solving this:
Warning Signals  Implementing likelihood-based methods for early warning signals. Trying three models:  
 Model 3 is intended to be a changepoint analysis, where α(t) is piecewise constant. I solved analytically the transition probability density in Model 2 on User:Carl Boettiger/Notebook/Stochastic Population Dynamics/2010/05/06, see this and the following entry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Maximum likelihood assignment based on arbitrary number of partitions now completed. Working on stochastic assignment. Now have functions for:   partitioning data into k groups, inferring an ancestral state painting based on this partition inferring a continuous model with k OU regimes based on this painting   need to add my function for the proper model-comparison bootstrap of likelihood ratio values rather than the likelihoods themselves. See my original entry on this approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>A some point I&amp;rsquo;ll want to think more seriously about incorporating geographic information into comparative analyses. At some level this data is more available than appropriate continuous traits, as illustrated in the example phylogenetics wiki from Prof. Roderic Page that I just came across.  Today&amp;rsquo;s Goals  Repeating last night&amp;rsquo;s bootstraps on the likelihood ratio. Need to clean up and incorporate my bootstrap codes first. Should also explore the bootstrapping of the partitioning functions from yesterday.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapped against 2000 replicate simulations overnight on both the Anoles dataset and the Labrids dataset. Distributions that overlap zero represent replicates that choose the wrong model. The Anoles data below; the first column corresponds to the likelihood ratios shown in Butler &amp;amp; King (2004), comparing each model against BM.   The Labrid dataset:   Find matching figures for the case of parameters held fixed on more recent entry</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrap the fitted models (rather than allow the parameters to be refit, simply evaluate the likelihood of the model under each simulated dataset) Directly evaluate Neyman-Pearson lemma for each pairwise model comparison. Also analyze the bootstrapped likelihoods directly (and without refitting) for each model.  To Do  Add a summary function for the likelihood_ratio_bootstrap.R library final wrapper function for infer_niches.R partitioning library More error handling and documentation Example of partitioning Anoles then bootstrapping Bootstrapping likelihoods directly  References on thinking about bootstrapping model comparisons  The original Neyman-Pearson paper Testing Statistical Hypotheses Text by Lehmann &amp;amp; Romano Permutation, Parametric and Bootstrap Tests of Hypotheses by Good Thanks to Peter on these; Bibsonomy collection  ouch2ape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>New Simulations  Now have code to run partitioned models on the Anoles dataset, compare partitioned models to the paintings chosen by Butler and King. Preliminary figures below. Models with _s are partitioned by my algorithm, others are the the original ones from earlier.   Also have examples with simulated data with a known number of partitions, to check the method. Tested with data produced at two peaks on the Labrid tree, the pattern seems similar to that of the Labrids &amp;ndash; comparisons involving any model with more than 2 peaks produce LR ratios that become very unlikely in either pairwise comparison.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Current Situation &amp;amp; Challenges 2000 bootstraps of models fitted to simulated ou2 data
 A single data set is produced by simulation under a specified ou2 model on the Labrid tree (actually one that was fitted to the original Labrid data). Each model (Brownian motion and 1 to 5 separate OU peaks (assigned by my partition function) is fitted to this dataset. Each fitted model is used to generate 2000 replicate datasets For each replicate dataset, the model used to generate it is compared to each other model in likelihood ratio test 2(log(L~1~) − log(L~2~)), where L~1~ is the likelihood of the model that generated the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Writing up work just on ensemble vs single instance detection of regime shifts. See this entry

Outline Title
On the ability to detect leading indicators of catastrophe in unreplicated time series
Introduction Background on Warning Signals
 literature Saddle Node bifurcation Detecting decreasing stabilization &amp;ndash; gradual vs changepoint estimation  Reasons detection can fail:
 Ergodicity: ensembles vs single instances Sufficient statistical power Appropriate dynamics  Methods
 Defining an indicator &amp;ndash; significant Kendall rank correlation coefficient τ as in doi:10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Single replicate. Almost all warning signals have significant correlation despite the constant environment.
False warning signals remain just as common when signals are averaged across 100 replicates?
 Exploring statistical qualification of early warning signals. Dakos et. al. (2008) use a correlation significance test (based on Kendall&amp;rsquo;s tau) on the autocorrelation to detect the warning signals. Correlation significance test seems a very poor estimate of signal, high false positive rate at any threshold p-value for sufficiently frequent sampling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Graham &amp;amp; Peter Meeting Fig 1
Fig 2
 Decided that bootstrapping against fixed model parameters would be more difficult to interpret, Fig 1. Simulated data results with refitting seem strange (Fig. 2), perhaps related to fitting of the tree. Observed LR for data should at least remain symmetric, so something has gone wrong. Expected pattern should be deducible simply by upper left triangle of graphs, should accept the first model where the data becomes typical.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Trouble-shooting on parameter refitting version of LR bootstraps.  
NESCent  Considering a visit to NESCent, meet researchers and learn about programs, post-docs, etc.  People  Todd Vision, UNC &amp;ndash; Ass. Director Informatics. Contact Re: Dryad project. Consider a white paper on interdisciplinary evolutionary synthesis. Brian Weigmann NCSU Diptera Systematics. Ass. Director Outreach NESCent Allen Rodrigo Director NESCent. (Computational evolutionary biology). Discuss possible catalysis meeting, working group, visiting scholar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapping procedures should have the option to refit the painting. Currently use the fixed painting but refit parameters. wrote the function peaks_update() which update the painting as well as the OU peak parameters.  20 replicates, bootstraps the painting step as well
Computing / Package  LR_bootstrap and model_bootstrap should be the same function call with an optional second model for the LR bootstrapping. Similarly the LR_bootstrap_all and model_bootstrap_all() should be the same function call.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Seem to have successfully fixed the behavior when getting over parameterized models. See diffs against the git log for details.
 Will work on acceleration of code (avoiding refitting), meanwhile a little more trouble shooting and queuing some long runs.
 ace function fails on certain data sets for unknown reasons. Think rewriting this from scratch will be an important step.
  Mixture Models in Bayesian context  Josh sent me this paper regarding our discussion on model choice in Bayesian context last Friday.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Goal: complete outline for tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s meeting.  Notes Theory Coffee  Two more days before eve speaker nominations are due. Potentially nominating:
 Brice Kendall Ray Hillborn Model choice (Ecological Detective).  Discussion of post-doc / job application process.
  Education  NIMBioS Computational Biology Curriculum Development July 6-9</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Reviewed timescales manuscript. Revisiting  Meeting  Basically I want to apply central limit theorem for stationary processes (accounts for covariances), assuming mean zero  where
 Discussion of Freidlin-Wentzell theory in connection to Arrhenius law and the well-defined stochastic tipping point which occurs before the branch point. Kurtz results don&amp;rsquo;t really help in the case of ergodicity, can make statements about the (even non-stationary) ensemble limit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Working on bootstrapping theta parameters bootstrapping multiple parameters doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem effective in the context of the boot package, despite claiming it can use a vector of stats. Certainly part of challenge is that different models have different numbers of parameters, so this isn&amp;rsquo;t a fixed size vector. Approaching manually for the moment, inhibits use of bootstrap confidence intervals function from the boot package. Some irregular behavior in bootstrapping parameters &amp;ndash; have to load package and then reload likelihood_bootstrap library source file or else bootstraps are NAs, needs further investigation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Sent Peter updated draft of Labrids manuscript Writing up logarithms manuscript finally&amp;hellip; Contacting Helen re. primates data Created Labrid Functional Morphology literature collection:  Research collected using Mendeley
 Started stochastic methods and model inference collection:  Research collected using Mendeley
Various To Do  Add Peter&amp;rsquo;s bootstrap references and books to stochastic methods and model inference library. Add Science of Science papers to Future of Science collection. Adding tags, abstracts, etc to Mendeley public Library Personal/extended task view (and opinion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Beetles Noise</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/rethinking-beetles-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/rethinking-beetles-noise/</guid>
      <description>Noise in the larval class is damped by and grows proportional to its intrinsic variation and the contribution of other classes through their derivatives of f~L~, that is, as well as the sum of its intrinsic rates (essentially whichever is larger). Taking E dynamics to be fast we might reduce to a continous time LPA model:  and the larval fluctuations are essentially:
where β~i~ is the intrinsic noise of the age class.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roi and Sam Comparative Phylogenetics R Workshop</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/roi-and-sam-comparative-phylogenetics-r-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/roi-and-sam-comparative-phylogenetics-r-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Day 2: 4p - 6:30p  Attending the R workshop by Roi Holzmann and Sam Price from the Wainwright lab. Missed the introductory session on Monday. Course data currently available here. Resources: Springer R books pdfs available through UC Davis. In particular: R book w/ ape.  Speciation &amp;amp; Diversification 3rd session (4:10 - 5:10 pm): Packages: Laser, Geiger, Ape, apTreeshape &amp;amp; Diversitree
 Lineage through time plots ape and laser:   ltt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solution to the strange behavior in ouch</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/solution-to-the-strange-behavior-in-ouch/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/solution-to-the-strange-behavior-in-ouch/</guid>
      <description>Looks like my troubles actually stem from a bug in the code. I summarize the problem here, just as I posted in my query to R sig phylo. Essentially the program erroneously squares alpha at the moment, explaining the pattern I found yesterday. Giving it root alpha preemptively should be a good work around.

data(bimac) tree &amp;lt;- with(bimac,ouchtree(node,ancestor,time/max(time),species)) print(h2 &amp;lt;- hansen(log(bimac[&#39;size&#39;]),tree,bimac[&#39;OU.1&#39;],alpha=1,sigma=1))  The print command says alpha = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status - Thoughts</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/status---thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/status---thoughts/</guid>
      <description>Goal: BM vs OU vs proposed multipeak OU model with and without global alpha/sigma. Anoles dataset, carex dataset, labrids?
 Added ape2ouch_all function based on maticce to convert file formats. Might be worth checking against my current implementation. Meanwhile it&amp;rsquo;s really the converting trees back from ouch to ape that gives the ace function trouble. something about ordering of the nodes, even though that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t matter in the phylo format.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status on Structured Populations</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/status-on-structured-populations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/status-on-structured-populations/</guid>
      <description>Model roundup  metapop Two populations with one-step transitions. IBM in C code, R interface to IBM and linear noise approximation. crowley One-step transitions version of metapop. R interface to IBM and linear noise. beetles Two-step transitions with exponential waiting times in age classes. R interface completed in ind_based_models.R hastings Simple two-step model. no R interfaces yet. tribolium Non-markov aging process. R interface completed in simulate.R. includes likelihood inference as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status update</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/status-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/status-update/</guid>
      <description>Actually out of town this day, but draft off to co-authors, will review Friday. meanwhile time to get back to some warning signals work, will be in other notebook for rest of the week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Still puzzling on LR</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/still-puzzling-on-lr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/still-puzzling-on-lr/</guid>
      <description> The likelihood ratios when parameters are not held fixed, using data originally generated from a two peak model. Has 1000 bootstrap replicates per plot.   The likelihood ratios when parameters are held fixed, after being generated from a two-peak model. (2000 replicates each)   parameters held fixed, three peak model (200 replicates each)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Still writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/still-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/still-writing/</guid>
      <description>Ah, back after being in bed almost a week with flu. Back to writing manuscript, reworking the presentation of the actual method. Much of the day caught up in Watson&amp;rsquo;s practice orals (applying computational mechanics to inhibitory neuron circuits), checking in with Yun on his orals and then GTC. too many delays, hope I feel fully better soon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structured Population Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/structured-population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/structured-population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Beetle Model Macroscopic equations:
Has the corresponding variance-covariance dynamics
Where g_i is the second jump moment, which is a function of the state (E, L, P, A) just as f_i is. (In this case it will correspond to the sum of all birth and death terms).
General Form &amp;amp; Algorithm Consider the dynamics are given by
and define variance-covariance matrix M and the Jacobian matrix of f as J. Then the dynamics of the diagonal elements (variance terms) are written as</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary of Structured Population noise so far</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/summary-of-structured-population-noise-so-far/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/summary-of-structured-population-noise-so-far/</guid>
      <description>Fig 1 Code b=5, ue= 0, ul = 0.001, up = 0, ua = 0.01, ae = .13*k, al = .01*k, ap = .15*k, cle = .2, cap = .1, cae = 5, V=volume
Fig 2 b=5, ue= 0, ul = 0.001, up = 0, ua = .001, ae = .1*k, al = .01*k, ap = .1*k, cle = 1, cap = .4, cae = 1, V=volume

System Size Expansion  Analytic calculation captures the noise propagation through the age structure correctly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer Review</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/summer-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/summer-review/</guid>
      <description>Stochastic Population Dynamics in Beetles    Early Warning from Fluctuations in Populations</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ergodicity Question- Time averaging vs Ensemble averaging</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/the-ergodicity-question--time-averaging-vs-ensemble-averaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/the-ergodicity-question--time-averaging-vs-ensemble-averaging/</guid>
      <description>11am &amp;ndash; 3pm
 Tried time averaging over the entire time window (set sample_size to 1 less than max time); in close agreement with the ensemble predictions (getting around 1355). Mystery doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to actually be a problem in the method, but just innate variability! Even over reasonable time-averages and ensemble averages there&amp;rsquo;s significant deviation from the expected variance! This variation around the warning signal/leading indicator is exactly what might frustrate the warning signal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lab Notebook Goes Open</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/the-lab-notebook-goes-open/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/the-lab-notebook-goes-open/</guid>
      <description>(Originally posted on OpenWetWare)
 This is the first entry in my lab notebook, but not the beginning of the project. I have been exploring demographic and colored environmental noise since beginning my graduate program at UC Davis. Much of that time has been spent in building the appropriate tool set though, so now it&amp;rsquo;s time to dive in.
 A good starting point is Denis et. al. (2001) Ecological Monographs 71.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/thursday/</guid>
      <description>Some exploration with felsenstein_tree.R, see svn log.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/thursday/</guid>
      <description>Alan will write introduction to manuscript. Schedule meeting for next week. Scheduling the Hastings lab meeting doodle Coordinate with Baskett lab  Resources for ABC / Bayesian inference in ecological and spatial context workshop  Sisson Sa, Fan Y, Tanaka MM. Sequential Monte Carlo without likelihoods. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 2007;104(6):1760-5. Available at: http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=1794282&amp;amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;amp;rendertype=abstract. de Valpine P, Hastings A. Fitting Population Models Incorporating Process Noise and Observation Error.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards a meaningful warning signal metric</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/towards-a-meaningful-warning-signal-metric/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/towards-a-meaningful-warning-signal-metric/</guid>
      <description>Most papers do not give a statistical approach, but merely argue for the existence of a trend. Kendall&amp;rsquo;s tau approach proved very unreliable. While the preliminary de-trending approach is unjustified in that the simulated data is known to be absent from trends, as a kind of windowed averaging it may sense as a way to detect changes. Should distinguish between the gradual slow changes and change-point estimation. Perhaps change-point provides a more rigorous starting point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Preparing for EDG talk</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Much of today&amp;rsquo;s activity included in yesterday&amp;rsquo;s.
Recording Reading Still looking for a good way to capture time snapshots of what I&amp;rsquo;ve read. Perhaps the Mendeley API will have a good solution. Here I try twapper-keeper to create an rss of my tweets on a given day, and the google api, but not very ideal solutions. Checked a variety of ways to filter rss feeds by date so that it would just show the current ones, none seem to manage this though.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updates to Code</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/updates-to-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/updates-to-code/</guid>
      <description>Mostly organizational updates at the moment. Restructured the directory tree, and added proper literate programming headers to the code using Doxygen markup.  code</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating examples of stochastic structured population dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/updating-examples-of-stochastic-structured-population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/updating-examples-of-stochastic-structured-population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Demonstrating the differences in accounting for the two-step transitions explicitly.
 Dotted lines show the one_step process, solid show the two_step process. code. Code embedded below (experimental, wonder if this is easier than following the link).
  

Summer Research Summary  Finished and sent off the summer research summary for my afternoon meeting with Adam and Micha.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating manuscript</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/updating-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/updating-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>The progress of the past few days has lead to substantial revision proposals in my manuscript draft. Rewriting for discussion with Brian tomorrow. Currently revised outline:
 Intro
 Biological Motivation Comparative Methods and Comparing Models Model choice paradigm: the right direction, but incomplete  Simple Example
 The Star Tree Two hypotheses: stabilizing vs disruptive selection Information Criteria approach is insufficient Likelihood surfaces Likelihood ratio distribution  Anoles Example</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wainwright Lab Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/wainwright-lab-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/wainwright-lab-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Presented a revised version of my talk for Evolution 2010, focusing on the inadequacy of information-criteria heuristics for model choice in phylogenetic comparative methods and presenting the likelihood-ratio based approach I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on. Much better received this time. (The last two weeks have been pretty dedicated to preparing for the upcoming conferences, mostly for this presentation, so not much in the way of new research. Will be able to return to new stuff in July, following iEvoBio).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wainwright Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/wainwright-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/wainwright-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussed goals and appropriate approach. Settled on linear order rather than trying to directly implement the full MCMC over paintings solution directly. Breaks into four steps/manuscripts:
 Phylogenetic signal and model choice in Comparative Methods: Likelihood ratio approach Detecting changing constraints in evolution: varying alpha and sigma across the tree Bayesian approach for all existing continuous trait comparative methods MCMC over possible histories to infer number of niches</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Current Puzzles &amp;amp; Goals 1 rep
100 reps
 Kendall&amp;rsquo;s tau unreliable, exploring alternatives. Sliding window for identifying when warning is first detected? Goal is to detect any decrease in stability or distance from critical point? Chasing down data from Scheffer. Climate data reuses the CaCO3 from Dakos. Chasing down data from Dakos   Fig. 1 M Cariaco Basin, data file Vostok deuterium CaCO3 data Tropical Pacific core 1218   Warning signals examples with actual tipping points (Figures left).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Working on implementation of the the TwoRates model looking for changepoint: See for most of code implementation sde_likelihood.R and for the model choice example see warning_example.R  General Code cleanup  Added a saddle-node bifurcation simulation in the format of the metapop/hastings/crowley/beetles models already in the stochastic population dynamics library. Allows for C-based parallelized ensemble simulation using my Gillespie library. R call to all of these models can be found in ind_based_models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Alternate models  Writing down the change-point model correctly now, starting with the simulation. Done. Implemented in sde_likelihood.R
 Implementing Neyman-Pearson comparisons for all three models.
  Linearizing directly from the saddle node model Dynamics:
Slope (alpha) at equilibrium comes from the derivative:
is the slope evaluated at n equal to equilbrium (which is the root of some messy cubic).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Reworking code to allow standard format for:   evaluating likelihood, &amp;ndash; Done fitting by maximum-likelihood, &amp;ndash; Done simulating, &amp;ndash; Done bootstrapping plotting models and bootstrap results.  changePt.sim, changePt.lik implemented.

Function Behavior notes  R&amp;rsquo;s mle function wants a named list.
 Updated parameter handling of OU.lik to allow parameters in alpha,theta,sigma format or theta1, theta2, theta3 format, as either lists or numerics, named or unnamed. Type handling in each function isn&amp;rsquo;t helping the speed, but optimization will have to wait.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Exploring convergence in maximum likelihood model fits each on data produced by their own simulation method:
 fit1, basic OU method, converges just fine. (using L-BFGS-B method with appropriate bounding box to avoid negatives). fit2 , the linear change rate model, converges fine using Nelder-Meade (using 1e12 ~ inf likelihood return when attempting negative alpha or sigma), but throws hard errors for L-BFGS-B:   Error in optim(pars, warning.likfn, method = method, lower = lower) : non-finite finite-difference value [3]   fit3 runs on &amp;ldquo;L-BFGS-B&amp;rdquo; and returns reasonable values, though not meeting convergence standards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>bootstrapping models implemented improved handling of model classes &amp;ndash; included T, t0, N, and X0 in object def implemented plotting for model bootstrap difficulties with changePt model fit remain. fixed one source of trouble &amp;ndash; no longer passes zero-length data to OU.lik() when t_shift is outside the time interval.  Still giving errors on coercing lists into doubles for the saddle_node bifurcation simulated data set. &amp;ndash;fixed, was getting t_shift as a vector from time(X).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapping for likelihood ratios! Updated class behavior &amp;ndash; all simulation and fitting routines now return timeseries objects as data with correct range and timestep. updated plotting routines. Likelihood ratio plotting function. Bootstraps of parameters can be plotted using the output from the likelihood ratio fit simulation, avoiding redundancy, just specify which model is desired. Bootstrap likelihood ratio plots includes the original ratio and calculates plot range using this information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals -- still in code development</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals----still-in-code-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals----still-in-code-development/</guid>
      <description>OWW was down, notebook embedded from springnote:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals-research/</guid>
      <description>Deuterium early warning signal used for Glaciation I-IV presented in Dakos 2008:  Deuterium signal over past 4 glaciations
 Does smoothing to remove trends &amp;ndash; longer-scale fluctuations? Seems unnatural, many of those are part of the signal. Also applied to simulated time series &amp;ndash; even those these are at stationarity! Bandwidth chosen by visual inspection. Get the CaCO3 presented in Scheffer 2010 and Dakos 2008. &amp;ndash; Done: CaCO3</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals by model choice</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals-by-model-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals-by-model-choice/</guid>
      <description>Finished implementation of simulation from saddle-node example Implemented simulation from transition density for all three models  Whoops  The change point model can&amp;rsquo;t be summarized by the transition density, as this depends only on the time interval and not the absolute time. The nice description of being able to solve for the transition density when the transition occurs during the time interval specified is neither necessary nor applicable in this context!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals with SDEs</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals-with-sdes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals-with-sdes/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Have a functional likelihood calculation from the full individual-based simulation, see Friday. Accuracy needs more testing, and the computation is probably too slow for optimization routines. Have an implementation of the linear decrease in stability model with analytic conditional probability density. Needed a couple adjustments today. Need to add direct simulation to the warning signals package, currently retunrs only time-averaged/ensemble averaged stats. Can be approximated by setting the window equal to the timestep and ensembles equal to one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/wednesday/</guid>
      <description>10-2p Finish preparing for EDG talk.
 2-3p. Talk went pretty well. Could still polish slides up for them to be useful, likewise for outline.
 3-4 OA meeting
 4-9p awesome talk in ESLP with Katie Maynard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/wednesday/</guid>
      <description>Structured populations part of project migrated to github from the google code page. Finally switched to using STL for linked list in simulation. Have working simulation function ensemble run function also calculates the probability based on kernel-density estimation from the replicates. Working on likelihood calculation.  Code progress  Lots of fun trying to get full structured population simulator working accurately. See git log for details, but ended up abandoning two separate versions of custom-written C linked lists and just switched entire code over to C++ to use the STL&amp;rsquo;s linked list, which finally worked like a charm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/wednesday/</guid>
      <description>Monte Carlo  Reading Sanderson&amp;rsquo;s nonparametric rate smoothing and semi-parametric r8s papers in Monte Carlo with Rannala. Comments on articles in text, but great discussion today, particularly Bruce&amp;rsquo;s take on this style of approach.   Sanderson, M.J. Estimating absolute rates of molecular evolution and divergence times: a penalized likelihood approach. Molecular biology and evolution 19, 101-9(2002). Sanderson, M.J. A Nonparametric Approach of Rate Constancy to Estimating Divergence Times in the Absence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>working on Likelihood ratio manuscript. Some more literature review and outlining.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>working on likelihood ratio manuscript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio manuscript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio manuscript.  Labrid Herbivory data Parrotfish gape shows significant differences for independent OU models (alpha, theta, sigma different) than wrasses. While the two-peak ouch model gets no support, allowing alpha and sigma to very results in a strongly significant model improvement.
code
&amp;gt; ws2$ ws2$alpha ws2$data ws2$loglik ws2$regimes ws2$sigma ws2$theta ws2$tree ws2$Xo &amp;gt; ws2$theta [1] 0.2245493 0.9569619 &amp;gt; ws2$alpha [1] 2.943846e+00 4.995744e-06 &amp;gt; ws2$sigma [1] 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>Finished a draft of manuscript on Likelihood ratio, sent to Sam and Peter Ralph.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>revising likelihood ratio manuscript &amp;ndash; added a section of conceptual examples to link the model choice and phylogenetic signal sections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio/phylogenetic signal manuscript</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio/phylogenetic signal manuscript.

scrap notes from more literature combing  Cheverud 1985 autocorellational model, extended by Gittlman &amp;amp; Kot 1990 Grafen 89, Pagen &amp;amp; Harvey 89 extending PIC to polytomies Harvey &amp;amp; Mace 82, Harvey &amp;amp; Clutton Brock 85 taxonomic rather than phylogenetic  From Blomberg et al: &amp;ldquo;The three best-justified phylogenetically based statistical methods can all be applied with a star phylogeny, in which case they yield results that are exactly the same as a conventional analysis (phylogenetically independent contrasts: Felsenstein 1985; generalized least squares: Grafen 1989; Martins and Hansen 1997; Garland and Ives 2000; Rohlf 2001; Monte Carlo simulations: Martins and Garland 1991; Garland et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing continues</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/writing-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/writing-continues/</guid>
      <description>Deleting large sections is a great way to spur better writing. Revised organization substantially, discussion somewhat loose still. But basic framework all in place. draft off to Peter and Graham!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a day of writing</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/a-day-of-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/a-day-of-writing/</guid>
      <description>Figuring out the best way to present the critique of AIC, introduction to the method, introduction to the power test. Seeking inspiration from Huelsenbeck 1996 and digging farther back into the literature:

 Cox, D.R. Further results on tests of separate families of hypotheses. Journal of the Royal Stastical Society 24, 406-424(1962). Cox, D.R. Tests of Seperate Families of Hypotheses. Proceedings of the 4th Berkeley Symposium, University of California Press 105 - 123(1961).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio Submission</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ievobio-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ievobio-submission/</guid>
      <description>Quantifying Information in a Phylogenetic Tree: The Robustness of Phylogenetic Signal Since Felsenstein (1985)&amp;rsquo;s influential paper on phylogenetic contrasts, phylogenetically-based inferences of evolutionary patterns have gotten increasingly more complex (Hansen, 1997; Butler and King, 2004; Freckleton and Harvey, 2006; O&amp;rsquo;Meara et al., 2006; Pagel and Meade, 2006). More and more sophisticated models are applied to datasets of species mean traits on a phylogenetic tree in an attempt to answer such questions as reconstructing ancestral states, identify changes in rates of character evolution across time and across clades, identify the number and location of evolutionary optima or the strength of stabilizing selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio day one</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ievobio-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ievobio-day-one/</guid>
      <description>Program:
conference twitter
 Lunch with O&amp;rsquo;Meara &amp;amp; Price, discussing working group potential
 Dinner with Nescent folks on Dryad project and others</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio day two</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ievobio-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ievobio-day-two/</guid>
      <description>Program:

My Lightning talk on Open Science:
Ievobio
View more presentations from cboettig.
Also in Nature Proceedings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio lightning talk</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ievobio-lightning-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ievobio-lightning-talk/</guid>
      <description>Submitting a five minute lighting talk on open science. Submitted version here, final text below. See the page revision history for earlier drafts and the original call below. Special thanks to Sam, Alistair, Betta, Shaun, and Alex for feedback.
My experiment with open science: Why the benefits of sharing go beyond source code The practice and philosophy of open source run deep within the iEvoBio community. Sharing source code has made software development faster and more reliable.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>