<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Hugo and blogdown</title>
      <link>/2017/04/19/migrating-to-hugo-and-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/19/migrating-to-hugo-and-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>After OpenWetWare (2010), Wordpress (2010 - 2012) and Jekyll (2012 - 2017), I move platforms once again: now to Hugo. Why the move? As usual, this site remains a way for me to explore new technologies, but the cutting edge is by no means the allure which leads me to migrate. Rather, I find myself ever trying to move towards simpler platforms, what’s easier to maintain, free to host, easier to replicate, and what makes best use of the most widely available and well-maintained existing software and avoids unncessary custom hacks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>socialR: Reproducible Research &amp; Notebook integration with R</title>
      <link>/2010/12/11/socialr-an-r-package-to-track-the-status-of-computations-with-social-network-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 03:44:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/11/socialr-an-r-package-to-track-the-status-of-computations-with-social-network-tools/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve created an R package that uses social media tools for reproducible research. The goal of the package is this: whenever I run a code, output figures are automatically added to my figure repository (Flickr), linked to the timestamped version of the code that produced them in the code repository. Figures should be tagged by project and be embedded selectively or automatically into this lab notebook. The basic workflow of the notebook looks like this:[ref]Diagram of my notebook as presented at Science Online, 2011, see other slides in my entry on this.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>