<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rnexml on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/rnexml/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rnexml on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/rnexml/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>test_ape.R unit tests now passing. Should still revise the coercion methods in nexml_write.R to something more clever. We aren&amp;rsquo;t coercing a tree to a nexml, we are building a nexml from a tree. Likewise handling the otu assignments of species names should be done directly 11:20 am 2013/08/28 start cleaning up old read/write methods obsoleted by toNeXML/fromNeXML methods 10:59 am 2013/08/28 inherited classes now replace all the original classes 10:54 am 2013/08/28 All inheritance-based classes appearing in inst/examples/trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML  Example methods for metadata: https://github.com/ropensci/RNeXML/issues/20#issuecomment-26457772 Closes #19 https://github.com/ropensci/RNeXML/issues/19#issuecomment-26459110 Discussion of best identifiers for OTUs #24. Now waiting on Scott for choice of implementation  Misc R puzzle In R&amp;rsquo;s S4 methods, I can define methods with different signatures, i.e. different object classes for the same function call. But can I alter the names and number of arguments for a method?
As usual, see Github for details on commits and issues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Some very good feedback from Hilmar as I tackle some of the semantic capabilities of NeXML in RNeXML. As the complete discussion is already archived in the Github issues tracking, (see in particular #26 and #24) I only paraphrase here.
One of the central advantages we can offer in programmatic generation of NeXML in the R environment is the ability to validate names and enhance the metadata included in the resulting nexml file using programmatic queries to taxonomic name resolution services such as ITIS, EOL, NCBI, as provided in the taxize package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>(From issue #20)
Basic metadata queries a question of how the user queries that metadata. Currently we have a metadata function that simply extracts all the metadata at the specified level (nexml, otus, trees, tree, etc) and returns a named character string in which the name corresponds to the rel or property and the value corresponds to the content or href, e.g.:
birds &amp;lt;- read.nexml(&amp;quot;birdOrders.xml&amp;quot;) meta &amp;lt;- get_metadata(birds)  prints the named string with the top-level (default-level) metadata elements as so:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Thursday  Reading through Andrew&amp;rsquo;s manuscript Working on RNeXML checks / travis continuous integration. Completing documentation, updating unit tests to reflect recent API changes.
 Difficulty getting taxize dependency to pass travis check. Needed these lines in travis:  - sudo apt-get install gdal-bin libgdal1 libgdal1-dev netcdf-bin libproj-dev - ./travis-tool.sh install_aptget gdal-bin   Interview with Nature Careers journalist Amanda, discussing open notebook and open science developments  Friday  Finish up RNeXML checks / travis integration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML merge travis integration with support for rrdf. See pull #57 Reply to Perry re nonparametric approaches 10am Andrew Skype meeting re: his manuscript rOpenSci discussion re: other services, formats. Reading Caldwell et al, Geophysical Letters. Good example of naiive data mining leading to spurious correlations from non-independent models. (/ht @FreshwaterEcology Looking over NSF&amp;rsquo;s Data Infrastructure Building Blocks, DIBB call and previously funded work.
 Remote control for Ubuntu via android?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>CRAN trivia When should you bump version for a (rejected) resubmission?  Once accepted, any change other than to the metadata (essentially the DESCRIPTION file) needs an increased version. For submissions, we prefer (but do not insist on) a new number of each attempt.
 &amp;ndash;Prof Brian Ripley
Using non-CRAN repositories in SUGGESTS or ENAHANCES More dubious tricks, from Yihui:
 FYI, here is how R core checks dependencies: https://github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extending ape::phylo class to NeXML:</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/extending-apephylo-class-to-nexml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/extending-apephylo-class-to-nexml/</guid>
      <description>While working on the RNeXML package, I have recently I have been puzzling over extending S3 objects to share some of the nice properties of S4 objects and methods while continuing to function with the potentially huge library of functions written to work with them. SO:
To illustrate this issue, consider the S3 class phylo provided by the ape package and used by most of the 30+ packages that reverse depend or reverse import ape.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>