<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ropensci on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/ropensci.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ropensci on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/ropensci/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/09/24/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/09/24/notes/</guid>
      <description>rocker / docker  Talking over strategy with Dirk, see summary in #1 and follow-up issues, #3, #4, #5.  rdataone &amp;amp; EML Trying to fix travis issues. Much craziness.
travis.sh doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide notes on setup for repos where the R package is in a subdirectory. Looks like cd commands are persistent though throughout a travis file. okay.
 dataone is imported by EML but suggested by dataone. Since install_github likes to install the suggests list, this creates problems:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible research environments with Docker</title>
      <link>/2014/08/25/reproducible-research-environments-with-docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/25/reproducible-research-environments-with-docker/</guid>
      <description>Academic research takes place in computational environments of continually increasing complexity. This creates ever-higher barriers not only to reproducing or extending the results of other researchers, but also barriers to collaboration and training of new researchers.
Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be nice if we could all work in equivalent computing environments, such that whatever worked for me on my computer would work for you on yours? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be nice if we could just clone and copy our entire software environment when we needed to move our computations over to a more powerful cloud or cluster computer?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/05/27/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/27/notes/</guid>
      <description>nonparametric-bayes  nonparametric-bayes sensitivity-trends runs. nonparametric-bayes sensitivity.R runs: explore facets to see what setting causes the below-perfect performance cluster.  knitcitations  updates to knitcitations (paste fron NEWS) Looking at adapting CSL for inline text formatting csl/issues/33 Implemented pandoc rendering  ropensci  Use of .Renviron vs .Rprofile for API keys  Seems the difference between .Rprofile and .Renviron is that (a) the latter is just a named character vector, and (b) the latter is accessed by Sys.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/04/11/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/11/notes/</guid>
      <description>labnotebook Updates to configuration to be more portable and lightweight:
 Drop APIs for Mendeley and Github in favor of just pulling from atom/rss feeds. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t require a platform-specific API or authentication, and has proven more robust, if sometimes less flexible and fancy. Drop git-modified and sha timestamps. It&amp;rsquo;s nice having these on the pages and included in the rdfa, but the information is accessible from the git repository and from Github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/04/10/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/10/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</guid>
      <description>multiple uncertainty  Set up Paul Fackler&amp;rsquo;s MDPSOLVE and run Paul&amp;rsquo;s code. Installing user-contributed extensions in matlab seems mostly a matter adding the unzipped source directories to the path, e.g. as so:
  currentdir = cd cd /home/cboettig/.matlab/MDPSOLVE addpath(genpath(cd)) cd /home/cboettig/.matlab/plot2svg addpath(genpath(cd)) cd(currentdir)  (I still find matlab/octave&amp;rsquo;s syntax of not distinguishing character strings from variable names from function names kind of terrifying, but I guess that&amp;rsquo;s the price of working with economists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/04/07/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/07/notes/</guid>
      <description>ropensci Working on proposal. Discussion of section 2: other players in the domain (or rather, the many community interfaces with rOpenSci).
other  Discussion with Hadley re: API testing and test_if functionality, see testthat/141.
 Related with Hadley discussion on handling tests and keys for API packages, httr/93
 Software Carpentry developing R lessons
  rfishbase Add FAO areas (from 04/05), see rfishbase/20
EML  Discussion of unit handling, feedback from Karen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/03/31/ropenhack-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/31/ropenhack-notes/</guid>
      <description>Breakfast  discussion of what makes an API good or a total pain discussion of extending data.set class with metadata  Morning Session Chatting with Hadley:
Best practices for R client packages to REST APIs  (When) Do we return response call metadata? Very modular function construction Error handling, assertthat checks Explicit parsing, as seperate function. e.g. Better alternatives in place of require when loading SUGGESTS lists, which still pollutes the namespace; see examples in httr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/03/24/review-of-progress-on-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/24/review-of-progress-on-packages/</guid>
      <description>A lot of the past week has been focused on some catching up and tidying up in my active projects in metadata manipulation and publishing tools, EML, RNeXML, and rfigshare. The full story of the week and half unfolds on github, but summarizing progress here.
rfigshare Changes to httr interface orginally broke rfigshare, though working with @hadley the original mechanism was restored through sign_oauth1.0(). The changes provided a much nicer mechanism for handling oauth authentication without having to specify tokens directly, and resulted in a relatively straightforward overhaul of the authentication mechanism in the package, while still preserving the package API.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/03/18/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/18/notes/</guid>
      <description>ropensci  Ensuring interoperability in R / ropensci projects. See pre-hackathon discussion: ropensci/hackathon/issues/#20 rfigshare to use new oauth interface of httr, see rfigshare/#72 Ugh. More fun with travis integration on RNeXML RNeXML/#61  pdg-control / policycosts  Started tidying up this repo&amp;rsquo;s manuscript folder a bit.
 Merge Paul&amp;rsquo;s various changes on tex and Word documents into Rmd  Misc  Whoops. Couldn&amp;rsquo;r resist a wee rant on G+, 2014-03-02 on this #PLOSfail discussion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/03/10/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/10/notes/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML merge travis integration with support for rrdf. See pull #57 Reply to Perry re nonparametric approaches 10am Andrew Skype meeting re: his manuscript rOpenSci discussion re: other services, formats. Reading Caldwell et al, Geophysical Letters. Good example of naiive data mining leading to spurious correlations from non-independent models. (/ht @FreshwaterEcology Looking over NSF&amp;rsquo;s Data Infrastructure Building Blocks, DIBB call and previously funded work.
 Remote control for Ubuntu via android?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/03/07/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/07/notes/</guid>
      <description>Thursday  Reading through Andrew&amp;rsquo;s manuscript Working on RNeXML checks / travis continuous integration. Completing documentation, updating unit tests to reflect recent API changes.
 Difficulty getting taxize dependency to pass travis check. Needed these lines in travis:  - sudo apt-get install gdal-bin libgdal1 libgdal1-dev netcdf-bin libproj-dev - ./travis-tool.sh install_aptget gdal-bin   Interview with Nature Careers journalist Amanda, discussing open notebook and open science developments  Friday  Finish up RNeXML checks / travis integration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/01/31/weekly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/31/weekly-review/</guid>
      <description>EML  bug fixes and replies to various input from community on EML package
 Thoughts on understanding and using EML in research, including Dryad. See https://github.com/ropensci/EML/issues/82#issuecomment-33558301
  multiple-uncertainty Jim and Mike meeting  Why the steps in the optimal solution of the deterministic case? Irregularities in value function in first iteration: sometimes not exact ties; actually preferring to fish at almost 0 rather than 0.
 address range constraints on h and x.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/01/07/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/07/notes/</guid>
      <description>Coding  fishbase API discussions rfishbase updates pushed to CRAN Merges and minor bug fixes for rfigshare
 RNeXML: After some cooperative sleuth-work, we successfully resolved issue #23, uncovering a bug (missing feature really) in xmllint.
  as usual, detailed activity on github.
Reading  The sudden collapse of pollinator communities - Jelle Lever - 2014 - Ecology Letters - Wiley Online Library http://goo.gl/ZKuKsj Github has traffic stats again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/01/06/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/06/notes/</guid>
      <description>fishbase API discussions knitcitations (push previous updates to CRAN) data extraction from sardine collapse story (see EML in data/), news article My thoughts on SWC teaching web-native publication workflow reading, ToCs speaker invitation replies review request replies  Reading  &amp;ldquo;Are rapid transitions btwn invasive and native species caused by alt stable states, and does it matter?&amp;rdquo; http://feedly.com/k/1gbEIWT
 &amp;ldquo;Phylogenetic trait-based analyses of ecological networks.&amp;rdquo; http://feedly.com/k/1gbEvD6
 Nice editorial on &amp;ldquo;core elements of a TPB paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/26/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/26/notes/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML Character metadata EML provides a nice illustration of the kind of metadata we would want to typically accompany character trait data; at minimum, at the attribute level.
Some of this is already there &amp;ndash; we know if states are continuous or discrete, what possible states they can take on, and can add labels to state nodes to define what the symbols mean (however, perhaps an additional meta annotation node would be preferred).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/19/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/19/notes/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML  Feedback from Rutger, need to add about attributes so that RDFa abstraction references the right level of the DOM (issue #35).
 Looking for strategy for distilling RDF from RDFa in R, see my question on SO. Hopefully don&amp;rsquo;t have to wrap some C library myself&amp;hellip;  nonparametric-bayes Writing writing.
 Update pandoc templates to use yaml metadata for author, affiliation, abstract, etc. Avoids having to manually edit the elsarticle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/17/rnexml-metadata-queries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/17/rnexml-metadata-queries/</guid>
      <description>(From issue #20)
Basic metadata queries a question of how the user queries that metadata. Currently we have a metadata function that simply extracts all the metadata at the specified level (nexml, otus, trees, tree, etc) and returns a named character string in which the name corresponds to the rel or property and the value corresponds to the content or href, e.g.:
birds &amp;lt;- read.nexml(&amp;quot;birdOrders.xml&amp;quot;) meta &amp;lt;- get_metadata(birds)  prints the named string with the top-level (default-level) metadata elements as so:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/14/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/14/notes/</guid>
      <description>ropensci  ropensci stategic planning: wrote personal vision statement  RNeXML  Comments on issues #12 and #15, thinking about character matrices comments on #20, thinking about metadata parsing. (If only everyone knew xpath&amp;hellip;)  Commit details on Github</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/08/mbi-day-five-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/08/mbi-day-five-notes/</guid>
      <description>Panel discussion
 Hugh&amp;rsquo;s question on the usefulness of dynamic vs static models: do we have dynamical systems envy? Chris: are temporal dynamics historical artefact, and space the new frontier? Hugh: though decision theory is fundamentally temporal. really question of sequential decision vs single decision Hugh, on what would be his priority if he had time for new question: Solve the 2 player, 2 step SDP competition closed form.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/05/mbi-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/05/mbi-day-two/</guid>
      <description>MBI Workshop Paul Armsworth Very nice example of control in creating a market for ecosystem services for landowners. Key feature is that multiple land-owners respond by adjusting their prices, and so payments can be divided into fraction going into subsidy and fraction going into conservation. When one land-owner controls land that is particularly good cost per conservation accomplished, they also stand to gain largest value.
Also looked at auction mechanism and impact of cooperation among landowners to create hold outs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/04/mbi-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/04/mbi-notes/</guid>
      <description>SUSTAINABLE MANAGEMENT OF LIVING NATURAL RESOURCES  Description Full Schedule Participants  Introductions Hastings Lou Gross  Big picture: big data, computational challenges.
 NEON, DataONE, ADW, iDigBio &amp;ldquo;Convergence&amp;rdquo; as the new interdisciplinary (National Academies) Rise of synthesis centers &amp;ldquo;Enabling architecture for next gen life science research&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; National Academies report Lou Gross (2013) Comp Science for Natural Resource Management &amp;ndash; Fuller, Wang, Gross (2007)
 language barriers: What&amp;rsquo;s a model?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/10/17/rnexml-semantic-considerations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/17/rnexml-semantic-considerations/</guid>
      <description>Some very good feedback from Hilmar as I tackle some of the semantic capabilities of NeXML in RNeXML. As the complete discussion is already archived in the Github issues tracking, (see in particular #26 and #24) I only paraphrase here.
One of the central advantages we can offer in programmatic generation of NeXML in the R environment is the ability to validate names and enhance the metadata included in the resulting nexml file using programmatic queries to taxonomic name resolution services such as ITIS, EOL, NCBI, as provided in the taxize package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/10/16/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/16/notes/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML  Example methods for metadata: https://github.com/ropensci/RNeXML/issues/20#issuecomment-26457772 Closes #19 https://github.com/ropensci/RNeXML/issues/19#issuecomment-26459110 Discussion of best identifiers for OTUs #24. Now waiting on Scott for choice of implementation  Misc R puzzle In R&amp;rsquo;s S4 methods, I can define methods with different signatures, i.e. different object classes for the same function call. But can I alter the names and number of arguments for a method?
As usual, see Github for details on commits and issues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/10/10/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/10/notes/</guid>
      <description>Authenticating via DataOne API Matt Jones provides a nice dataone package to handle accessing and posting data to DataOne nodes such as the KNB from R. Uploading files through the API requires authentication, which in turn requires a certificate from CILogin. As this process proved a bit tricky to me, I add some documentation here. I am using a Ubuntu (13.04) system, so the procedure might differ slightly for other systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/10/09/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/09/notes/</guid>
      <description>ugh, most journals don&amp;rsquo;t seem to hold to their own data publication policies.
PNAS theoretically endorses UPSIDE, r citet(&amp;quot;10.1073/pnas.0400437101&amp;quot;) principles from the National Academy of Science:
 Principle 1. Authors should include in their publications the data, algorithms, or other information that is central or integral to the publication—that is, whatever is necessary to support the major claims of the paper and would enable one skilled in the art to verify or replicate the claims.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extending ape::phylo class to NeXML:</title>
      <link>/2013/10/07/nexml-phylo-class-extension/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/07/nexml-phylo-class-extension/</guid>
      <description>While working on the RNeXML package, I have recently I have been puzzling over extending S3 objects to share some of the nice properties of S4 objects and methods while continuing to function with the potentially huge library of functions written to work with them. SO:
To illustrate this issue, consider the S3 class phylo provided by the ape package and used by most of the 30+ packages that reverse depend or reverse import ape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/23/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/23/notes/</guid>
      <description>nonparametric bayes Reading  Arnqvist, G. 2013 Editorial rejects? Novelty, schnovelty! Trends in ecology &amp;amp; evolution 28, 448-9. (doi:10.1016/j.tree.2013.05.007) Accounting for Complementarity to Maximize Monitoring Power for Species Management. 27, 988-999. (doi:10.1111/cobi.12092) Nes, E. H. Van, Hirota, M., Holmgren, M. &amp;amp; Scheffer, M. 2013 Tipping points in tropical tree cover: linking theory to data. (doi:10.1111/gcb.12398) Millar, R. B. 2002 Reference priors for Bayesian fisheries models. , 1492-1502. (doi:10.1139/F02-108) Mcallister, M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/19/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/19/notes/</guid>
      <description>writing manuscript slides data request to Glaser.
  gpdd  Global Popluation Dynamics Database initiated package rgpdd data extraction &amp;ndash; No API, but does provide direct dump in the form of a Microsoft Access mdb database. For the moment I&amp;rsquo;m using mdbtools: mdb-tables and mdb-extract to convert to CSV and then reading those into R. RODBC package installs but cannot read the database directly for me. Since data will fit into working memory no real reason to support database calls from R?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/18/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/18/notes/</guid>
      <description>nonparametric-bayes writing writing. see commits. Started slides for Mangel group retreat. (in progress). Working on requested review&amp;hellip; background reading too. reml read methods for data.set class, extending attributeList metadata tools.
  Scribble notes for interivew  we are where math was 400 years ago - present theorem without proof.
 code plays an ever-increasing role in our research, and hence in describing what we have done potentially the most precise and consise way to describe a method.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/16/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/16/notes/</guid>
      <description>class=&#34;task-list&#34; finish up and push backlog of notebook updates knitcitations slidify (issue 46) recently resolved several further issues/requests with rfishbase  ropensci Have implemented a solution to extending data.frame with metadata that I was tackling the other day. This raises several open questions on how we do the implementation, including whether we restrict this extension to providing the attributeList-level metadata (or a subset thereof), or if we allow higher level nodes of eml to act as extensions of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/08/some-rfishbase-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/08/some-rfishbase-updates/</guid>
      <description>Ever since writing the rfishbase package I&amp;rsquo;ve been frustrated by the lack of a proper API from Fishbase.org that would allow access to that wealth of information that is not exposed in the &amp;ldquo;Summary XML&amp;rdquo; files from which rfishbase extracts its content. Since writing the paper in Journal of Fish Biology, I continue to receive user requests asking if or how such-and-such a data element might be extracted. Usually this involves a disappointing boiler-plate reply about how the package is limited to the &amp;ldquo;Summary XML&amp;rdquo; data and that improved query potential must wait for a proper API from Fishbase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/07/rnexml-milestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/07/rnexml-milestone/</guid>
      <description>We have also recently reached the first milestone in RNeXML. We can now read NeXML files into R and convert to the popular phylo format from the ape package, as well as writing the ape::phylo trees out into valid NeXML. We can also add basic metadata such as author, license, title and description to the file.
Development notes At the heart of this package is an internal S4 representation of the schema.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/02/reml-milestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/02/reml-milestone/</guid>
      <description>Reached a milestone in reml development today with basic implementation of reading, writing, and publishing valid EML files and a working test suite.
An S4-based structure This involved a complete re-write of the pre-ESA code and is now completely S4-class based, allowing a more flexible structure that is easier and faster to extend. For instance, rather than having to explicitly think about the commands to parse and serialize a new metadata element that needs to be added from the schema, we just define the class for the object.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/08/28/rnexml-coding/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/28/rnexml-coding/</guid>
      <description>test_ape.R unit tests now passing. Should still revise the coercion methods in nexml_write.R to something more clever. We aren&amp;rsquo;t coercing a tree to a nexml, we are building a nexml from a tree. Likewise handling the otu assignments of species names should be done directly 11:20 am 2013/08/28 start cleaning up old read/write methods obsoleted by toNeXML/fromNeXML methods 10:59 am 2013/08/28 inherited classes now replace all the original classes 10:54 am 2013/08/28 All inheritance-based classes appearing in inst/examples/trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/08/26/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/26/notes/</guid>
      <description>misc tricks Always forget how to see the function definition of an S4 method:
showMethods(&amp;quot;xmlToS4&amp;quot;, includeDefs=TRUE)  ropensci  Closed rfigshare issue #50 Still retooling reml to S4 and ReXML to inheritance-based S4 classes building classes on the schema&amp;rsquo;s inheritance model 10:49 am 2013/08/26  In behavioral ecology we usually equate optimality with expected behavior arising from natural selection &amp;ndash; i.e. the extent to which the observed behavior deviates from the optimal behavior is assumed to be due to modeling inaccuracies (optimizing the wrong thing).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/08/01/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/01/notes/</guid>
      <description>Registered for AmNat 2014 conference in Asilomar.
 Nice collection Data Visualization pieces from Nature Methods. vim clipboard: put older items from clipboard history using: &amp;quot;0p, &amp;quot;1p, &amp;quot;2p. See list in :reg. (from here) #ESA2013 Lotka-Volterra Talks Review methods to write S4 back to XML  from earlier:
misc reading  Duncan Hull&amp;rsquo;s Seven deadly sins of bioinformatics Carole&amp;rsquo;s Goble&amp;rsquo;s talk at ismb, as summarized in graphical form Interesting: researchobject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/07/25/formal-semantics-with-reml/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/25/formal-semantics-with-reml/</guid>
      <description>A lot has been happening in the reml development over on our package Github page, particularly through discussion on the issues tracker we have been working through several of the major conceptual challenges in designing the package.
Semantics Writing Semantics. Lots of elements of the EML schema have semantic meaning, but we can&amp;rsquo;t start leveraging ontological tools while these terms are defined only as part of the Schema vocabulary. In their current state, they are just &amp;ldquo;meaningless bits of syntax&amp;rdquo;, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/07/22/xml-parsing-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/22/xml-parsing-strategies/</guid>
      <description>Writing out some advice for our GSOC student on XML parsing. (Now filed as RNeXML/#11
Here is some quick background on different ways we might go about extracting NeXML into an R object we want to work with. We can use S4 classes, R&amp;rsquo;s native data.frame and list types, or extract specific terms of interest with xpath. I illustrate each of these below using the example &amp;ldquo;trees.xml&amp;rdquo; in your repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes from chat with Duncan</title>
      <link>/2013/07/19/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/19/notes/</guid>
      <description>Keep metadata as part of the object Recursion problem coming up.
  Validating:  https://github.com/ropensci/reml/issues/7 Duncan has code using Matt&amp;rsquo;s java API If the EML isn&amp;rsquo;t valid, so what? Important for developers, users don&amp;rsquo;t care.
  API design  what&amp;rsquo;s with the do.call? This forces evaluation, can mess up lazyLoading, making for inefficient function handling.
 Schema to create S4 objects Create R objects first, and then toXML</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/07/08/reml-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/08/reml-update/</guid>
      <description>Made substanial progress on the reml project. We have reached our first milestone, being able to:
 Successfully validate the EML generated (#28) Start a unit test suite write eml unit tests (#14) Extract appropriate R objects from EML dataTable read eml (#6) Add function to publish EML data through figshare publish eml (#3) Generate an EML file given a data.frame and appropriate metadata write eml (#2)  As illustrated by the example shown in the Readme:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/06/26/starting-an-eml-package-for-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/26/starting-an-eml-package-for-r/</guid>
      <description>Started reml, and R package for reading, writing, manipulating and publishing EML files. More details and progress so far on the Github page; in particular flushing out design goals in the issues tracker.
Initial goals To start, I am aiming for a proof of principle case in which we can write an R data.frame into EML (issue #2), publish to a remote repository such as figshare (issue #3), and then read the data back in as the original R object types from the EML (issue #6).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/06/24/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/24/notes/</guid>
      <description>Exploring XML Schema in R I danced around the room after reading these lines in the excellent XML and Web Technologies for Data Sciences with R book:
 We can generate S4 class definitions corresponding to the data structures that are represented in the XML document. We can programmatically generate R code that will map an XML document adhering to this schema to corresponding R data structures. Similarly, we can automate the creation of code to serialize, or write, an R object of a particular type to a suitable XML format corresponding to the schema</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/06/23/notes-on-leveraging-the-ecological-markup-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/23/notes-on-leveraging-the-ecological-markup-language/</guid>
      <description>This post creates new tag eml for posts discussing the Ecological Markup Langauge or the implementation of an R parser thereof (reml).
Why EML? Jones et al.(2005) give an excellent explanation describing the relative advantage of the descriptive metadata approach over vertically integrated repositories (such as Genbank, TreeBase, or many other repostories that have been the focus of rOpenSci development to date).
In short, the EML approach allows archiving of very heterogeneous data without having to standardize everything into a narrow and pre-defined syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/06/13/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/13/notes/</guid>
      <description>Assembling various loose ends and some ropensci work.
Misc things to work out and write at some date  Catch up on literature reading (unsorted list in Mendeley). Get entries into notebook.
 Write thoughts on selecting links anchor text in the notebook knitr script workflow: externalizing chunks, cache and figure prefixes.
 branching projects and unique repositories source code for all manuscripts into repositories clean up directories. in particular, establish separate prosecutors-fallacy repository Comments on workflow: Date-oriented (notebook) vs File-oriented (Github) explanation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/05/20/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/05/20/notes/</guid>
      <description>EWS TE revisions  Finalized manuscript(?) Checking references, reply letter, closing remaining issues.
 Very annoying to submit to a journal system that takes LaTeX but not any external style or class file dependencies. For instance, how does one add two footnotes to the same author without adding any such dependencies (oh, and writing macros that do not involve pairs of $ which pandoc mistakes for its own macros&amp;hellip;) Reasonable author affiliations done otherwise using \and, \thanks, and \footnotemark; see [simple.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/04/17/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/17/notes/</guid>
      <description>warning-signals  Finishing up edits. Writing PRSB reply  Logistics  In tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s Marc meeting, check in about what to include for the CSTAR report manuscript / analysis updates Comments on recent lit?  ropensci  treebase/#4  Reading  Dai et. al. (2013) , with introductory piece by Carpenter (2013) . In this they look only at the spatial extent of a perturbation. Presumbably one might attempt to compare the spatial extent over time to establish a baseline, or otherwise identify a control system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collected notes from past few days</title>
      <link>/2013/03/19/collected-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/19/collected-notes/</guid>
      <description>Friday  some ropensci coordination Adapt basic science abstract and broader impacts statement some writing on notebook features draft nonparametric writing!  Monday  nonparametric-bayes writing. Combining my generic position piece (beyond-mechanistic-models.Rmd) with the technical nonparametric-bayes writeup (nonparametric-bayes.Rmd) to get a more general-audience paper.
 ropensci reviewing Note: annoying feature of knitr&amp;rsquo;s purl: appears to generate valid &amp;ldquo;external&amp;rdquo; knitr code, but includes all options in comment headers instead of just the chunk names.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/14/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/14/notes/</guid>
      <description>Research  consolidate and revise EWS text(?) replies to Luke and Brian on model choice  Notebook meta  fix google-analytics plugin (still needs to get toggle working?) tests of notebook-parsing.Rmd. New errors on ; somehow in straight XML parsing, ignoring for the moment. Opened a few new issues around improving site semantics. (#59, #60)  ropensci  Resubmit rfishbase &amp;ndash; silently load to local, not global namespace. Updated data cache (and ASCII-ify and compress).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/13/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/13/notes/</guid>
      <description>ropensci  rfishbase: 0.1-1 released to CRAN: bugfix updating server address. (Broke updateCache()). See NEWS for details.
 rfigshare: 0.2-4 released to CRAN: added method to remove attached files (issue #42), see NEWS for details  Misc  My reply to John on Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy piece. Thinking about a better way to provide convenient, stable access to code and data. Should provide csv versions of data.table outputs used to create each of the figures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/12/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/12/notes/</guid>
      <description>Writing  Working on nonparametric-bayes.  Reading Interesting PNAS comment from Doney &amp;amp; Sailley, (2013) (&amp;ldquo;When an ecological regime shift is really just stochastic noise&amp;rdquo;) on the Di Lorenzo &amp;amp; Ohman, (2013) piece in the same issue, showing that time integrated zooplankton data correlates closely with environmental drivers: in this case, the pacific decadal oscillation (PDO) index, which would be missed by the traditional approach of direct correlations. This refutes the previous explanation of such shifts observed in the krill populations as being driven by nonlinear ecological interactions, rather than merely linearly tracking the environment ((Hare &amp;amp; Mantua, 2000)).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <link>/2012/05/10/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/05/10/notes/</guid>
      <description>Partially Observable Stochastic Processes (cont.)  Reading a bit more about pomp. Looks like SCM and PMCMC offer nicely Bayesian inference tools using the same framework (rprocess and dmeasure), making a nice platform for implementing multiple methods. Almost feels like having the likelihood equation in hand again. A bit more skeptical about nonlinear forecasting and probe matching, as they feel even more heuristic or arbitrary. I suppose that&amp;rsquo;s just the price of having only rmeasure instead of dmeasure available though.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2012-04-20</title>
      <link>/2012/04/26/2012-04-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2012 13:32:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/26/2012-04-20/</guid>
      <description>Warning Signals Warning signals paper accepted. Making minor edits before submitting final copy.
Added Alan&amp;rsquo;s edits.
 Review model section again Letter: Response to reviewers Create Diff Media Summary Submit  Done!
Database papers  rfishbase edits made, reformatting in word, sent to Peter Ethics form, recommended reviewers, cover letter. Submit  Done!
Misc NERSC web directory: create www in /project/projectdirs/m1366 NSF Arctic SEES grants
 These larger, integrated efforts would promote understanding of Arctic systems and would develop optimized models, multiple stable state scenarios, sustainable pathways, decision matrices, visualization techniques and data infrastructure to aid decision making and communication, and structural, energy and communications technology solutions which would inform community practices, management, and policy for a more sustainable Arctic environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catching up</title>
      <link>/2012/04/19/catching-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 10:39:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/19/catching-up/</guid>
      <description>Catching up on notebook entries for last week and the beginning of this week in one go here. In the process of wrapping up a variety of older projects, so this is kinda all over the place.
rfishbase  Create function table, finalize functions Add support for references. Done, see getRefs. (And isn&amp;rsquo;t it awesome that you can link to a specific linenumber (i.e. line 280) in github by adding #L280 to the end of the url?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday / Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 23:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday/</guid>
      <description>rfishbase updated to Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback writing intro section on Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy. wrightscape update project repository. Scripts mostly in demos, results in notebook. Notebook makes is easy to get the most recent writeup on the topic, from where I can start to track back the history, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide a good at-a-glance view of the analyses I&amp;rsquo;ve run side-by-side. Moving the R script demos/ into markdown knitted files in inst/examples/ and rerunning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/06/friday-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2012 21:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/06/friday-8/</guid>
      <description>Fishbase  Revisions based on Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback Formatting to Journal of Fish Biology guidelines Updated formatting   fixed footnotes issue in pdf version. Externalize tables in word version.
  knit_hooks$set(chunk = function(x, options) { if (!options$split) return(x) cat(x, file = fig_path(&#39;.md&#39;, options)) }   Consider more intuitive function names rather than function arguments?  TreeBase  Needs additional functions replacing sapply queries and argument queries. Table of functions re-organize presentation  rOpenSci GSOC GSoC applications were due at noon today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday/Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/03/mondaytuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 15:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/03/mondaytuesday/</guid>
      <description>knitr + markdown + pandoc + latex Troubleshooting this workflow still&amp;hellip;
 Fonts xtable for html &amp;amp; latex/pdf xtable comments display tikz device trouble Pandoc table trouble pandoc footnotes Getting a satisfactory LaTeX template.
 Makefile   writing writing writing: Mostly writing this week, so my notebook has been lacking in entries. Trying to move several manuscripts forward: two are papers accompanying software packages for extracting, manipulating and visualizing data from online repositories (TreeBase and FishBase); part of the rOpenSci project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: pandoc citations notes, various</title>
      <link>/2012/03/27/tuesday-pandoc-citations-notes-various/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 22:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/27/tuesday-pandoc-citations-notes-various/</guid>
      <description>Markdown over latex? knitr may have solved the fundamental challenge of all Sweave/latex users with Markdown. Too many of us must be able to work with collaborators who don&amp;rsquo;t know LaTeX and journals that won&amp;rsquo;t accept LaTeX. It&amp;rsquo;s a sad state of the affairs, and has improved slowly for journals (at least many will take pdfs for initial submissions) if not for collaborators. Consequently getting away from LaTeX would be nice, but Word or Google docs just won&amp;rsquo;t cut it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/03/06/tuesday-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2012 19:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/06/tuesday-14/</guid>
      <description>Confirm travel plans for tomorrow  pdg-control  Stability analysis speeding up policycosts (extra loop) will probably require some C coding. Meanwhile could hard-code in the profit function to accelerate things.
 model averaging (mimic the fisheries science work &amp;amp; climate models that present distribution of outcomes over different models as the range of possibilities, lacking probabilities assigned to those models&amp;hellip;). work on model estimation externalization: Note that we can tangle a file to create a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/02/27/monday-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 15:20:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/27/monday-14/</guid>
      <description>Warning Signals  Added resulting indicator distributions on finer sampling results.
 Re-running now excluding the final dive (population below 300).
  Treebase working on manuscript. A few examples using the improved meta-data queries:
Computing configuration vim and R  install vim-r-plugin. Download, then run vim-addons install r-plugin install screen plugin add to .vimrc:   set nocompatible syntax enable filetype plugin on filetype indent on let vimrplugin_underscore = 0   learn some key bindings Really \rf to launch, and \d Also see this post for configuration with vim-latex-suite.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2012/02/22/wednesday-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 20:20:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/22/wednesday-12/</guid>
      <description>CC0 license approved for use on CRAN
 Update my DESCRIPTION files, use the new Author@R convention.
 Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s comment on mntd in comparative methods
 This lab notebook gets mentioned for good practices in academic workflow.
 Working on treebase paper
 ESA registration
 Lecture notes for tomorrow
 forage fish writing
  Reading Reading over (Munch et. al. 2005). I think this is a very nice treatment, a lot clearer I think than lots of other stuff I&amp;rsquo;ve looked at (thanks Tim &amp;amp; Jim!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Research, seminar (managing for resilience), talk (future of libraries), etc...</title>
      <link>/2012/02/21/tues-research-seminar-managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 19:20:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/21/tues-research-seminar-managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</guid>
      <description>research Stuff warningsignals  Exceeded wall time on NERSC, readjusting and running this again.  treebase  Working on treebase manuscript. Treebase Rewrote handling of server errors, added pauses to reduce load, etc.  PMC  A user pointed out my support for &amp;ldquo;white&amp;rdquo; model was incomplete. Fix is now on github (install instructions for development version are also now on github), will push to CRAN soon.
 Another user points out that pmc support for additional functions would be nice, such as rbrownie, fit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday: projects, reading, markdown notebook-technology</title>
      <link>/2012/02/12/saturday-projects-reading-markdown-plugins/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 13:40:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/12/saturday-projects-reading-markdown-plugins/</guid>
      <description>Greatly enjoyed seeing this perspective on power laws (Stumpf &amp;amp; Porter, 2012) Or as Richard McElreath put even more concisely,
 People get amazed by power laws but never by normal distributions. Seems like some max ent outcomes astonish while others don&amp;rsquo;t. When so many mechanisms aggregate to common densities, I&amp;rsquo;d hope we&amp;rsquo;d stop trying to argue that we can go backwards from pattern to process so easily.
 Projects  fishbase example query for Peter Commit edits to warningsignals paper, send to Alan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2012/02/02/thursday-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2012 22:14:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/02/thursday-13/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci  Dryad submission xml parsing example to Scott essentially see (fishbase example , and xpath tutoral ) knitr and latex figure placement (use float package with H to enforce placement). cc0 &amp;amp; OSI &amp;hellip; pmc purchase order, dryad data id approval. &amp;amp; writing writing writing&amp;hellip; Re-formating data for ggplot version of graphs, realized I should be specifying id.vars to melt (example from my Q on SO)  Reading  Great special feature on the data era in TREE ((which I mention despite it&amp;rsquo;s misfortune of being connected to Elsivier right now)) (Page, 2012), (Michener &amp;amp; Jones, 2012), (Porter et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday -- meetings</title>
      <link>/2012/01/18/wednesday-meetings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 23:22:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/18/wednesday-meetings/</guid>
      <description>Alan meeting write write write
Duncan Meeting Troubleshooting S3 and S4 Try adding methods? Changing order on NAMESPACE?
Leaving ouch off the import list: no errors, but within functions, don&amp;rsquo;t get S4 method. import but don&amp;rsquo;t depend on ouch: error. accurate, since simulate is left as an s3 function at the user level.
What a headache. See stackQ.
manuscript Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback
Meredith Meeting Run a science policy workshop with Davis open science group?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/12/12/monday-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 19:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/12/monday-12/</guid>
      <description>Wrote method2 test functions out in knitr/sweave. Sent document to Peter. Move my ropensci git origins to the ropensci github page. Ropensci comments on \dontrun: recommended for anything non-trivial, including web calls. Richer tests should be put into testthat. Reply to Charles Jervis, biology high school teacher interested in tools to teach math/modeling in ecology. Sounds like he&amp;rsquo;s already doing some cool stuff with phylogenies with his students. prepare vignette for rfishbase based on tutorial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - various logistics, then checking likelihood calculation</title>
      <link>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2011 20:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci  rOpenSci wins runner up prize in PLoS + Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s Binary Battle! Write replies to interview questions with Mendeley. roxygenizing documentation for RMendeley &amp;ndash; about half done  pdg-control  Call with Jake scheduled for tomorrow Emails with Michael. I&amp;rsquo;ll implement delay intervals, he&amp;rsquo;ll add costs to adjustment. Need to fix/finish delay interval optimization calculation (exponent of matrix &amp;amp; beta)  Warning Signals Meeting with Alan
 Regime shifts Emphasize the RO curve in uncertainty analysis See (Dulvy et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2011/10/25/treebase-package-on-cran/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2011 19:06:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/25/treebase-package-on-cran/</guid>
      <description>My treebase package is now up on the CRAN repository. (Source code is up, the binaries should appear soon). Here&amp;rsquo;s a few introductory examples to illustrate some of the functionality of the package. Thanks in part to new data deposition requirements at journals such as Evolution, Am Nat, and Sys Bio, and data management plan requirements from NSF, I hope the package will become increasingly useful for teaching by replicating results and for meta-analyses that can be automatically updated as the repository grows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday, Fisheries course</title>
      <link>/2011/10/13/thursday-fisheries-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2011 13:28:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/13/thursday-fisheries-course/</guid>
      <description>Fisheries impact on forage fish. Forage fish impact on the primary fisheries.
 Huxley, 1882: &amp;ldquo;Great Sea Fisheries cannot be exhausted&amp;rdquo; (full address) Worm et al., 2006: All fish will collapse by 2050 (Worm et. al. 2006)  Benguela Current upwelling (Anchovy collapse)
Discussion of: Prey switching impact?
Wasp-waist ecosystems
Ecopath/ecosim vs Atlantis
Questions:
Can we identify the nature of control?
Importance of wasp-waist control.
regime switching
Negative impact of forage fish on ground fish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/10/12/wednesday-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 22:01:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/12/wednesday-10/</guid>
      <description>8:30 gist - flush swap. Catalyst grant review. 9-9:30 SCHA stuff 9:30 - query roc curve thresholds 10 - 10:30 post rfishbase update 10:30 http://openfisheries.org/ 11:15 back to roc curves. noon. curves threshold reading done. lunch.  PNAS writing, examples.
Adding more Drake-data examples: on farm, running G10 and G6.
 1pm-2pm domes 2pm back to writing  Launch additional data runs: deut2, trying in series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rfishbase Tutorial - updated &amp; extended</title>
      <link>/2011/10/12/rfishbase-tutorial-updated-extended/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 11:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/12/rfishbase-tutorial-updated-extended/</guid>
      <description>Updated rfishbase package. Include querying for a list of scientific names and the addition of more quantitative traits, though the selection is still somewhat limited. Demo includes how to grab some data to match a phylogenetic tree, and some regular expression (grep) searches for feeding behavior.
Source code
Windows binary also available.
# demo.R rm(list=ls()) require(rfishbase) ###### Grabbing, Loading &amp;amp; Caching Fishbase Data ###### ## Download and parse data for first 40 ids (36 fish) #fish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: ropensci, manuscript edits</title>
      <link>/2011/09/23/friday-ropensci-manuscript-edits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2011 11:03:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/23/friday-ropensci-manuscript-edits/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci Conference Call Catalyst grant  Reviewed budget. Karthik will merge current proposals, Carl will review. Goal: send out next week. Ask Mark Hahnel to look it over  Blog posts  Carley planning to make guest blog post within the next week.  Mendeley/Plos Binary battle  Carl will file entry form. Karthik push edits to rplos Scott will add rplos tutorial to ropensci.org Carl will add rmendeley tutorial to ropensci.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rfishbase demo: Are there more Goby or Labrid species on reefs?</title>
      <link>/2011/09/02/rfishbase-demo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2011 12:59:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/02/rfishbase-demo/</guid>
      <description>I have updated the package to 0.0-3 alpha, having all the target functionality now. Improved error handling, downloading of data, processing. Get the source or windows binary here. I now download the full database and cache it locally for faster querying. Just about any kind of manipulation is then possible and fast.
For instance, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick demo based on a question from Peter Wainwright: &amp;ldquo;are there more gobys or labrids on reefs?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rropensci and some taxonomy in R with taxize</title>
      <link>/2011/08/26/rfishbase-and-some-taxonomy-in-r-with-taxize/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 23:16:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/26/rfishbase-and-some-taxonomy-in-r-with-taxize/</guid>
      <description>rfishbase Went through demo of rfishbase with Tomomi. Improved error handling, added a few data types and a few use cases.
I always forget that I have to drop nulls by indexing, not my return values of sapply.
x[!sapply(x, is.null)]  Very annoyed with fishbase id numbers (being discontinuous listings and unable to query xml by anything more intelligent). Querying all fishbase ids 1:30000, I get only 999 fish. hmm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FishBASE from R: some XML parsing</title>
      <link>/2011/08/26/fishbase-from-r-some-xml-parsing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 10:51:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/26/fishbase-from-r-some-xml-parsing/</guid>
      <description>cross-posted from Wainwright Lab blog, archiving in the notebook here. This early tutorial includes some background on XML parsing from R using XPath. See the later rfishbase tutorial for more functionality.
In lab known for its quality data collection, high-speed video style, writing the weekly blog post can be a bit of a challenge for the local code monkey. That&amp;rsquo;s right, no videos today. But lucky for me, even this group can still make good use of publicly available data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: rropensci, Rmpi, manuscripts, ...</title>
      <link>/2011/08/23/tuesday-rfishbase-rmpi-manuscripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2011 15:10:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/23/tuesday-rfishbase-rmpi-manuscripts/</guid>
      <description>rfishbase In answer to Tomomi&amp;rsquo;s question from last week, have basic functionality as an R package on github, rfishbase. Learned some slightly richer XML parsing in the process.
XML Notes Had to identify blocks by a child node that specifies the identity, and then find the sibling node that contains the content I needed. Goes something like this:
&amp;lt;dataObject&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dc:identifier&amp;gt;FB-Size-2&amp;lt;/dc:identifier&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dc:description&amp;gt; Text I need &amp;lt;/dc:description&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dataObject&amp;gt;  Which I parsed in R as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: reviewing edits, ropensci, computers.</title>
      <link>/2011/08/18/thursday-reviewing-edits-fishbase-computers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2011 15:03:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/18/thursday-reviewing-edits-fishbase-computers/</guid>
      <description>Graham &amp;amp; Peter meeting Going over review and figuring out how to address issues. Plan: Will write our line-by-line responses under the reviewer comments in the Google Doc. Peter and I will implement remaining changes on the .tex file, then we&amp;rsquo;ll compose the reply letter from the notes under the comments and include the latex-diff.
Brief topic notes from today&amp;rsquo;s meeting:
 set up different take on layout: lambda, AIC, power</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#ievobio Day 2</title>
      <link>/2011/06/22/ievobio-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 23:44:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/22/ievobio-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Day 2 is every bit as packed as day 1, and then some do to the higher concentration of lightning talks. Other coverage of #ievobio is starting to find it&amp;rsquo;s way to the web:
 Nico Cellinese
 Scott Chamberlain
 Rob Guralnick
  Meanwhile, my scratchpad of notes from day 2, tweet-style.
My Lightning Talk Gave my lightning talk in this session, slides:
R interface to TreeBASE</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/06/03/friday-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 17:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/03/friday-5/</guid>
      <description>A day&amp;rsquo;s agenda  Scott&amp;rsquo;s got us going on aR package forPLoS API, released Tuesday. Checked over the package and did some basic reorganization to put it in R package form. lots of feedback on my FF question on pw vs private for delayed-disclosure entries. warning signals manuscript package, figures, writing 9-11a Going through Peter&amp;rsquo;s revisions 11-1p Meeting with Peter &amp;amp; Graham 1-2p Meeting with Mikaela, Betta for GTC 2-4 PDG on Brian&amp;rsquo;s Autoparts paper 4-5:30  Colored git diff&amp;rsquo;s etc (from progit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/29/sunday-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2011 23:24:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/29/sunday-2/</guid>
      <description>Completed phylogenetic power manuscript updates based on Peter&amp;rsquo;s comments. Graham will read Monday. Took a whack at updating the treebase package with a method for grabbing nexus character matrices. Seegithub issues log, querying Emmanuel on this one. Local directory management / cleanup  Prepare annual progress report for committee  Phylogenetics Power manuscript. Nearly there. (SICB presentation) Warning signals manuscript resubmission. (Presenting at ESA) Generalized comparative method/release of constraint &amp;ndash; method done, time to write.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday Meetings: Duncan; Alan</title>
      <link>/2011/05/26/thursday-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 23:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/26/thursday-6/</guid>
      <description>Duncan Meeting  ROAuth/RCurl question. Mendeley is OAuth 1, github is OAuth 2 (simpler). Both are implemented in pure R in another package, may be good. OAuth 1 constructs complicated http urls with secret, and token, and random key, need to escape chars, etc. OAuth 2 is https, just uses token. Authentication options: Jeff&amp;rsquo;s ROAuth/Duncan&amp;rsquo;s mod, other OAuth package. RMendeley&amp;ndash; windows binary, competition? socialR &amp;ndash; discussed strategy to get a figure with matching code and data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/22/sunday/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2011 21:33:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/22/sunday/</guid>
      <description>Reading  International Symposium on Biomathematics and Ecology: Education and Research &amp;ndash; This looks excellent, wonder if I can make it. Besides, it&amp;rsquo;s in Portland and the acronym is promising. Pacific Ecoinformatics and Computational Ecology Lab - Based in Berkeley, looks rather intriguing, hard to tell how active this is as a group. Ecoinformatics? So it does exist? Paraphrasing Jeremy Fox, has it done anything? A rather nice review in ARES: (Jones et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TreeBASE in R: a first tutorial</title>
      <link>/2011/05/16/treebase-in-r-a-first-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 19:46:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/16/treebase-in-r-a-first-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>My TreeBASE R package is essentially functional now. Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick tutorial on the kinds of things it can do. Grab the treebase package here, install and load the library into R.
TreeBASE provides two APIs to query the database, one which searches by the metadata associated with different publications (called OAI-PMH), and another which queries the phylogenies directly (called Phylo-ws). They have somewhat redundant functions, but for our purposes the second one returns the actual data, while the first returns metadata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: Treebase</title>
      <link>/2011/05/11/wednesday-treebase/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 15:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/11/wednesday-treebase/</guid>
      <description>TREEBASE PACKAGE:
 Modified treebase package to return the treebase id in the phylo class as phy$id, so that I can use the id to query the appropriate meta data.
 Modified the package with the option to return only max number of trees,
try(xpathApply(search_returns, paste(&amp;quot;//rdf:li[position()&amp;lt; &amp;quot;, max_trees, &amp;quot;]&amp;quot;, sep=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;), function(x){  &amp;hellip;
 Modified to check for branch lengths and remove trees without branch lengths from the returned set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interfaces for databases: TreeBASE, Dryad, DataONE</title>
      <link>/2011/05/10/interfaces-for-databases-treebase-dryad-dataone/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 09:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/10/interfaces-for-databases-treebase-dryad-dataone/</guid>
      <description>Next Steps Treebase  (See Sunday&amp;rsquo;s post) - Phylo-ws implemented, but a few extra functions would strengthen the interface a bit: limit the number of trees returned, querying trees for branch lengths,
 RaXML pipeline for returning rough branch lengths conditioned on the given topology, user documentation, more test examples.
 Implement OAI-PMH test cases for treebase: For instance, query all records after a given date (or all possible other queries), i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday: a few Treebase R package updates</title>
      <link>/2011/05/08/sunday-a-few-treebase-r-package-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 23:16:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/08/sunday-a-few-treebase-r-package-updates/</guid>
      <description>Working on a few updates to the TreeBASE package. This flushes out the basic functionality provided by the phylo-ws API now. Needs a bit more testing of the possible queries and some bells and whistles options. Meanwhile, going to start looking at the metadata side with the OAI-PMH API. With this I should be able to grab metadata associated with a tree or the tree associated with the metadata. Should also be able to extend the queries over to other databases such as Dryad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>treeBASE R interface: proposal for #iEvoBio</title>
      <link>/2011/05/03/treebase-an-r-interface-proposal-for-ievobio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 21:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/03/treebase-an-r-interface-proposal-for-ievobio/</guid>
      <description>Lightning Talk Proposal  I will present the R package treeBASE, which provides an R implementation of the treeBASE phylows API. This package makes it possible to search and import data from this database of published phylogenetic trees easily from within an R script. Recent data archiving requirements at major evolutionary journals such as The American Naturalist (Whitlock et. al. 2010) and Evolution (Fairbairn, 2011) to deposit data used in the study on the Dryad digital repository (and deposit accompanying trees in TreeBASE), along with new requirements for data management from funderssuch as NSF are rapidly changing the landscape of data availability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing phylognenies in TreeBASE from R</title>
      <link>/2011/04/26/accessing-phylognenies-in-treebase-from-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2011 14:10:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/26/accessing-phylognenies-in-treebase-from-r/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve recently ((25 April, 8 April)) begun a project to see if I can search for and load phylogenies from TreeBASE directly into R. Thanks to the rather brilliant API in place (documented on the treeBASE wiki) for TreeBASE, some advice from Rutger Vos (TreeBASE developer), and some xpaths R code from Gabe Becker (stats grad student, UC Davis), I have a (mostly) working demonstration. As I get a chance, I&amp;rsquo;ll be adding the rest of the queries available in the API, improve the error handling and give some more thought to a user interface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/04/20/wednesday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2011 22:24:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/20/wednesday-3/</guid>
      <description>Reading  GrrlScientist disagrees with M. Nielsen (and I add my 2c: Open Science might not give you the credit you need to get a job in today&amp;rsquo;s science culture, but hey, in all probability, neither will the traditional strategy, so have fun). Nature says: Too many PhDs Some useful tools for data visualization: particularly want to try:Fusion Tables, Gephi, DataViz Mendeley groups don&amp;rsquo;t display (or share) stars. Can only sort A-Z or by most recent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TreeBase: exploratory exercises in database-driven phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/2011/04/08/treebase-exploratory-exercises-in-database-driven-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 15:18:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/08/treebase-exploratory-exercises-in-database-driven-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>Taking a look at the TreeBase database for potential project with Gabe &amp;amp; Duncan&amp;rsquo;s Large Data seminar. It would be interesting to get a working knowledge of the database and the API, making large-scale meta-analyses easy. Many studies seem to select taxa based on what they have in their own lab rather than re-use existing phylogenies, not because it is better suited to answering the questions but because it is more familiar.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>