<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hpc on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/hpc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hpc on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 16:49:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/hpc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel hpc on clusters in R, MPI</title>
      <link>/2011/11/10/parallel-hpc-on-clusters-in-r-mpi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 16:49:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/10/parallel-hpc-on-clusters-in-r-mpi/</guid>
      <description>Some notes for reference on parallel computing strategies on R with dedicated high performance clusters.
parallelization in R For cluster computing in R, I&amp;rsquo;ve found the &amp;ldquo;snow&amp;rdquo; package with MPI to be the most flexible and robust solution. snowfall is a useful package to use multiple cores on a single processor, but requesting all 16 threads on a node is a much more difficult demand for the queue to fill than 16 threads on all nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: scaling wrightscape examples</title>
      <link>/2011/08/29/monday-scaling-wrightscape-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2011 18:27:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/29/monday-scaling-wrightscape-examples/</guid>
      <description>syntaxHighligher isn&amp;rsquo;t working. no idea why, posted to forums.
 Still no luck compiling gsl on carver. Can&amp;rsquo;t install gsl R package or compile wrightscape C code. posted C issue to NERSC, R issue to statscicomp.
   Commits to taxize pushed to Scott.
wrightscape parrotfish example Convergence test: with simple (common) initial values (alpha=.1, sigma=1), the different methods behave mostly appropriately: outer nested models out-perform inner ones, and likelihoods roughly agree between ouch package methods and wrightscape equivalents:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday: working on computational scaling, ion, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/08/27/saturday-working-on-computational-scaling-ion-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2011 23:44:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/27/saturday-working-on-computational-scaling-ion-etc/</guid>
      <description>Can I get a generic montecarlotest function working for both warningsignals and pmc?
Needs to be able to handle S4 classes as well as S3 classes, or need to define the methods update, simulate, loglik and getParameters for any object that would use the method. i.e. these need to be defined in warningsignals for its functions and in wrightscape/pmc for its creatures. then the generic can be used. Implementing now&amp;hellip; Completed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: migrating codes into MPI</title>
      <link>/2011/08/17/wednesday-migrating-codes-into-mpi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 22:53:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/17/wednesday-migrating-codes-into-mpi/</guid>
      <description>Parellelization/Scaling of code MPI on farm cluster
Got my MPI codes running.
Much better way to get jobs into the queue, asking for 16 threads that don&amp;rsquo;t have to be on the same node is much faster. Can also ask for 161 threads, but will wait longer in the queue.
The trick to getting this to run was mostly getting the library set correctly. Setting the library path at the top of the script did the trick:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Segue: Easy cloud hpc in R, now with custom packages</title>
      <link>/2011/07/07/segue-easy-cloud-hpc-in-r-now-with-custom-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 16:45:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/07/segue-easy-cloud-hpc-in-r-now-with-custom-packages/</guid>
      <description>After a few helpful emails from package creator JD Long, I have the segue package running with custom R packages. The package is available on Google code. With two lines of code I can start submitting jobs to very large clusters of computers on the Amazon cloud. For a basic introduction to the package see Jeff Breen&amp;rsquo;s post.
Quick notes on updating using mercurial: Since I&amp;rsquo;ve already pulled the code using</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: Simulated model fit analysis on wrightscape, parrotfish tree</title>
      <link>/2011/06/08/wednesday-simulated-model-fit-analysis-on-wrightscape-parrotfish-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2011 13:03:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/08/wednesday-simulated-model-fit-analysis-on-wrightscape-parrotfish-tree/</guid>
      <description>Reviewed last night&amp;rsquo;s simulations, see yesterday&amp;rsquo;s post.  Simulated data testing: Fitting the general model well on the parrotfish tree even with clear simulated data seems hard. Simulating with alpha(intramandibulars) = .01, and others = 20, and fitting general model and the alpha-only independent model (release of constraint model). The release model MLE recovers reasonable values: alpha(intra) = 1.7, alpha(others) = 21.8, while the general model fit is clearly struggling even with SANN.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Conference Agenda Alumni-organized Plus-One Day Agenda Great chance to talk with US Secretary of the Department of Energy Stephen Chu Interesting leadership training session lead by improv acting professional Raquel Holmes of ImprovScience
  Video recording of my talk  Slides:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data to Knowledge Day 1</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/data-to-knowledge-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/data-to-knowledge-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Scaling Time Series Data Mining to trillions of series Eamonn Keogh
 Similarity search is the fundamental problem for any task This problem is now solved. As effective as possible, as efficient as possible.  What is similarity search? All about required invariances: Looking at ancient manuscripts of fish &amp;ndash; identify multiple drawings of the same species. Invariant to color, scale, and orientation.
(Note that rotation becomes phase, easy to handle).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data to Knowledge Day II and other notes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/data-to-knowledge-day-ii-and-other-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/data-to-knowledge-day-ii-and-other-notes/</guid>
      <description>Great second day at the Data to Knowledge conference (a few notes below).
Also I have been trying to move a few projects forward during the commute and break. I&amp;rsquo;ve sent Alan my revisions on the prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s fallacy manuscript, getting pretty close. Following up on a query from John, ran a simulation showing the impact of having a delay in the timeseries before the slow change towards the bifurcation begins.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>