<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Primates on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/primates/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Primates on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/primates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Manuscript writing.  Phylogenetics Submitted Lightning talk to iEvoBio
PDG group will be discussing
 Rabosky DL and Lovette IJ. .&amp;rdquo;) pmid:18611849. PubMed HubMed [1]  tomorrow, along with critique and response.
 Waiting to hear back from Peter on manuscript. Should follow up with Ralph on likelihood ratio discussion with Ethan. Transcluding exploratory work on primate phylogeny data:  Embedded:

Primate Phylogeny Carl Boettiger 00:37, 30 April 2010 (EDT):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual Progress Report</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow will be meeting with my dissertation committee: Alan Hastings, Peter Wainwright, and Brian Moore. This provides a good opportunity to summarize the status of my current projects and my principle accomplishments for the year. Will try a tex&amp;rsquo;d document as I&amp;rsquo;ve done in previous years but here&amp;rsquo;s for some preliminary brainstorming.
 Summary: In the past year, I&amp;rsquo;ve published one paper, given 4 talks (CPB, NIMBioS, Berkeley, IIASA), read 144+ articles and wrote 9000+ lines of code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in Trees</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/power-in-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/power-in-trees/</guid>
      <description>Following up after yesterday&amp;rsquo;s meeting, I am working on implementing the confidence interval analysis and quantifying information in trees. This second point I will develop by comparing the Felsenstein example tree (information-rich) to the star tree (uninformative), and develop this discussion in the context of assessing the importance of phylogenetic corrections and phylogenetic intertia (my original theme again: noise or data??).
Primate Brain Morphometry Daniel Mietchen contacted me through openwetware 11 days ago with interest in applying phylogenetic comparative methods to Primate Brain Morphometry data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primate chronogram</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/primate-chronogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/primate-chronogram/</guid>
      <description>From User:Daniel Mietchen/Notebook/Evolutionary MRI/2010/04/12:
 Jinchuan Xing recommended New perspectives on anthropoid origins whose Fig. 2 goes into our direction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primates</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/primates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/primates/</guid>
      <description>Primates project now has a Github repository. Updates are embedded from here.
 Experimenting with distributing code and data effectively. Pluses and minuses of three options:
   zipped file with R code and data. Requires setting working directory, harder to update. Subsequent uploads must include all the data, rather than incremental. Directly grab repository over github. Simple to update and access, stores only incremental changes. Requires knowledge of git R package: Nicely integrates data, code, and documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Working on bootstrapping theta parameters bootstrapping multiple parameters doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem effective in the context of the boot package, despite claiming it can use a vector of stats. Certainly part of challenge is that different models have different numbers of parameters, so this isn&amp;rsquo;t a fixed size vector. Approaching manually for the moment, inhibits use of bootstrap confidence intervals function from the boot package. Some irregular behavior in bootstrapping parameters &amp;ndash; have to load package and then reload likelihood_bootstrap library source file or else bootstraps are NAs, needs further investigation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>