<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teaching on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/categories/teaching/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Teaching on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 15:30:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Some Collaborative Tools for Science</title>
      <link>/2012/02/06/some-collaborative-tools-for-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 15:30:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/06/some-collaborative-tools-for-science/</guid>
      <description>Ania Truszczynski invited me to give a little talk on the use of various collaborative tools for scientists. I enjoyed presenting this as a chalk-talk, but alas no slides to link so here&amp;rsquo;s a list of reference. Rather than the impossible attempt to be comprehensive, this is restricted to resources I use regularly and have found to be the best of their class. All are freely available.
Tools   Science Blogs (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: some code-tricks, Algorithms group planning</title>
      <link>/2011/05/23/monday-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2011 23:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/23/monday-5/</guid>
      <description>Teary Some discussion on combining Greek letters with variables in R. Previously have solved this with substitute() command,
x = 4.5 plot(1:10, main = substitute(paste(&amp;quot;Kendall &amp;quot;, tau == val), list(val = x[1])))  but Peter has a more elegant solution that can be vectorized:
sapply(interaction(&amp;quot;sigma&amp;quot;,1:5, sep=&amp;quot; == &amp;quot;),function(x)parse(text=x)) #for instance plot(0) legend(&amp;quot;topright&amp;quot;,legend=sapply(interaction(&amp;quot;sigma&amp;quot;,1:5, sep=&amp;quot; == &amp;quot;),function(x)parse(text=x)),lty=2)  Better yet, bquote has a mechanism to evaluate an argument vs express the argument as a symbol, see gist id=1108159.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Birth-death Tutorial for PBG Core</title>
      <link>/2011/05/18/birth-death-tutorial-for-pbg-core/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2011 23:55:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/18/birth-death-tutorial-for-pbg-core/</guid>
      <description>Ran a introductory tutorial on birth-death models for phylogenetic trees in R today for Peter Wainwright&amp;rsquo;s section of the Pop Bio Core sequence. Notes below, in a manner that may suggest I was better organized than reality might attest. Luckily the firsties are brilliant&amp;hellip;
Getting Started Code is shown section by section with results in the following examples. If you prefer, you can download my full code file here, but you will have to comment out my flickr plotting utilities before it will run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega evolution Workshop: Continuous Characters R session planning</title>
      <link>/2011/02/19/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-continuous-characters-r-session-planning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 03:45:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/19/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-continuous-characters-r-session-planning/</guid>
      <description>Preparing for the Bodega Phylogenetics workshop. I&amp;rsquo;ll be covering the R tutorial followingJusten Whittall&amp;rsquo;s introduction to continuous characters:
 In my intro lecture i will discuss Felsenstein 1985 (including a little phylo signal), then follow with some alternatives (including the OU model). I can also discuss the tree transformations ala Pagel&amp;rsquo;s kappa, delta, etc. and mention multivariate approaches to detecting correlated characters in a phylogenetic context.
 I&amp;rsquo;m toying with the idea of a brief (~1hr) phylogenetic signal / model inference exercise:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To podcast or not to podcast university lectures</title>
      <link>/2011/02/01/to-podcast-or-not-to-podcast-university-lectures/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 13:27:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/01/to-podcast-or-not-to-podcast-university-lectures/</guid>
      <description>Today in graduate teaching community we&amp;rsquo;re discussing the value of podcasts which rapidly becoming the standard expectation of in university lectures. There weren&amp;rsquo;t podcasts when I was a student, at least never in the classes I&amp;rsquo;d taken -though I&amp;rsquo;ve often wished I had access to complete recordings of my university lectures. Most wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be valuable, but some I would still wish to go back to long after the fact, not so much to recall content but to remember the styles and stories my notes fail to capture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro Ecology Lecture at University of the Pacific</title>
      <link>/2011/01/25/intro-ecology-lecture-at-university-of-the-pacific/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2011 10:12:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/25/intro-ecology-lecture-at-university-of-the-pacific/</guid>
      <description>I was invited to give a guest lecture on introductory ecology for an introductory environmental science course at University of the Pacific in Stockton today. This provided both a nice outreach opportunity and a chance to speak to a full introductory class for 1:45hr, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t done before.
I ran the class something as an experiment for myself as much as an instruction. Having spent considerable time thinking more-or-less abstractly about effective teaching strategies with carefully planned lectures, activities, objectives, and assessments, I found myself suddenly at the other end of the spectrum: faced with giving a long lecture covering pretty much my entire field with little time to prepare and only the fuzziest objectives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tweets from an Ecology Field class </title>
      <link>/2010/11/25/tweets-from-an-ecology-field-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2010 02:06:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/25/tweets-from-an-ecology-field-class/</guid>
      <description>I just spoke with Professor Mau Stanton, a leading researcher in our field and an award-winning teacher, about the potential for using twitter in her field ecology course. Though never having used any social media before, Mau has both clear and clever idea of how she wants to apply it in this 15-student field class.
The challenge: Students don&amp;rsquo;t seem to read email as much any more, and are often not at a computer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/10/18/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/18/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Graduate Teaching Community &amp;ndash; reflections on teaching Haven&amp;rsquo;t made a lot of entries in this notebook as I&amp;rsquo;m not teaching regularly at the moment, though am still attending meetings of the Graduate Teaching Community, a record of which can be found on our GTC blog. But today in GTC we are thinking about reflections on teaching, and starting with a little bit of journaling, so this seemed like a good place to do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/04/26/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/26/teaching/</guid>
      <description>GTC: Assessment  Today I&amp;rsquo;m facilitating the GTC session discussing Assessment. Here&amp;rsquo;s our VUE map of the activity.  
What better way to begin a discussion about assessment than with an assessment? We began with a somewhat tongue-in-cheek quiz about the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to conduct an assessment, modelling some common faults in poor assessments while also serving as a brainstorm to get some ideas out there. We presented some background theory on assessment, drawing from the excellent text: Handelsman, J.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/04/13/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/13/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Misc / Notes  Starting to prepare for GTC sections  Technology and Education  Open courses backed by learning research: Carnegie Mellon Wallwisher online notice board example Open education featured in NY Times  Assessment  XP instead of grades? Lee Sheldon system another Sheldon method post</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/04/12/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/12/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Notes potentially for my EDG talk.
&amp;ldquo;Keeping Up&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a talk to EDG? Science is growing. Fast. Number of papers published. Genomes on Genbank. Software on CRAN. Everyone&amp;rsquo;s felt the pressure. So what do we do? Keeping with tradition, I&amp;rsquo;ll present my own work in developing comparative phylogenetic methods to identify niche differentiation in Labrid fish. I will try and use this context to pose the question &amp;ndash; what do we do about this information explosion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/03/01/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/01/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Evolution of Mimicry &amp;amp; Levels of Selection  Today my turn to help facilitate in Begun&amp;rsquo;s Monte Carlo on designing a course on evolution for non-majors. Worked with Elizabeth on an interactive case study teaching levels of selection through the example of mimicry in butterflies. Following a brief introduction, we gave a pilot run of a hands-on activity to explore population dynamics in a predator-control-model-mimic (jay-cabbage-monarch-viceroy) system. Here&amp;rsquo;s the description.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/02/22/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/22/teaching/</guid>
      <description>GTC Session: Student Centered Learning: Successes, Failures and Strategies  Gabrielle and I facilitated a GTC section on Student-Centered learning. Details in the GTC blog post. Small group of about a dozen of us, still worked to break into four groups for the discussion section. Overall went very well, don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of comments to add about the experience or things I&amp;rsquo;d do differently. Did get some positive feedback and comments that we could have used much more time to explore these ideas!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/02/19/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/19/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Faculty Mentoring Faculty Presentation &amp;ldquo;Short Cuts to Excellent Teaching: A Primer&amp;rdquo;  by James Shaffrath, from Exercise Biology, The Department of Neurobiology, Physiology and Behavior  Just saw this presentation in the Faculty Mentoring Faculty program. Good program, though pretty basic, not really touching on peer learning but focusing on lecture content and style. Things like rolling lexicon (using both jargon and simple phrases), being present, being engaging. The broad introduction was definitely the best part, and an inspiring view about the role of education.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/02/11/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/11/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Regime Shifts Seminar take two  Today I was again up for the regime shifts class to cover the details Alan&amp;rsquo;s Ecology Letters paper. Board lecture style on content I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable with, so enjoyable for me but hardly much of an experiment in effective teaching. Still, something that can be done well or poorly, so I think today went well. Began with individuals at the board to review the four principle figures from the previous class &amp;ndash; birth rates and death rates, difference in rates, the bifurcation diagram and the potential landscape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/02/04/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/04/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Early Warning Signals to Regime Shifts Seminar  I was just responsible for covering a relatively technical paper on the idea of detecting early warning signals to regime shifts. This is a class of about 10 people. First half we took turns on the board, relying entirely on graphical analysis, and going from a birth death model through stability analysis to illustrate bi-stability to the bifurcation diagram and the energy landscape representation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/01/25/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/01/25/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Clash of Old and New Today was my day to facilitate for a graduate student discussion seminar. The seminar is well attended by quite a handful of faculty and post-docs, some thirty people. The discussion is almost always dominated by a few faculty, which is a great source of information but offers little opportunity for students to ask questions or wrestle with ideas themselves. To get at this, I tried breaking the class into small groups for the first half and passing out different sets of discussion questions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>