<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Delayed Release on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/delayed-release.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Delayed Release on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 11:27:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/delayed-release/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals - noise response</title>
      <link>/2011/11/03/warning-signals---noise-response.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 11:27:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/03/warning-signals---noise-response.html</guid>
      <description>Dakos (Dakos et. al. 2012) considers $ \tfrac{dx}{dt} = f(x,p) $ and perturbs the parameter randomly to introduce variation. Evaluating around an equilibrium where $ f(x^, p^) = 0 $, they expand to first order (citing (Ripa &amp;amp; Heino, 1999)):
$$ \frac{dx}{dt} = \partial_x f(x^,p^)(x-x^) + \partial_p f(x^,p^) (p - p^) $$
and taking $ \xi = x- x^* $, with some slight of hand argue this can be rewritten as an Ito process,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rewrites</title>
      <link>/2011/10/17/rewrites.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 17:37:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/17/rewrites.html</guid>
      <description>Add more data set examples Remove skew, Remove the broken CaCO3 analysis Show distributions for increased sampling effort. Does time interval make a difference for convergence of deuterium2 run? Nope. Fails in parallel, running in series.  Code:  get away from explicit parallelization and deeply nested functions. really master optimizers, and avoid errors &amp;amp; failed convergence. store finished data for plotting as data objects. CaCO3 example -&amp;gt; MLE estimate of unstable model doesn&amp;rsquo;t converge, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be used to simulate then!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA personal notes: people, goals</title>
      <link>/2011/08/13/esa-personal-notes-people-goals.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2011 19:22:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/13/esa-personal-notes-people-goals.html</guid>
      <description>Meetings  John Drake Suzanne O&amp;rsquo;Regan (Post-doc with John, strong dynamical systems) Justin Kinze &amp;ndash; great post-doc at Berkeley with John Harte, should visit. Paul Armsworth &amp;ndash; with Alan, have asked me to join NIMBioS working group on Pretty Darn Good Control (Tuesday evening). Hal Caswell &amp;ndash; interested in some of the data management / provenance for theoretical work. (Mon) Jeremy Fox &amp;ndash; Interesting lunch discussion, clonal interference as ecological insight?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fisheries stock assessments for early warning</title>
      <link>/2011/08/02/fisheries-stock-assessments-for-early-warning.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 16:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/02/fisheries-stock-assessments-for-early-warning.html</guid>
      <description>What you want to look for are stock assessments. For example, for the species closest to home, under the Pacific Fisheries Management Council:
http://www.pcouncil.org/groundfish/stock-assessments/archived-stock-assessments/
Three rockfish species that might be good to look into for your purposes are widow, yelloweye, and bocaccio, but these will have shorter-term data than any of the cod data. Also, NOAA NMFS Technical Reports on individual stocks often have long appendices with lots of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/02/monday-8.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 16:41:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/02/monday-8.html</guid>
      <description>Peter advice  Figure out your focus. Have all the stuff from your PhD published (at least submitted), make sure your post-doc moves forward. (#1 mistake). Publish with data folks to show you have much to offer the non-theorist community Speak to potential advisers, get them excited about the work. Berkeley over Michigan over NESCent/NIMBioS. Visit Berkeley. Ackerley on sabbatical?  Review for Theoretical Ecology Working on another review. Not a bad paper, but presenting many classical results as novel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Manuscript</title>
      <link>/2011/07/27/weds-manuscript.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2011 22:38:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/27/weds-manuscript.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve removed the model choice/model adequacy section of the appendix. This is the section that Reviewer 2 said needed further development, which would be beyond the scope of this paper:
 Here the authors claim that by using particular structural models based on assumptions about underlying dynamics their method makes it easy to identify cases that do not conform to the assumptions. It would be interesting to evaluate this claim but it would require a substantial amount of analysis that may be beyond the scope of a short paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: ESA, appendix, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/07/25/monday-esa.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 23:22:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/25/monday-esa.html</guid>
      <description>Reading Gene expression as a continuous phenotypic trait &amp;ndash; establishing signal for selection over drift. (Bedford &amp;amp; Hartl, 2009) OU vs BM (or just estimation of selection in the OU model relative to tree length) would have been an obvious way to do this, but the paper tries to make the argument that scaling the data and then comparing
$$\frac{\sigma^2}{2\alpha} $$
is some indication.
Model choice section on warning signals Trying to figure out whether or not to remove this section (previously Appendix H: Model Choice and Model Adequacy).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday: Appendix edits</title>
      <link>/2011/07/24/sunday-appendix-edits.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 16:47:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/24/sunday-appendix-edits.html</guid>
      <description>Appendix A. Method Summary &amp;ndash; Basically the &amp;ldquo;methods&amp;rdquo; section as we had it in the Nature version, a bit updated.
 These sections are as before, with minor updates from the reviewers, etc. They&amp;rsquo;re also probably the most important part:
 Appendix B. The data sets Appendix C. Model Derivations Appendix D. Likelihood calculations Appendix E. The likelihood statistic  Appendix F. The distributions for the ROC curves &amp;ndash; these are the former figure 1b/c distributions used to make the ROC curve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday - back to Warning Signals MS</title>
      <link>/2011/07/17/saturday---back-to-warning-signals-ms.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 10:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/17/saturday---back-to-warning-signals-ms.html</guid>
      <description>New outline   &amp;rdquo;An increasing recognition&amp;rdquo;  &amp;ldquo;proof-of-principle&amp;rdquo; - reliability is unknown  &amp;ldquo;Cries wolf&amp;rdquo;  ROC, Fig 1  tau  method  data, Fig 2  analysis, Fig 3  enough data Fig 4  disclaimer  conclusion  Former Outline  Early Warning matter, no-one does statistics We need quantify uncertainty stats ROC curve shows this trade-off ROC also compares different methods &amp;amp; data sizes (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early warning signals presentation notes</title>
      <link>/2011/07/07/early-warning-signals-presentation-notes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 16:40:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/07/early-warning-signals-presentation-notes.html</guid>
      <description> motivate story of fisheries management.
 Step advance a time series of fluctuations. Shows a gradual decline and eventually sudden crash. Predict when we crash? Introduce indicators. Advance a different time series, this time displaying summary statistics as we go. Have audience make prediction whether next step will be collapse. Present summary statistics with uncertainty included. (color code confidence?)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: Data wrangling into graphs</title>
      <link>/2011/07/06/wednesday-data-wrangling-into-graphs.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 14:34:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/06/wednesday-data-wrangling-into-graphs.html</guid>
      <description>Really high sampling runs (20000 pts) still don&amp;rsquo;t seem to show any improvement in deut3 dataset summary statistics, perhaps it is the window size. testing by launching deut_replot.R, n5 on zero, 500, 1000, 2000 on a fixed windowsize of 60, see how it compares to the half window. probably because is such a weak signal.
running drake tau sampling with corrected (1&amp;frasl;2 length) windowsizes. &amp;ndash; destroys any improvement in indicators:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: Warning Signals Data Wrangling</title>
      <link>/2011/07/05/tuesday-warning-signals-data-wrangling.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 17:45:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/05/tuesday-warning-signals-data-wrangling.html</guid>
      <description>Revise abstract. 10a-11a. done.  Misc data handling 11-1pm
 wrote a file to fix flickr data file names that are occasionally mangled by parallel loop printing. wrote a file to plot $m T$ values on each dataset to get a sense of which have the most dramatic warning signals. running on one.   locale troubles on install lead to errors in data read  Error in make.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals writing, organization, appendices</title>
      <link>/2011/07/04/warning-signals-writing-organization-appendices.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 19:03:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/04/warning-signals-writing-organization-appendices.html</guid>
      <description>main text Summary Sentence. Abstract
Paragraphs  Early Warning matter, no-one does statistics We need quantify uncertainty stats ROC curve shows this trade-off ROC also compares different methods &amp;amp; data sizes (i.e. Fig 4) Quantifying &amp;ldquo;increasing variance&amp;rdquo; etc &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;ll use tau We&amp;rsquo;ll also do a likelihood-based method Introduce the datasets ROC curves on the data, Fig 3 Quantifying data necessary, Fig 4 Disclaimers: Not completely general Conclusion  Supporting Online Material Original Appendix had:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday, warning signals writing, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/07/01/friday-warning-signals-writing-etc.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2011 17:57:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/01/friday-warning-signals-writing-etc.html</guid>
      <description>9-10a email, etc 10 am check simulations: Daphnia examples (Drake data) runs done. A few examples, see neighboring plots in image database for the corresponding distributions and further examples. Runtime of this code (click images for script) about 10 hours on 16 cores on zero.
   launched ibm_analysis.R on zero, n10.
 Writing writing&amp;hellip; first full text draft done.
  Trying to get started on the centos cluster, some trouble submitting job to queue, see email discussion with Bill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: Warning Signals writing, figures, segue</title>
      <link>/2011/06/30/thursday-7.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/30/thursday-7.html</guid>
      <description>Alan meeting Figure 1: Introducing the ROC Curve Figure 2: Standard approach Figure 3: ROC curves corresponding to standard approach Do we show the distributions? &amp;ndash; Create for each, but log in appendix
ROC curves corresponding to increased sampling &amp;ndash; our method, other stats? organize how?
Computational Runs Running at constant sample points rather than sample effort.
 On eleven: n5ibm_stable.R 6pm On zero, n10 drake_analysis.R 6pm On zero, n19 deut_analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals: summary statistic performance at varying sampling effort</title>
      <link>/2011/06/29/warning-signals-summary-statistic-performance-at-varying-sampling-effort.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 22:08:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/29/warning-signals-summary-statistic-performance-at-varying-sampling-effort.html</guid>
      <description>oikos post launch case of increased sampling on sim data for autocorrelation (is our approach more robust to model differences?)  IBM data Example Using data from the individual-based model simulation of a system approaching a saddle-node.
Variance While the initial example with variance shows almost no signal, increasing the sampling effort substantially improves the performance. This can be seen in the ROC curves and as a tightening and spreading out of the null and test distributions as the sampling effort is increased.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals Literature: when stats are and aren&#39;t attempted</title>
      <link>/2011/06/01/warning-signals-literature-when-stats-are-and-arent-attempted.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 15:10:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/01/warning-signals-literature-when-stats-are-and-arent-attempted.html</guid>
      <description>In preparing manuscript on warning signals, reviewing the literature on when statistical validation of the warning signal is included, and if so, what kind are done. There&amp;rsquo;s certainly no consensus in the approach, with the majority of papers not even attempting a method (and those that do not finding significance). Scheffer&amp;rsquo;s key review (Scheffer et. al. 2009) calls for the need to measure statistical significance of warning signals,
 Therefore, it would be useful to build a set of reliable statistical procedures to test whether an increase in autocorrelation, for example, is significant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Warning Signals in Coral Dynamics -- Economic analysis of risk</title>
      <link>/2011/04/19/early-warning-signals-in-coral-dynamics----economic-analysis-of-risk.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2011 11:53:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/19/early-warning-signals-in-coral-dynamics----economic-analysis-of-risk.html</guid>
      <description>Alan and I have been considering analyzing a particular system for early warning signals where we could highlight risk management from an economics stand-point, probably with the help of Jim Sanchirico. Our current work focuses on quantifying the relative risk of false alarms and missed detections. While statisticians typically accept a 5% &amp;ldquo;false alarm&amp;rdquo; rate, we argue this given limited data this is always a trade-off against the missed detection rate and hence the location of this threshold should properly a decision of management, not of convention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Final round edits</title>
      <link>/2011/04/13/weds-final-round-edits.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 16:21:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/13/weds-final-round-edits.html</guid>
      <description> Low-power (40 data-point) IBM simulation example   Consider examples of false negative (Deteriorating example), and negative correlations in constant and deteriorating environments (? - nope) Implement LTC updated models! Working over Alex revisions  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: Warning Signals - Updated graphs</title>
      <link>/2011/04/11/monday-warning-signals-updated-graphs.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 22:47:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/11/monday-warning-signals-updated-graphs.html</guid>
      <description>Trying a different set-up for the graphs. Added two additional datasets, trying layout of making all three figures into a panels in a single figure.
Concerns:
 Better than only one empirical example, but not sure that the three Glaciation data sets add that much since they are all quite similar. Five panels wide might be too much. Don&amp;rsquo;t have an example where a transition is about to occur but the data doesn&amp;rsquo;t have adequate power even for our Likelihood method, third panel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday finishing up appendices(?)</title>
      <link>/2011/04/01/thursday-finishing-up-appendices.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 15:50:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/01/thursday-finishing-up-appendices.html</guid>
      <description>Fresh off the cpus: single replicate examples on the Drake data
What&amp;rsquo;s still running:  likelihood for IBM data with 2000 replicates, nice 19 on zero (ibm_likelihood.R) likelihood for Glaciation I-III with 2000 replicates, nice 18 on zero (deut_likelihood.R) likelihood for Glaciation I-III with 2000 replicates, (nice 19 on one)? (deut_likelihood.R) likelihood on sim data, Glaciation III and CaCO3: 80 replicates on one, nice 1 on one (figure3.R) and with 2000 replicates, nice 19 on one (figure3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: appendices; parameter distributions</title>
      <link>/2011/03/30/wednesday-appendices-parameter-distributions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2011 17:59:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/30/wednesday-appendices-parameter-distributions.html</guid>
      <description>Fixed bug causing montecarlotest() calls not to complete: in likelihood_bifurcation_models, LTC error checking uses any() to see if any Vx are negative, returns NA if none are negative but has NAs. rm.na=TRUE fixed this. GetParNames works, probably worth an appendix section to discuss parameter bootstraps as well, particularly in the cases of low power. Updated codes to turn this flag back on and am re-running. Figure3 plot has been using the 160 bootstrap replicates, updated to the 2000 replicates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday-- Appendices</title>
      <link>/2011/03/26/saturday---appendices.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 23:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/26/saturday---appendices.html</guid>
      <description>Appendices Working on Appendices
Ergodicity Null of Kendall&amp;rsquo;s tau/rank correlations &amp;ndash; independence of X and Y, not satisfied even over replicates. Adjusted codes to use Pearson&amp;rsquo;s (default option, need to pass option up to higher-level functions). Repeated Figure 2 plots with Pearson&amp;rsquo;s, results not much different, funny multimodal though:
Actually verifying independence is rather more challenging, though convenient in this case that a test such as Pearson&amp;rsquo;s is not designed to do this, see http://en.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: Figures, figures, figures</title>
      <link>/2011/03/23/tuesday-figures-figures-figures.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 10:37:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/23/tuesday-figures-figures-figures.html</guid>
      <description>Today working mostly on selecting examples of data sets to include in the figure patterns. Working with the idea of three figures &amp;ndash; data, bootstraps of Tau, bootstraps of likelihood &amp;ndash; in panels for several examples: some real data sets and some simulated data sets with and without warning. In addition to this, I still have some more work to do with references, and refining the writing of a few of the appendices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing: Warning Signals Mansucript</title>
      <link>/2011/03/20/writing-warning-signals-mansucript.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2011 14:39:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/20/writing-warning-signals-mansucript.html</guid>
      <description>Summary Paragraph
 Critical transitions exist (Holling, 1973), (May, 1977),(Scheffer et. al. 2001) Warning signals exist (Scheffer et. al. 2009), (Drake &amp;amp; Griffen, 2010) Warning signals are summary statistics, critical slowing down (Wissel, 1984). Statement of general problem: double-edged sword &amp;ndash; no quantification of the chance detection scheme will fail. We provide a way to do this We find existing methods lack sufficient power and have high false-alarm potential We provide a model-based solution using machinery of modern likelihood statistics  Background  Define CSD, standard detection scheme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sam&#39;s Practice talk</title>
      <link>/2011/03/18/sams-practice-talk.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 16:37:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/18/sams-practice-talk.html</guid>
      <description>Notes from: Sam Price&amp;rsquo;s Practice Job Talk for Hull, UK, next week, in Wainwright lab:
 Diversification of mammals predated KT event(Bininda-Emonds et. al. 2007) (also considerably later, but not right after) Ecological shift in wrasses to parrotfishes(Price et. al. 2010). No evidence of elevate rates of evolution. But, scraping parrotfishes do show difference (starting from base of Hipposcarus-Scarus common ancestor). Multiple transitions to/from reef living. 2x faster on coral reefs!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals in Ecological Systems: Revisions and Drake &amp; Griffen Data</title>
      <link>/2011/03/17/warning-signals-in-ecological-systems-drake-griffen-data.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 09:59:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/17/warning-signals-in-ecological-systems-drake-griffen-data.html</guid>
      <description>Manuscript revisions  Heard back from Alan this morning on manuscript, need to cut wordcount in half, from 3000 to 1500 words. Should emphasize the countless and utterly arbitrary choices made in every one of these analyses. Should emphasize our approach can be applied without replicates. (also without interpolating/having evenly sampled data) Should do coefficient of variation on non-detrended data(?) should discuss?  Chemostat data This morning Alan sent me the data used by Drake &amp;amp; Griffen (Drake &amp;amp; Griffen, 2010).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Two years ago, I scribbled an entry into my notebook entitled Wrong Picture, Wrong Model: Why warning signals don&amp;rsquo;t look like rare events. Months later I made some off-hand remark to Alan (my Ph.D. mentor) about how transitions found in historical records, such as the Climate examples in Dakos et. al. (2008), could actually be selecting for stochastic transitions, and this selection process might make them look like traditional warning signals &amp;ndash; i.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>