<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Multiple Uncertainty on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/multiple-uncertainty/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Multiple Uncertainty on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/multiple-uncertainty/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/04/10/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/10/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</guid>
      <description>multiple uncertainty  Set up Paul Fackler&amp;rsquo;s MDPSOLVE and run Paul&amp;rsquo;s code. Installing user-contributed extensions in matlab seems mostly a matter adding the unzipped source directories to the path, e.g. as so:
  currentdir = cd cd /home/cboettig/.matlab/MDPSOLVE addpath(genpath(cd)) cd /home/cboettig/.matlab/plot2svg addpath(genpath(cd)) cd(currentdir)  (I still find matlab/octave&amp;rsquo;s syntax of not distinguishing character strings from variable names from function names kind of terrifying, but I guess that&amp;rsquo;s the price of working with economists.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/04/09/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/09/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</guid>
      <description>Attempt to replicate Figure 3, but with one noise at a time  Code: one_noise_at_a_time.m Uniform Noise Large noise means devation of 0.5, as in Sethi Other noise terms are 0 instead of 0.1  Figure 3  Code: carl_fig3.m Uniform Noise Large noise means devation of 0.5, as in Sethi Small noise means 0.1, as in Sethi  Now fixed. See:
 Updated code version of carl_fig3.m  One noise at a time, lognormal noise, sigma = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/04/08/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/08/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</guid>
      <description>Growth Noise Only Run:
matlab -nodesktop &amp;lt; testing.m &amp;gt; testing.log  Results from running testing.m:
 log normal noise sigma_g = 0.2 Other noise set to zero.
 Coarse grid 0:5:150 (See linked code all parameters)  measurement Noise only  Code: measurement_uncertainty.m sigma_m = 0.5 Other noise set to zero.
 Fine grid 0:1:150 (See linked code all parameters)  Implementation Noise only  Code: implementation_uncertainty.m sigma_i = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/01/31/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/31/notes/</guid>
      <description>Scratch notes on uncertainty.
Function definition: multiple_uncertainty.m
Settings:
f=@(x, h) max( (x-h) * (1 - (x-h) ./ 100) + (x-h), 0); x_grid = [0:5:100]; h_grid = x_grid; % Must be same dimensions as x_grid, or L91 errors... Tmax = 5; sigma_g = 0.1; sigma_m = 0.; sigma_i = 0.0; delta = 0.05; pdf = @(p,mu,s) lognpdf(p ./ mu, 0, s); %pdf = @(p,mu,s) unifpdf(p, mu .* (1 - s), mu .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/01/31/weekly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/31/weekly-review/</guid>
      <description>EML  bug fixes and replies to various input from community on EML package
 Thoughts on understanding and using EML in research, including Dryad. See https://github.com/ropensci/EML/issues/82#issuecomment-33558301
  multiple-uncertainty Jim and Mike meeting  Why the steps in the optimal solution of the deterministic case? Irregularities in value function in first iteration: sometimes not exact ties; actually preferring to fish at almost 0 rather than 0.
 address range constraints on h and x.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/03/26/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/26/research/</guid>
      <description>nonparametric-bayes writing writing &amp;hellip;
multiple-uncertainty Fixed matlab implementation. (Some fun with matrix transposes in translating from R. #4) See:
 multiple-uncertainty.m example  Compare to
 R algorithm example  Matlab code shows the same pattern in which growth noise results in constant escapement, but either implementation or measurement noise cause deviations from this rule (most dramatic in the case of implementation uncertainty).
Notebook Some feedback and ideas from Noam, such as landing pages #77 and inline intro #78.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/03/22/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/22/research/</guid>
      <description>multiple-uncertainty  Fixed issues with translation to matlab and applyfun. Element-wise calls can use meshgrid arguments directly, and one can force functions to use element-wise operations with bxfun. So the following are equivalent: :  [X, Y] = meshgrid(x,y) applyfun(@min, X, Y)  or
function out = element_min(x,y) bxfun(@min, x, y) element_min(X, Y)  Meanwhile my challenge with additional arguments to applyfun can be circumvented with an inline function,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/03/20/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/20/research/</guid>
      <description>pomp Exploring pomp for examples tomorrow. See pomp-example
 To access help on S4 methods  print method source code: getMethod(&amp;quot;simulate&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;pomp&amp;quot;) access help file on available methods: method?show(&amp;quot;pomp&amp;quot;)  pomp simulate method returns object of class pomp with data in object@data, unless user sets either/both of obs=TRUE and state=TRUE to return the observed and true state data (in list objects). Seems to be the only way to get the true state data out of the simulate routine (other than shortcutting the observation method rmeasure).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/03/13/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/13/notes/</guid>
      <description>Multiple-uncertainty  Created smaller version of table to simplify comparisons Switched to stationary policy comparisons only. (Running out over longer time shifts total value a bit but doesn&amp;rsquo;t amplify scale of the differences much) Larger noise amplifies the effects (compare 0.3 levels to 0.5 levels) note that averaging over replicates gives rather consistent means. The differences between successive runs of the algorithm give results agreeing to the tenths place at least.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/03/12/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/12/notes/</guid>
      <description>Monday  multiple_uncertainty abstract Meeting with Robin Snyder application writing  Tuesday Morning  applications Coordinating summer conference travel ropensci proposals EML is not an ontology, not analgous to Dublin Core, etc. Just an XML schema. see OBOE for an ecological ontology. to explore later.
  Afternoon multiple-uncertainty  Revisiting multiple-uncertainty runs. Running smaller table example. Recoded script to allow arbitrary set of noise configurations to be consistently compared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/12/21/progress-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/12/21/progress-summary/</guid>
      <description>Progress mid-October through mid-December 80% Time: nonparametric-bayes The bulk of my time has been spent becoming familiar with the literature on Gaussian Processes and their numerical implementation. I have written my own Gaussian process code from scratch to convince myself of my understanding of the methodology, and explored some of the related numerical issues addressing computational speed and stability.
I then developed an algorithm for applying the Gaussian process inference of the state dynamics to stochastic dynamic programming methods for determining an optimal harvesting policy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/11/22/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/22/notes/</guid>
      <description>multiple-uncertainty Working out the multiple uncertainty computational performance and noise forms. Fixing a few things in the way log-normal noise was calculated. Uniform noise in particular can still give rather non-smooth policy, needs a bit of digging. Uniform noise doesn&amp;rsquo;t show the non-monotonicity of the log-normal noise in measurement uncertainty though.
Uniform lognormal log  A few small tweaks to probability calculations
 Handle the case of mu = grid zero, not just exactly zero, to avoid introducing NAs Calculate dlnorm as (x_grid/mu, 0, sigma), rather than as (x_grid, mu, sigma).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/11/21/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/21/notes/</guid>
      <description>writing comment piece. writing writing writing.
  Also today (misc):  Check in with Peter re: Labrids paper Fix issue #32 rfigshare Follow up with Nina about improved FishBase API pay ESA and SSE dues Santa Cruz SOE email lists uniform growth noise version on corrected multiple-uncertainty run transparent plots in new ggplot theme? Set in dev.args=list(bg=&amp;quot;transparent&amp;quot;) Consider SOE AMS lecturer pool? Description, Application  CV, Letter of application with course list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple uncertainty corrected</title>
      <link>/2012/11/16/mult-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/16/mult-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>Fixed the multiple uncertainty calculation implementation. Code had transposed $\mathbb{I}$, also one of the $\mathbb{M}$ matrices. Should still confirm final implementation. In the below example each case has log-normal growth noise present. The non-monotonic section of the measurement uncertainty
See notes on code changes inline.
Additional notes from walking through algoritm step by step.  $x$ index in the true state space $y$ index in the observed state space $h$ index in the true action $q$ index in the policy/decision space</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/11/08/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/08/notes/</guid>
      <description>Complete IACUC training for fish room. File forms: http://ehs.ucsc.edu/programs/research-safety/animal-research/index.html Online training &amp;ndash; possibly see https://www.citiprogram.org/Default.asp? Shiny: http://www.rstudio.com/shiny/
 Comment piece
 Prep exit seminar
 Applied math club: Networks. Reading http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2011/284909
  Discussion of when network structure has made an important difference on our understanding of a problem. When have the common summary statistics of a network (degree-distribution) allowed us to compte network dynamics without fully resolving the network?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/11/01/multiple-uncertainty-corrections/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/01/multiple-uncertainty-corrections/</guid>
      <description>Consider a stock $x_t$ at time $t$ that recruits stochastically following harvest $h_t$ from the escaped population ($s_t := x_t - ht$), $x{t+1} = z_g f(s_t)$, where $z_g$ is a multiplicative stochastic shock to the growth. We imagine the decision maker sets a policy determining the harvest quota $q_t$ each year, which is implemented as the real harvest with some error $z_i$, $h_t = z_i q_t$. Before setting a quota, the decision maker assesses the stock $y_t = z_m x_t$, so $y$ is a noisy measurement of the true stock $x$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/09/14/analytic-solution-to-multiple-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/09/14/analytic-solution-to-multiple-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>No idea where I went wrong, but the final graphs are not what I expected Update: Integrated out some uncertainty in the expectation step, need to preserve full set of transtions
We consider adding additional sources of noise through observation error and implementation error to the orginal model of Reed (1979), which considers only growth error. This follows in the line of exploration taken by Clark and Kirkwood (1987), Roughgarden (1996) and Sethi (2006).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/08/21/pdg-control-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/08/21/pdg-control-updates/</guid>
      <description>Resolving S &amp;lt; D Code updates octokit
Reading  Macksamie, K., Cockburn, J., &amp;amp; Wagner, J. (2012). Robust control amidst stock and flow benefits: The case of wolf-elk-hunting dynamics in the US Mountain West. 2012 AERE Summer Conference, Asheville, NC (pp. 1-33). Retrieved from http://www.webmeets.com/files/papers/AERE/2012/3/AEREConfPaper05172012.pdf  The Linear parameter varying (LPV) approach which allows this problem to leverage a standard LMI (linear matrix inequality) solver seeems like a clever route, but unclear if this would be restricted to the additive noise models such as they consider?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policy functions and value functions under multiple uncertainty</title>
      <link>/2012/06/13/sethi-policy-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/06/13/sethi-policy-functions/</guid>
      <description>Implements a numerical version of the SDP described in (Sethi et. al. 2005).
## Clear the workspace and load package dependencies: rm(list=ls()) require(pdgControl) require(reshape2) require(ggplot2) require(data.table)  We consider a Beverton Holt state equation governing population dynamics, $f(x,h) = \frac{A x}{1 + B x}$
f &amp;lt;- BevHolt  With parameters A = 1.5 and B = 0.05.
pars &amp;lt;- c(1.5, 0.05) K &amp;lt;- (pars[1] - 1)/pars[2]  Note that the positive stationary root of the model is given by \( \frac{A-1}{B} \), or carring capacity K = 10.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>