<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Notebook Technology on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/notebook-technology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Notebook Technology on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 10:50:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/notebook-technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing out a Jekyll-based notebook</title>
      <link>/2012/05/03/testing-out-a-jekyll-based-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 May 2012 10:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/05/03/testing-out-a-jekyll-based-notebook/</guid>
      <description>I am trying out Jekyll as an alternative to Wordpress for powering this site and my open lab notebook. If you subscribe, the new RSS (atom) feed for the new notebook is at http://carlboettiger.info/atom.xml. I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear any feedback, good or bad, about the switch. A recent post gives my own reflections. The site&amp;rsquo;s source-code is available on github.
Navigating two platforms The Wordpress site now lives at http://carlboettiger.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catching up</title>
      <link>/2012/04/19/catching-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 10:39:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/19/catching-up/</guid>
      <description>Catching up on notebook entries for last week and the beginning of this week in one go here. In the process of wrapping up a variety of older projects, so this is kinda all over the place.
rfishbase  Create function table, finalize functions Add support for references. Done, see getRefs. (And isn&amp;rsquo;t it awesome that you can link to a specific linenumber (i.e. line 280) in github by adding #L280 to the end of the url?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday: projects, reading, markdown notebook-technology</title>
      <link>/2012/02/12/saturday-projects-reading-markdown-notebook-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 13:40:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/12/saturday-projects-reading-markdown-notebook-technology/</guid>
      <description>Greatly enjoyed seeing this perspective on power laws (Stumpf &amp;amp; Porter, 2012) Or as Richard McElreath put even more concisely,
 People get amazed by power laws but never by normal distributions. Seems like some max ent outcomes astonish while others don&amp;rsquo;t. When so many mechanisms aggregate to common densities, I&amp;rsquo;d hope we&amp;rsquo;d stop trying to argue that we can go backwards from pattern to process so easily.
 Projects  fishbase example query for Peter Commit edits to warningsignals paper, send to Alan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/01/30/monday-15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2012 19:38:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/30/monday-15/</guid>
      <description>pdg-control, aside exercise Lab group commented that optimum in Reed model looks unrealistic due to frequency with which it shuts down all fishing. This is an artifact of not having extraction costs increase sufficiently for small catch, and can be easily fixed by increasing that cost (c in the profit eq, profits-costs = p*x-c/x)
view sourcecode, Reed.R
NIMBioS short visitor application Have been thinking that it would be really useful to have some extra time at Nimbios to meet with folks at the time of our next working group meeting (March 12-15).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/12/12/monday-12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 19:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/12/monday-12/</guid>
      <description>Wrote method2 test functions out in knitr/sweave. Sent document to Peter. Move my ropensci git origins to the ropensci github page. Ropensci comments on \dontrun: recommended for anything non-trivial, including web calls. Richer tests should be put into testthat. Reply to Charles Jervis, biology high school teacher interested in tools to teach math/modeling in ecology. Sounds like he&amp;rsquo;s already doing some cool stuff with phylogenies with his students. prepare vignette for rfishbase based on tutorial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sparkleshare configuration</title>
      <link>/2011/11/04/sparkleshare-configuration/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2011 22:35:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/04/sparkleshare-configuration/</guid>
      <description>Configured sparkleshare across my linux server &amp;amp; laptops, and android phone. Provides a dropbox-style syncing and version history for all files using git. I can sync as much space as I have hardisk capacity, with as many users and machines as I like, at no cost. Wonderful.
Basic setup Get sparkleshare working on a server is dead simple, Can also use a github server, gitorious server, etc. Setup is clearly documented, which is really just doing a bunch of standard stuff if you have a server or github already set up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>server file management from bowser: ajaxplorer, mollify</title>
      <link>/2011/11/01/server-file-management-from-bowser-ajaxplorer-mollify/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 20:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/01/server-file-management-from-bowser-ajaxplorer-mollify/</guid>
      <description>A few notes on trying out some server-based file sharing solutions.
ajaXplorer Kind of amazingly good and easy to install, with configuration-free functionality like previews of images and playing mp3s. More secure file sharing (at least, public link not generated until asked for, can have password assigned to it). Sharing is the only step not activated by default. Create a folder called &amp;ldquo;public&amp;rdquo; in the ajaxplorer directory, and this feature will appear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>memory management, cron</title>
      <link>/2011/09/07/memory-management-cron/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 21:28:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/07/memory-management-cron/</guid>
      <description>Create the memcheck.sh script that will write a mem.log file with the data, and agnuplot script that will plot it.
[gist id=1201994]
Then set up a cron job. First, set the editor to something functional:
export EDITOR=vi  then, crontab -e to edit the cron table. Add this line to run the command every 2 minutes (see wikipedia entry for quick intro), and plot it every 15 minutes:
*/2 * * * * /home/cboettig/.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Site configuration: file sharing notes</title>
      <link>/2011/05/28/notebook-technology-file-sharing-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 23:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/28/notebook-technology-file-sharing-notes/</guid>
      <description>Easiest way to share files is ssh onto the carlboettiger.info server, change into the directory carlboettiger.info/ and create a new directory there &amp;ndash; i.e. share/. This behaves as a regular static webpage directory that will list the files provided.
Secure access can be created by going to the goodies &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;htaccess/WebDav page and selecting the option to make a directory or subdirectory secure, and then specifying the passwords, etc. Have created the subdirectory http://carlboettiger.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MathJax the smart way: Child Themes</title>
      <link>/2011/05/16/mathjax-the-smart-way-child-themes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 12:54:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/16/mathjax-the-smart-way-child-themes/</guid>
      <description>Adding mathjax by modifying the header.php file in my wordpress theme, as recommended by MathJax website, isn&amp;rsquo;t stable to upgrades of the theme, which simply replace the header.php file with a fresh version. The &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; way to do this is using child themes, which are pretty simple, even though this got me writing my first php functions.
 Create a directory in wp-content/themes with the desired name of the new theme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: meetings, notebook</title>
      <link>/2011/05/09/monday-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2011 23:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/09/monday-4/</guid>
      <description>Coop &amp;amp; Moore 270: Species Trees Discussing Bucky paper (Ane et. al. 2006)
Approach of BEST and *BEAST (last time): Prior probability on gene trees P(G|S), given species trees. Goal: Posterior of species trees,
$$ P(S|X) = \intG \Pi{\ell} \left[ P(X{\ell}|G{\ell}) P(G_{\ell}|S) \right] P(S) dG $$
$$ P(G{\ell}|S) = \Pi{b \in S} P(Hb(G{\ell})|S_b) $$
Uses a Dirchlet process model for clustering genes by topologies. All genes in a cluster agree to share a common topology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a semantic notebook</title>
      <link>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 18:39:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</guid>
      <description>What would a semantic lab notebook look like? What would be possible with such a structure, ideally? What is already possible now? There&amp;rsquo;s a lot that can be done with an electronic notebook that adds value over a paper notebook: browsing by categories and tags, embedding links, time-stamping entries, searching the full text, and having automated trackbacks or pingbacks when a post is mentioned in another post or appears elsewhere on the web.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Parrotfish data set analysis</title>
      <link>/2011/05/04/weds-parrotfish-data-set-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2011 23:16:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/04/weds-parrotfish-data-set-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Parrotfish  Need better convergence error handling.
 Need to remedy: &amp;ldquo;Function cannot be evaluated at initial parameters&amp;rdquo; errors &amp;ndash; Occur when attempting very large values of alpha, resulting in NaN output (trouble with exponentials of alpha in calculations).
 Changed summaries to group by painting, so compare models and traits. Less natural than comparing across painting for a single trait since that allows comparisons both across models and across paintings, but makes sense when comparing only a single partition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citation tools &amp; Future of Publishing</title>
      <link>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 23:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of rapid development in scientific tools based on a Wordpress platform recently, perhaps spurred in part by the recent Beyond-the-PDF and sessions in Science Online conferences. A new discussion group has emerged around these tools, as described by Martin Fenner.
I have been exploring better tools for citation management within my lab notebook. Recently I have been using the papercite plugin to add citations from my BibTeX files, which are generated from Mendeley, as I described earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to a recent bugfix in the exitwp scripts I was able to export all my Wordpress entries. The script pulls the entries from the Wordpress database and formats them in markdown, along with extracting all metadata such as timestamp, tags, categories, publication status, and Wordpress id number, which are all embedded as YAML header information.
Why migrate the old entries? When I moved to the Jekyll notebook, I left the Wordpress site standing with all its existing content and simply remapped the home pages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>This Open Lab Notebook started on a public MediaWiki-based site, OpenWetWare (OWW), which was created with the ambitious vision of having a single wiki for biological sciences (or at least, synthetic microbiology, since such the wiki grew out of a collection of such labs). Users could have their own pages that served as a personal website or lab group site, contribute pages on specific protocols, host course websites, and most interestingly, were encouraged to create open lab notebooks using specially designed templates for the purpose.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>All notebook entries are formatted with XHTML compliant (polyglot) HTML5 semantic structure. This means that any entry can be parsed with a generic XML parser to extract the entry content in &amp;lt;article&amp;gt;, the &amp;lt;header&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;footer&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;aside&amp;gt;, etc. The &amp;lt;head&amp;gt; section provides &amp;lt;title&amp;gt; and essential &amp;lt;meta&amp;gt; tags declaring the character encoding (which also sets the MIME type for HTML5).
Head In _includes/header.html we introduce some basic academic archive metadata using the Dublin Core ontology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Misc  Mostly writing application today&amp;hellip; Review for EcoLet looking over pomdp/momdp
 Notebook archives now on figshare (plain-txt versions). Can now also cite entries by doi, e.g.: Lab Notebook (2010) doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.96916, and Lab Notebook, (2011) doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.96919. Would publishing individual entries and individual figshare objects be preferable or just annoying?
 Meeting tomorrow with Annette Thomas, CEO NPG/MacMillian. review interview with David Worlock  Munch data project  Data extraction for geospatial life history project (file  R script for converting place names into latitude/longitude:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Monday  altmetrics post post for multiple uncertainty, email to Steve, Marc Marc meeting ropensci proposals Phylotastic  Notebook configuration  trying out http://greycite.knowledgeblog.org/. Add to knitcitations. Add Greycite recommended opengraph and google scholar metadata metadata.html Import metadata from _config.yml. Any custom variable defined in config can be accessed at site.varname. See updated _config.yml  Reading  Schnitzler, J., Graham, C. H., Dormann, C. F., Schiffers, K., &amp;amp; Peter Linder, H.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>C. Titus Brown has an excellent post discussing his exploration into the merits and technicalities cross-posting his blog posts to figshare. The rfigshare package written by Ted Hart and myself can do just this, once we puzzled out some of the same challenges (Notes to Titus: though the documentation doesn&amp;rsquo;t mention it, you can get a programmatic list of available categories from http://api.figshare.com/v1/categories. Figshare can also take code as a fileset or dataset, and may soon add a type for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>plots for the notebook I have started uploading images to my own server, rather than flickr. Programmatically, this is just a matter of switching the knitr upload function:
opts_knit$set(upload.fun = socialR::notebook.url)  from my custom flickr.url function (a wrapper to Rflickr) to a custom function notebook.url using a system call to cp (to my local jekyll notebook) and rsync (so the figure displays before my next jekyll push).
The new script names image by date and the first 10 characters of the sha hash, as well as the knitr chunk name.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Github issues tracker has increasingly become my research to-do list. Far beyond bugs and features of the code associated with the project, the issues sign-post different directions for investigation and the progress I&amp;rsquo;ve made in each. Tags serve to group issues related to a common sub-project (as in my pdg-control) repo or priotize tasks (as in my nonparametric-bayes repo.
Issues not only have title and tags, but support a comment thread for progress and discussion of the issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Some quick thoughts on learning Jekyll After recieving a few queries on how to get started with Jekyll I thought I&amp;rsquo;d jot down my own opinions here. Of course there is already rather good documentation for the software and plenty of blogs providing tutorials. While no doubt more than adequate, I have more opinions on how to get started actually learning what&amp;rsquo;s going on than I could easily fit into a tweet, and also a couple favorite links to references so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d jot down my reply in long form here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Figures have been one of the standing challenges of the open notebook. Displaying figures online requires that they are first uploaded to a server somewhere. Recently I have used automated uploads to external servers such as figshare to host all images generated in the course of my research, and simply point to those graphs which I wish to include in a notebook page using an image link. Unfortunately, this means that the images themselves are not being permanently archived when I deposit my notebook entries into their annual archives on figshare.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>(Working from Galveston this week while at Louise&amp;rsquo;s conference, looking after little one. some progress below.)
Monday Alan Skype meeting  Comment piece / reply ews-review Comments on TE review? IARPA Conference, funding options?  Tasks  On Marc&amp;rsquo;s suggestion, writing comparison of pattern-based and mechanism based approaches to modeling, particularly in decision theory context. draft in nonparametric-bayes Review edits and writing on ews-review  Tuesday Kathy Skype  Decision theory in early warning signals?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Archiving the lab notebook on figshare</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/archiving-the-lab-notebook-on-figshare/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/archiving-the-lab-notebook-on-figshare/</guid>
      <description>Robust archiving through CLOCKSS One of the most comprehensive approaches I have come across so far uses figshare. This offers the most promising avenue for content preservation, but is weakest in managing the URIs and associating them with the original content. All figshare content is archived by CLOCKSS, an international library cooperation providing redundant and geopolitically distributed backup of the archives around the world (and used by many academic journals, both subscription based &amp;amp; open access).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automated feeds in notebook entries</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/automated-feeds-in-notebook-entries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/automated-feeds-in-notebook-entries/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the use of automated feeds in my notebook entries, which would make writing posts both faster and more complete. I had recently modified my Jekyll plugins to include commits on the day of the post. Consequently, I could add a bit of liquid code to any post, such as:
{% raw %}
{% octokit_commits pdg_control%}  {% endraw %}
(or even to the post template) and have the commit log for the specified repository automatically imported.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DOI != citable</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/doi--citable/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/doi--citable/</guid>
      <description>I feel I see this kind of comment almost daily:
Is there a way to obtain DOI for a @github repository? (for citing #opensource software packages, similar to @figshare objects) #git
&amp;mdash; Ahmed Moustafa (@AhmedMoustafa) May 29, 2013 
Again and again, researchers suggest that DOI to makes something &amp;ldquo;citable&amp;rdquo;. And this frustrates me.
Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong. I love DOIs, and I love CrossRef. And I bang on the table when I have some old journal article that doesn&amp;rsquo;t yet have a DOI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Jekyll layout</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/exploring-jekyll-layout/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/exploring-jekyll-layout/</guid>
      <description>Jekyll works wonderfully with little knowledge beyond basic html/css to create _layout templates and then you&amp;rsquo;re free to write beautiful pages and posts in markdown. But adding more dynamic content, the kind of cool stuff avialable in so many wordpress plugins, tends to require a little understanding of the template formatting language, Liquid. Liquid is actually super simple and powerful way to build a dynamic website. The project&amp;rsquo;s wiki provides a great introduction, starting with</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jekyll vs Wordpress</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/jekyll-vs-wordpress/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/jekyll-vs-wordpress/</guid>
      <description>I am now trying out a Jekyll-based platform rather than a Wordpress based for my website and lab notebook. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, the Wordpress site still remains where it was with links intact, I&amp;rsquo;ve simply remapped the homepage. For now this is an experiment, we&amp;rsquo;ll see how it goes.
Why switch? Speed Wordpress was great, meeting most of my needs for a customizable site that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t really accomplish in my first online notebook on OpenWetWare.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook Features: parsing linked data in the semantic notebook</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-parsing-linked-data-in-the-semantic-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-parsing-linked-data-in-the-semantic-notebook/</guid>
      <description>In a post a while back I originally put forward the idea of a semantic lab notebook. Semantics, or linked data, are among the most powerful concepts to emerge in online science for scholarly data organization and communication. I have slowly been adding and exploring new ways to introduce semantic concepts into the notebook, which I have documented along the way under my #semantics tag. In this post, rather than discuss how to generate the semantic data, I try to focus on some of the things we can do with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: SHA Hashes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-sha-hashes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-sha-hashes/</guid>
      <description>Note: this entry is part of a series of posts which explain some of the technical features of my lab notebook.
I version manage all changes to my entry using git. Each page is linked to its source history on Github, which will display a list of all previous edits to the post with an easy-to-read commit log and highlighted diffs. A version history is often considered an essential part of an open lab notebook, where changes to the notebook are documented and preserved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: an introduction</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-an-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-an-introduction/</guid>
      <description>In keeping this open lab notebook, I have sought to address three goals (in addition to all the traditional reasons for keeping a lab notebook)
 Provide an educational resource Experiment with scientific infrastructure and tools for sharing and replicating research Facilitate the rapid and open dissemination of scientific research  which are coincidentally evocative of NSF&amp;rsquo;s Broader Impacts areas. In this series of posts I plan to explore and illustrate some of my experiments to address these goals through various web-based tools available for an open notebook platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: digital archiving</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-digital-archiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-digital-archiving/</guid>
      <description>Note: this entry is part of a series of posts which explain some of the technical features of my lab notebook.
Archival preservation of digital scholarly content is an important challenge throughout the research community. As the notebook is the permanent record of my regular scholarly endeavors, this provides the opportunity to experiment with tools and techniques for digital archiving while also better preserving the notebook. In the experimental spirit that drives all my exploration here, I am testing several ways to accomplish this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: reproducible code</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-reproducible-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-reproducible-code/</guid>
      <description>I now use the dynamic documentation software called knitr to write most entries that shore results and figures. The code to replicate the results is included automatically, ensuring that what I say I did and what code I actually ran to get the results are consistent. Though I have written about knitr before, both regarding its use in my notebook and in my manuscripts, here I provide a quick summary of how a reader might actually reproduce a figure or result they come across in the notebook, as well as some of the possible problems involved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook tweaks: APIs in Ruby, Github hosting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-tweaks-apis-in-ruby-github-hosting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-tweaks-apis-in-ruby-github-hosting/</guid>
      <description>Crossref API and Faraday Looking at automating vita entries. The faraday gem looks like a nice general tool for API queries in Ruby (ht Martin Fenner)
 Example exploration  Mendeley API and omniauth  Omniauth appears to be a solution for Rails apps only? Not clear if it can be used in vanilla Ruby. Still stumped by this case; question on SO  Bisonomy and its API  RSS feeds too, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notes/</guid>
      <description>Returned proofs for warning signals paper. Wrightscape figures sent to Peter. move fallacy to a branch off of main in earlywaring package? Running knit on the large clusters means images cannot be uploaded as they are created, since compute nodes don&amp;rsquo;t have internet access. Saving files locally, I&amp;rsquo;ve created a little script to parse the output file.md to find the and upload the local images, and swap the local paths for the url paths.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Lab Notebook</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/semantic-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/semantic-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>As the lab notebook grows, to make the maximum use of content it would be particularly useful to maximize the ability for a computer to understand the content, allowing us to identify, manipulate, and connect data using scripts and software. This is the concept of linked data, or a semantic notebook. I have explored this this idea before in the context of a wordpress-based platform, but now that Jekyll has let me strip away some of the abstraction of Wordpress it seems a good time to revisit this idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solarized Colors with Twitter-Bootstrap?</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/solarized-colors-with-twitter-bootstrap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/solarized-colors-with-twitter-bootstrap/</guid>
      <description>Trying out rendering my notebook using Ethan Schoonover&amp;rsquo;s Solarized color scheme. The solarized palette has been selected according to Ethan&amp;rsquo;s exacting standards for contrast, symmetry, and readability.
My site CSS is built with Twitter-Bootstrap, which uses LESS to generate CSS files. Normal CSS is valid LESS code too, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the concept of a variable. So changing colors in CSS requires changing each and every occurance of some hex colorcode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my Lab Notebook - Reloaded</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook---reloaded/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook---reloaded/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my lab notebook, version 3.0. My original open lab notebooks began on the wiki platform OpenWetWare, moved to a personally hosted Wordpress platform, and now run on a Jekyll-powered platform (site-config), but the basic idea remains the same. For completeness, earlier entries from both platforms have been migrated here. Quoting from my original introduction to the Wordpress notebook:
 Disclaimer: Not a Blog  Welcome to my open lab notebook.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>