<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Hugo and blogdown</title>
      <link>/2017/04/19/migrating-to-hugo-and-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/19/migrating-to-hugo-and-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>After OpenWetWare (2010), Wordpress (2010 - 2012) and Jekyll (2012 - 2017), I move platforms once again: now to Hugo. Why the move? As usual, this site remains a way for me to explore new technologies, but the cutting edge is by no means the allure which leads me to migrate. Rather, I find myself ever trying to move towards simpler platforms, what’s easier to maintain, free to host, easier to replicate, and what makes best use of the most widely available and well-maintained existing software and avoids unncessary custom hacks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>knitr, github, and a new phase for the lab notebook</title>
      <link>/2012/03/21/knitr-github-and-a-new-phase-for-the-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 12:13:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/21/knitr-github-and-a-new-phase-for-the-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>I have recently modified the basic workflow of my lab notebook since discovering knitr. Before, I would write code files which I could track on github, push figures created by the code to flickr, and then write a notebook entry on wordpress describing what I was doing. I&amp;rsquo;d embed each figure I wanted into the entry, and each figure got an automatic link to github for the script that created it (which usually worked, though it didn&amp;rsquo;t say where in the script the command came from, and it required manually specifying the script name).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citing R packages</title>
      <link>/2012/03/20/citing-r-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2012 10:02:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/20/citing-r-packages/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m not always careful in citing all the R packages I use. R actually has some rather nice built-in mechanisms to support this, so I really have no excuse. Here&amp;rsquo;s some quick examples:
citation(&amp;quot;ouch&amp;quot;)  To cite the ouch package in publications use: Aaron A. King and Marguerite A. Butler (2009), ouch: Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models for phylogenetic comparative hypotheses (R package), http://ouch.r-forge.r-project.org Butler, M. A. and King, A. A. (2004) Phylogenetic comparative analysis: a modeling approach for adaptive evolution Am.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journey to freedom - a code&#39;s tale of open source license migration</title>
      <link>/2012/01/31/journey-to-freedom-a-codes-tale-of-open-source-license-migration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2012 17:58:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/31/journey-to-freedom-a-codes-tale-of-open-source-license-migration/</guid>
      <description>My software wants to be free. It wants to be seen and used and loved by as many people as possible. When first it heard of open source licenses, it set sail to join the company of great software in the promised land, but finding true freedom has been a tortured journey.
In the clutches of the GPL Created and defended by the Free Software Foundation and used by such venerable institutions as the Linux Kernel, the gcc compiler, and the R statistical environment, the GNU&amp;rsquo;s General Public License seemed like a gold standard to call home.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are open lab notebooks considered prior publication?</title>
      <link>/2012/01/16/are-open-lab-notebooks-considered-prior-publication/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2012 10:47:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/16/are-open-lab-notebooks-considered-prior-publication/</guid>
      <description>This question invariably comes up at some point in any discussion of open notebook science. This concern is usually voiced in reference to the high-visibility magazines, which many scientists seem to assume will have very restrictive conditions. A quick read of their policies shows otherwise. Here are the links to pre-publication policies of major journals, with my short summaries &amp;amp; comments.
Nature - Go right ahead. Explicit protection clause for open/collaborative blogs/wikis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How google views me: by search terms or citation counts?</title>
      <link>/2011/09/09/how-google-views-me-by-search-terms-or-citation-counts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2011 09:55:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/09/how-google-views-me-by-search-terms-or-citation-counts/</guid>
      <description>How Google search views me: here&amp;rsquo;s a word cloud of search terms reaching my site in August. Word cloud produced with R: click-through for link to source-code. Uses the rather convenient tm package for text-mining functions in R. Note that this shows the frequency of individual words used in searches, rather than the whole search term.
Code:
require(tm) require(wordcloud) require(RColorBrewer) carl &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;searchterms.csv&amp;quot;, colClasses=c(&amp;quot;character&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;numeric&amp;quot;)) words &amp;lt;- character(sum(carl[[2]])) m &amp;lt;- 1 for(i in 1:length(carl[[1]])){ n &amp;lt;- carl[[2]][i] x &amp;lt;- carl[[1]][i] words[m:(m+(n-1))] &amp;lt;- rep(x, n) m &amp;lt;- m+n } carl &amp;lt;- Corpus(DataframeSource(carl)) carl &amp;lt;- tm_map(carl, removePunctuation) carl &amp;lt;- tm_map(carl, tolower) carl.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citation tools &amp; Future of Publishing</title>
      <link>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 23:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of rapid development in scientific tools based on a Wordpress platform recently, perhaps spurred in part by the recent Beyond-the-PDF and sessions in Science Online conferences. A new discussion group has emerged around these tools, as described by Martin Fenner.
I have been exploring better tools for citation management within my lab notebook. Recently I have been using the papercite plugin to add citations from my BibTeX files, which are generated from Mendeley, as I described earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Mangement on UC3 Merritt Repository</title>
      <link>/2011/02/16/data-mangement-on-uc3-merritt-repository/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 19:06:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/16/data-mangement-on-uc3-merritt-repository/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to learn a little more about the potential for data management solutions through the UC3 Merritt repository, and decide how this compares to commercial alternatives such as Amazon S3, Picasa/Flickr (obviously for images only), and field-specific and publication specific repositories such as Dryad. Merritt email support have been very helpful in answering my questions and concerns.
 Persistence: of the data itself, of the URLs &amp;amp; object identifiers, of access to the data?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Data: Plans for a UC Davis workshop</title>
      <link>/2011/02/01/the-future-of-data-preparing-researchers-to-face-new-funding-and-publishing-policies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 09:40:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/01/the-future-of-data-preparing-researchers-to-face-new-funding-and-publishing-policies/</guid>
      <description>I have been working with several of the faculty of UC Davis to prepare a workshop for our department to (1) help make our researchers aware of the new requirements for NSF proposals and journal submissions with regard to data archiving, (2) To explore what new opportunities this creates and what tools exist that will help our researchers take maximum advantage of it, and (3) to engage our research community in the discussion of future standards for sharing, standardizing, rewarding and funding the archiving of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections from #scio11: Saturday&#39;s Open Science Track</title>
      <link>/2011/01/15/reflections-from-scio11-saturdays-open-science-track/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2011 23:12:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/15/reflections-from-scio11-saturdays-open-science-track/</guid>
      <description>Have just returned from the amazing and energetic science online 2011 conference, where I will now, like the rest of the attendees, turn to catching up on sleep, following new online acquaintances, struggling not to append #scio11 to everything I write, and composing that nearly obligatory post-event blog entry we all use like a glass of water after a party; with the hope in may help me metabolize the experience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on the New Policies for Data Archiving at NSF and in Common Journals</title>
      <link>/2010/12/03/nsf-and-journal-data-archiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2010 19:08:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/03/nsf-and-journal-data-archiving/</guid>
      <description>This post is a work in progress, a scratch pad for me to start assembling what I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning about and resources pertaining to the new policies emerging from NSF and journals relevant to ecology and evolution. Hoping to highlight not only the policies, but the issues, opportunities, and concerns around them.
I am hoping to help organize a workshop to discuss these issues in my department this Winter. The Davis Open Science group, is planning a series of these workshops, hoping to work with departments, the libraries and the UC Davis Office of Research and its Responsible Conduct of Research  program (in compliance with NIH/NSF ethics requirements), as well as resident faculty and editors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today, Scott Collins, the president of the Ecological Society of America has announced that the society will now accept articles that have previously been posted on preprint servers. This comes on the heels of a growing discussion in our community. Ethan White has a good summary over on Jabberwocky Ecology.
Many voices have joined the discussion over the past month, and it is exciting and vindicating to see the Society engage and discuss these questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to a recent bugfix in the exitwp scripts I was able to export all my Wordpress entries. The script pulls the entries from the Wordpress database and formats them in markdown, along with extracting all metadata such as timestamp, tags, categories, publication status, and Wordpress id number, which are all embedded as YAML header information.
Why migrate the old entries? When I moved to the Jekyll notebook, I left the Wordpress site standing with all its existing content and simply remapped the home pages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>C. Titus Brown has an excellent post discussing his exploration into the merits and technicalities cross-posting his blog posts to figshare. The rfigshare package written by Ted Hart and myself can do just this, once we puzzled out some of the same challenges (Notes to Titus: though the documentation doesn&amp;rsquo;t mention it, you can get a programmatic list of available categories from http://api.figshare.com/v1/categories. Figshare can also take code as a fileset or dataset, and may soon add a type for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Github issues tracker has increasingly become my research to-do list. Far beyond bugs and features of the code associated with the project, the issues sign-post different directions for investigation and the progress I&amp;rsquo;ve made in each. Tags serve to group issues related to a common sub-project (as in my pdg-control) repo or priotize tasks (as in my nonparametric-bayes repo.
Issues not only have title and tags, but support a comment thread for progress and discussion of the issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>I have on ocassion been exploring the use of semantic markup in the notebook. In this post I illustrate how I am handling semantic citations. One of the more intriguing ideas is the ability to add semantic meaning to citations through the CITO ontology of Shotton (2010). Citation counts form a central part of academic discourse, but contain very little information regarding the reason for the citation. Most notably, &amp;lsquo;negative&amp;rsquo; citations refuting a claim carry just the same weight as those confirming or relying upon a claim.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Just because I&amp;rsquo;m a theorist deeply entrenched in methodological concerns about uncertainty and decision making doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I don&amp;rsquo;t think about practical conservation from time to time. Some musings from my comment here, copied over for my own reference.
Though I would like to believe the gap stems from the problems you discuss, I think that differing objectives between research and application may play a much larger role. I suspect that scientific papers that are most useful and influential for conservation practitioners and policymakers are those which confirm what they already believe, or whatever the interests opposed to them least want to hear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Sustainable Research Happened across a provocative example of why we need a software ecosystem, though it was certainly not intended to be one, which led me to ask myself:
 How complex does an algorithm have to be before a talented researcher with expertise in both the relevant mathematics and computer science will make a significant mistake in their first release of the software?
 As a corollary we might also ask, &amp;ldquo;How much less care do we put into research code not destined for release?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Author&amp;rsquo;s Note: Having refrained from actually posting this for 8 months, as I think I have quite mellowed more my critique. I do believe that education and peer review are the best way forward in tackling these issues, but cannot overstate how much of a long and rocky road that process will be. The Mozilla Science Foundation is really leading these efforts with their code review pilots (as I have discussed in posts since writing this), and through their work with Software Carpentry training.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Several weeks ago I wrote a post describing issues I commonly raise when reviewing software papers. This provoked a lively discussion among authors, editors, and other reviewers of software papers (most of us having been on at least both reviewing and authoring end), with quite varied perspectives as to whether such criteria were appropriate in this context. As I describe there, I view the concept of dedicated software papers as a somewhat necessary &amp;ldquo;hack&amp;rdquo; of the publishing system, and hope a more mature system will eventually come into place, as is now happening for data through efforts such as Dryad and associated journal archiving requirements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>All I really wanted to do is cite a paper in the R Journal, which is peer-reviewed, open access (CC-BY), LaTeX based and without author charges. Sure, I could do that already, but I like being able to programmatically generate citation metadata from a URL &amp;ndash; we do have this thing called the internet now, and citations are just links, right? Unfortunately, nice as it is, the R journal doesn&amp;rsquo;t have HTML landing pages for articles that embed the metadata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Archiving the lab notebook on figshare</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/archiving-the-lab-notebook-on-figshare/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/archiving-the-lab-notebook-on-figshare/</guid>
      <description>Robust archiving through CLOCKSS One of the most comprehensive approaches I have come across so far uses figshare. This offers the most promising avenue for content preservation, but is weakest in managing the URIs and associating them with the original content. All figshare content is archived by CLOCKSS, an international library cooperation providing redundant and geopolitically distributed backup of the archives around the world (and used by many academic journals, both subscription based &amp;amp; open access).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DOI != citable</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/doi--citable/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/doi--citable/</guid>
      <description>I feel I see this kind of comment almost daily:
Is there a way to obtain DOI for a @github repository? (for citing #opensource software packages, similar to @figshare objects) #git
&amp;mdash; Ahmed Moustafa (@AhmedMoustafa) May 29, 2013 
Again and again, researchers suggest that DOI to makes something &amp;ldquo;citable&amp;rdquo;. And this frustrates me.
Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong. I love DOIs, and I love CrossRef. And I bang on the table when I have some old journal article that doesn&amp;rsquo;t yet have a DOI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do we need a culture of Data Science in Academia?</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/do-we-need-a-culture-of-data-science-in-academia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/do-we-need-a-culture-of-data-science-in-academia/</guid>
      <description>Just my draft copy of a Guest blog post I wrote for Dynamic Ecology.
On Tuesday the Whitehouse Office of Science and Technology Policy announced the creation of a $37.8 million dollar initiative to promote a &amp;ldquo;Data Science Culture&amp;rdquo; in academic institutions, funded by the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and hosted in centers at the universities UC Berkeley, University of Washington, and New York University.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it time to retire Pagel&#39;s lambda?</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/is-it-time-to-retire-pagels-lambda/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/is-it-time-to-retire-pagels-lambda/</guid>
      <description>Pagel&amp;rsquo;s $\lambda$ (lambda), introduced in Pagel 1999 as a potential measure of &amp;ldquo;phylogenetic signal,&amp;rdquo; the extent to which correlations in traits reflect their shared evolutionary history (as approximated by Brownian motion).
Numerous critiques and ready alternatives have not appeared to decrease it&amp;rsquo;s popularity. There are many issues with the statistic, some of which I attempt to summarise below.
The $\lambda$ statistic is defined by the Brownian motion model together with a transformation of the branch lengths: multiply all internal branches by $\lambda$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook Features: parsing linked data in the semantic notebook</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-parsing-linked-data-in-the-semantic-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-parsing-linked-data-in-the-semantic-notebook/</guid>
      <description>In a post a while back I originally put forward the idea of a semantic lab notebook. Semantics, or linked data, are among the most powerful concepts to emerge in online science for scholarly data organization and communication. I have slowly been adding and exploring new ways to introduce semantic concepts into the notebook, which I have documented along the way under my #semantics tag. In this post, rather than discuss how to generate the semantic data, I try to focus on some of the things we can do with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: SHA Hashes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-sha-hashes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-sha-hashes/</guid>
      <description>Note: this entry is part of a series of posts which explain some of the technical features of my lab notebook.
I version manage all changes to my entry using git. Each page is linked to its source history on Github, which will display a list of all previous edits to the post with an easy-to-read commit log and highlighted diffs. A version history is often considered an essential part of an open lab notebook, where changes to the notebook are documented and preserved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: an introduction</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-an-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-an-introduction/</guid>
      <description>In keeping this open lab notebook, I have sought to address three goals (in addition to all the traditional reasons for keeping a lab notebook)
 Provide an educational resource Experiment with scientific infrastructure and tools for sharing and replicating research Facilitate the rapid and open dissemination of scientific research  which are coincidentally evocative of NSF&amp;rsquo;s Broader Impacts areas. In this series of posts I plan to explore and illustrate some of my experiments to address these goals through various web-based tools available for an open notebook platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: digital archiving</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-digital-archiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-digital-archiving/</guid>
      <description>Note: this entry is part of a series of posts which explain some of the technical features of my lab notebook.
Archival preservation of digital scholarly content is an important challenge throughout the research community. As the notebook is the permanent record of my regular scholarly endeavors, this provides the opportunity to experiment with tools and techniques for digital archiving while also better preserving the notebook. In the experimental spirit that drives all my exploration here, I am testing several ways to accomplish this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook features: reproducible code</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-features-reproducible-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-features-reproducible-code/</guid>
      <description>I now use the dynamic documentation software called knitr to write most entries that shore results and figures. The code to replicate the results is included automatically, ensuring that what I say I did and what code I actually ran to get the results are consistent. Though I have written about knitr before, both regarding its use in my notebook and in my manuscripts, here I provide a quick summary of how a reader might actually reproduce a figure or result they come across in the notebook, as well as some of the possible problems involved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on the Mozilla Science Code Review Pilot</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/reflections-on-the-mozilla-science-code-review-pilot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/reflections-on-the-mozilla-science-code-review-pilot/</guid>
      <description>I was recently interviewed a Nature senior reporter Erika Check Hayden on the subject of the scientific code review project being conducted by Mozilla Science Lab. The piece appears in this week&amp;rsquo;s issue, Hayden 2013. My blog post sharing my own approach to code review is mentioned at the beginning of the article, though it is rather Roger Peng&amp;rsquo;s comments at the end that have stirred some interesting discussion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Lab Notebook</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/semantic-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/semantic-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>As the lab notebook grows, to make the maximum use of content it would be particularly useful to maximize the ability for a computer to understand the content, allowing us to identify, manipulate, and connect data using scripts and software. This is the concept of linked data, or a semantic notebook. I have explored this this idea before in the context of a wordpress-based platform, but now that Jekyll has let me strip away some of the abstraction of Wordpress it seems a good time to revisit this idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>So, you&#39;re active on Research Gate?</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/so-youre-active-on-research-gate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/so-youre-active-on-research-gate/</guid>
      <description>I have occassionally been getting this question:
 So, you&amp;rsquo;re active on ResearchGate?
 Sounds like being accused of some scandal, doesn&amp;rsquo;t it?
I&amp;rsquo;m not generally active on it - my impression is that the open science community is mostly skeptical about ResearchGate and any other &amp;ldquo;Social Network&amp;rdquo; for scientists, largely on the grounds that &amp;ldquo;we already use the same social networks everyone else uses.&amp;rdquo; Some object on more philosophical grounds (profit, Mendeley, etc), but heck I publish in Elsevier/Springer/Wiley so I won&amp;rsquo;t preach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my Lab Notebook - Reloaded</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook---reloaded/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook---reloaded/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to my lab notebook, version 3.0. My original open lab notebooks began on the wiki platform OpenWetWare, moved to a personally hosted Wordpress platform, and now run on a Jekyll-powered platform (site-config), but the basic idea remains the same. For completeness, earlier entries from both platforms have been migrated here. Quoting from my original introduction to the Wordpress notebook:
 Disclaimer: Not a Blog  Welcome to my open lab notebook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I look for in &#39;Software Papers&#39;</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/what-i-look-for-in-software-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/what-i-look-for-in-software-papers/</guid>
      <description>Update Thanks to the rich discussion in the comments and beyond, I&amp;rsquo;ve revised my thoughts on this somewhat, as I discuss in this more recent post.
I am more and more frequently reviewing &amp;lsquo;software papers:&amp;rsquo; which I define as publications whose primary purpose is to publicize a piece of scientific software and provide a traditional research product with hopes that it will receive citations and recognition from other researchers in grant and job reviews.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>manuscript reviews on github?</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/manuscript-reviews-on-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/manuscript-reviews-on-github/</guid>
      <description>I was recently impressed to learn of Trevor Bedford&amp;rsquo;s strategy of seeking pre-approval for posting his reviewer&amp;rsquo;s comments as Github issues. Beyond providing links to the data and source-code, I generally don&amp;rsquo;t advertise the open science nature of papers I submit &amp;ndash; I guess I assume that if the reader or reviewers care, it should be easy enough for them to discover it. Consequently I am usually immediately frustrated to realize that upon receiving my reviews I have to create a second, private repository for the review material, our replies to reviewers, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>