<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>My Publications on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/my-publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in My Publications on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 14:10:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/my-publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Is your phylogeny informative?</title>
      <link>/2012/01/19/is-your-phylogeny-informative/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 14:10:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/19/is-your-phylogeny-informative/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday my paper (Boettiger et. al. 2012) appeared in early view in Evolution (author&amp;rsquo;s preprint),As the open access copy doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear on pubmed for a while, you can access my author&amp;rsquo;s copy here. so I&amp;rsquo;d like to take this chance to share the back-story and highlight my own view on some of our findings, and the associated package on CRAN.Just submitted, meanwhile, the code is always on github.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t set out to write this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Two years ago, I scribbled an entry into my notebook entitled Wrong Picture, Wrong Model: Why warning signals don&amp;rsquo;t look like rare events. Months later I made some off-hand remark to Alan (my Ph.D. mentor) about how transitions found in historical records, such as the Climate examples in Dakos et. al. (2008), could actually be selecting for stochastic transitions, and this selection process might make them look like traditional warning signals &amp;ndash; i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limits to the detection of early warning signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/limits-to-the-detection-of-early-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/limits-to-the-detection-of-early-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Our paper, limits to the detection of early warning signals for critical transitions, has now appeared in the Proceedings of the Royal Interface. An open-access copy is available under CC-by license on the ArXiv. The essence of the paper is to bring a more model-based approach to early warning signals, while seeking to remain as general as possible.
Without a model-based approach, it is difficult to leverage statistically meaningful comparisons to identify what is a real warning signal and what is just noise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Prosecutor&#39;s Fallacy paper and other recent warning signals literature</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/my-prosecutors-fallacy-paper-and-other-recent-warning-signals-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/my-prosecutors-fallacy-paper-and-other-recent-warning-signals-literature/</guid>
      <description>My recent paper with Alan Hastings, &amp;ldquo;Early warning signals and the prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s fallacy&amp;rdquo;, is now out in PRSB. An open access preprint can be found on the (arXiv) and accompanying (source code) for the analysis can be found on Github.
Recent papers in early warning signals This invistigation is in a very similar spirit to two other recent papers on the subject. Kéfi et al. addresses a different kind of false positive for early warning signals, arising in systems approaching other transitions or bifurcations than the intended culprit, the saddle-node bifurcation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>