<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Code Tricks on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/code-tricks.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Code Tricks on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 10:39:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/code-tricks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Catching up</title>
      <link>/2012/04/19/catching-up.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 10:39:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/19/catching-up.html</guid>
      <description>Catching up on notebook entries for last week and the beginning of this week in one go here. In the process of wrapping up a variety of older projects, so this is kinda all over the place.
rfishbase  Create function table, finalize functions Add support for references. Done, see getRefs. (And isn&amp;rsquo;t it awesome that you can link to a specific linenumber (i.e. line 280) in github by adding #L280 to the end of the url?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: some random notes</title>
      <link>/2012/03/20/friday-some-random-notes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2012 16:53:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/20/friday-some-random-notes.html</guid>
      <description>Computational tricks  tables in github markdown via knitr. clever Getting custom C/C++ CUDA working in R  Data management and sharing solutions for large files  NERSC uses globus online for interface for transferring terabytes/hr, pretty clever. NERSC also enables web hosting to share data.
 Software-Carpentry style Data management a nice start. An open solution could stick the data on figshare (or elsewhere), write the readmes in markdown and keep them on github with links to the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/02/27/monday-14.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 15:20:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/27/monday-14.html</guid>
      <description>Warning Signals  Added resulting indicator distributions on finer sampling results.
 Re-running now excluding the final dive (population below 300).
  Treebase working on manuscript. A few examples using the improved meta-data queries:
Computing configuration vim and R  install vim-r-plugin. Download, then run vim-addons install r-plugin install screen plugin add to .vimrc:   set nocompatible syntax enable filetype plugin on filetype indent on let vimrplugin_underscore = 0   learn some key bindings Really \rf to launch, and \d Also see this post for configuration with vim-latex-suite.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: writing; some latexdiff notes</title>
      <link>/2012/02/10/thursday-writing-some-latexdiff-notes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2012 10:06:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/10/thursday-writing-some-latexdiff-notes.html</guid>
      <description>Forage fish writing See doc, FF dropbox PopDyn
Warning signals edits  Alan edits Figure captions, titles.
 Text changes from Noam.
  A better git latexdiff solution Placing the script below somewhere in the path like /usr/local/bin and modify ~/.gitconfig as indicated in the header comments. Then oen can view pdf-diffs of the latex of the current version against previous versions with commands such as
git latexdiff HEAD  shows the differences between the last commit and the current (uncommitted) changes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/01/30/monday-15.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2012 19:38:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/30/monday-15.html</guid>
      <description>pdg-control, aside exercise Lab group commented that optimum in Reed model looks unrealistic due to frequency with which it shuts down all fishing. This is an artifact of not having extraction costs increase sufficiently for small catch, and can be easily fixed by increasing that cost (c in the profit eq, profits-costs = p*x-c/x)
view sourcecode, Reed.R
NIMBioS short visitor application Have been thinking that it would be really useful to have some extra time at Nimbios to meet with folks at the time of our next working group meeting (March 12-15).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday -- meetings</title>
      <link>/2012/01/18/wednesday-meetings.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 23:22:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/18/wednesday-meetings.html</guid>
      <description>Alan meeting write write write
Duncan Meeting Troubleshooting S3 and S4 Try adding methods? Changing order on NAMESPACE?
Leaving ouch off the import list: no errors, but within functions, don&amp;rsquo;t get S4 method. import but don&amp;rsquo;t depend on ouch: error. accurate, since simulate is left as an s3 function at the user level.
What a headache. See stackQ.
manuscript Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback
Meredith Meeting Run a science policy workshop with Davis open science group?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday - Sweave workflow</title>
      <link>/2012/01/09/monday-13.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 22:09:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/09/monday-13.html</guid>
      <description>Bibtex, Mendeley &amp;amp; Sweave Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s repeated entries in the bibfile is particularly annoying with my sweave workflow, as it throws an error from bibtex command that Make doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to ignore.
Also, in writing the documentation I&amp;rsquo;d like to point the .Rnw file to my global library&amp;rsquo;s bibtex document, but then this means having the .Rnw/tex file generated to by the package pointing to a file that&amp;rsquo;s outside the package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Better dynamic documents (Sweave) with syntax highlighting, caching, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/12/12/better-sweave-dynamic-documents-with-syntax-highlighting-easier-tools.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 17:26:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/12/better-sweave-dynamic-documents-with-syntax-highlighting-easier-tools.html</guid>
      <description>The highlight package is a simple solution for very nice syntax highlighted code boxes in latex documents. Requires switching the driver, which is best done from within R and requires creating a makefile though. Needs the &amp;ldquo;highlight&amp;rdquo; package installed. Here&amp;rsquo;s a simple makefile.
A wealth/mess of Sweave related packages on the CRAN taskview for Reproducible Research (now what other software platform has a the equivalent of a Reproducible Research task view?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday, wordpress backups, pmc edits</title>
      <link>/2011/09/30/friday-wordpress-backups-pmc-edits.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 17:51:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/30/friday-wordpress-backups-pmc-edits.html</guid>
      <description>Wordpress local copy  configured mysqldump backup, following dreamhost wiki (added cron job manually instead of in panel).  edit local wp-config.php to use localhost. Get the database name, user name and password from the lines above it, which are used later.
define(&#39;DB_HOST&#39;, &#39;localhost&#39;); // ...and the server MySQL is running on  create user: log in as root
mysql -u root -p  and create user
mysql&amp;gt; create database database_name mysql&amp;gt; create user &#39;username&#39;@&#39;localhost&#39; identified by &#39;password&#39;; mysql&amp;gt; create database database_name mysql&amp;gt; grant usage on *.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday: git with latexdiff, TreeBASE and PMC package updates, bounds on lambda</title>
      <link>/2011/06/04/saturday-git-with-latexdiff-ropensci-and-pmc-package-updates-bounds-on-lambda.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2011 21:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/04/saturday-git-with-latexdiff-ropensci-and-pmc-package-updates-bounds-on-lambda.html</guid>
      <description>bounds on lambda: Updated the pmc wrappers for fit_continuous to pass bounds on lambda to the bootstrapping Monte Carlo functions. Settled on passing all options explicitly after quite a bit of effort. Looking for way to pass a function all of it&amp;rsquo;s arguments as a named arguments in a list; statscicomp list suggested do.call() function; quite brilliant.
Considering user workflow for wrappers. Conceptually, makes sense for user to run the standard package fit routines first, and then pass the results to pmc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: PMC, confidence intervals; screen code-tricks</title>
      <link>/2011/05/31/tuesday-5.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2011 14:38:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/31/tuesday-5.html</guid>
      <description>PMC  Final read through of manuscript from me and Peter.
 Looking at confidence intervals in fitContinuous? Package used to use the hessian from optim, but it was later removed due to errors. I added this back manually and attempt a few estimates. Given the Hessian (likelihood surface curvature) this is approximated by
sqrt(diag(solve(out$hessian)))
 See conf_interval_ex.R. i.e for Geospiza tree is:
[1] SE sigma: +/ 0.6763731 SE lambda: +/- 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Site configuration: file sharing notes</title>
      <link>/2011/05/28/notebook-technology-file-sharing-notes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2011 23:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/28/notebook-technology-file-sharing-notes.html</guid>
      <description>Easiest way to share files is ssh onto the carlboettiger.info server, change into the directory carlboettiger.info/ and create a new directory there &amp;ndash; i.e. share/. This behaves as a regular static webpage directory that will list the files provided.
Secure access can be created by going to the goodies &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;htaccess/WebDav page and selecting the option to make a directory or subdirectory secure, and then specifying the passwords, etc. Have created the subdirectory http://carlboettiger.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/24/tuesday-4.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2011 23:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/24/tuesday-4.html</guid>
      <description>Warning signals package  Reviewing Numerical challenges for faster analysis on warningsignals
 created a quick mcmcTools package so different packages can use my custom routines. Will have to explore some of the standard packages eventually, though most seem somewhat specialized (the Bayesian task-view is epic). bayesm looks promising, and LearnBayes package that accompanies Jim Albert&amp;rsquo;s book (Albert, unknown) might be worth a closer look.
 Wrote mcmc script for warningsignals, much more debugging to handle out-of-bounds conditions then expected.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Notes, presentation prep treebase error handling</title>
      <link>/2011/04/28/thursday-reading-notes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2011 13:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/28/thursday-reading-notes.html</guid>
      <description>Reading  Oikos journal recently started a rather nice blog. A journal long responsible for some of the best examples of developing and confronting ecological theory with empirical results, with an commendable emphasis on general principles and synthesis, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to see them enter the Web2.0 ecosystem. Editor Jeremy Fox has a nice introduction to the goals of the blog &amp;ndash; check out the &amp;ldquo;new ideas&amp;rdquo; categories for worthwhile reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Fallacy paper done Dissertation filing Decision theory from the ROC curve.
 Working group paper Jim/Mike paper
 wrightscape paper?
 Signature page two copies, archival paper?
 ropensci emails: Position paper: Goals
 misc emails
  Fallacy paper finalizing appendices  Commit images and runs from yesterday (ibm simulation still running&amp;hellip;)
 clean up appendix code
 clean up appendix text
  Code tricks for today vim set sytnax language, useful for getting R highlighting in .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>This Open Lab Notebook started on a public MediaWiki-based site, OpenWetWare (OWW), which was created with the ambitious vision of having a single wiki for biological sciences (or at least, synthetic microbiology, since such the wiki grew out of a collection of such labs). Users could have their own pages that served as a personal website or lab group site, contribute pages on specific protocols, host course websites, and most interestingly, were encouraged to create open lab notebooks using specially designed templates for the purpose.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>multiple-uncertainty  Fixed issues with translation to matlab and applyfun. Element-wise calls can use meshgrid arguments directly, and one can force functions to use element-wise operations with bxfun. So the following are equivalent: :  [X, Y] = meshgrid(x,y) applyfun(@min, X, Y)  or
function out = element_min(x,y) bxfun(@min, x, y) element_min(X, Y)  Meanwhile my challenge with additional arguments to applyfun can be circumvented with an inline function,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Reading  (Schreiber &amp;amp; Killingback, 2013 ) (Warren, 2013 )  Notebook  Added SHA hashes. See notebook Issues #67 for details. modification date. #74, also involved resolving page path robustly, #73 analytics on history button, layout #72 push dreamhost-based images to flickr See #75  prosecutor Run with OU based data. Draw from sde package.
Packages Knitcitations  Feature request for additional markup for page ranges #32  rfigshare  Handle pull request for rfigshare  code-tricks: notes on merging select files from pull request Pull request included changes to files we don&amp;rsquo;t want to change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Misc coding  knitcitations handling of html formatting in tooltip: html inside the tag must needs be escaped. knitcitations/#37
 pmc functions
  hmm.. how do we easily wrap a function such that it returns its arguments (given and default) in a named list (appropriate for do.call(function_name, args_list))? match.call() inside the function will give the literal string of how the function was called, which, if evaluated in the same environment with same variables in working space, will return the same results, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t lend itself to updating any one of those arguments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Mangel group talk  Presented nonparametric-bayes slides ADP introduction / trouble-shooting (see yesterday&amp;rsquo;s entry), html5 slides  Notes  Decent convergence in the forward algorithm is hard. Consider basis function representation of value function to decrease the search space in the backwards-algorithm first. Also consider searching for policy function (under appropriate piecewise constraints). Starts to sound more and more similar to POMDP  Misc  Trouble with equations in slidify/214 Finishing up posts from last week</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Exploring XML Schema in R I danced around the room after reading these lines in the excellent XML and Web Technologies for Data Sciences with R book:
 We can generate S4 class definitions corresponding to the data structures that are represented in the XML document. We can programmatically generate R code that will map an XML document adhering to this schema to corresponding R data structures. Similarly, we can automate the creation of code to serialize, or write, an R object of a particular type to a suitable XML format corresponding to the schema</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Remote RStudio configuration (keep forgetting options and ports).
ssh -o &amp;quot;ExitOnForwardFailure yes&amp;quot; -f -N -L 1234:localhost:8787 one  Initialize runs for sensitivity, looping over parameters and data. See:
 sensitivity.md (Myers) sensitivity-allen.md  Overall:
ggplot(yields_dat) + geom_density(aes(value))  Compare over 12 simulation configurations with different parameters and different training data, the GP does consistently well. Only one case has relatively poor outcomes.
ggplot(yields_dat) + geom_density(aes(value, color=as.factor(simulation), fill=as.factor(simulation)), alpha=.5)   Run data backup to local disk NSF expense accounting calendar updates software paper policies email Luke Arbor reply looking at quick way to check out solutions to sums of Fisher wave equation over different diffusion coefficients (heterogenous dispersal rates), e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;d like to define a class that acts just like a data.frame, just like the data.table class does, but contains some additional metadata (e.g. the units associated with the columns) and has some additional methods associated with it (e.g. that might do something with those units) while also working with any function that simply knows how to handle data.frame objects.
How might this be done?
I&amp;rsquo;m not really sure where to start on this, so below is a summary of my attempt so far and some further puzzles I have stumbled across (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>2014-02-19 R allows you to specify &amp;gt;= in a package dependency, not ==. The Comprehensive R Archive Network, CRAN, makes no requirement that package authors do not break their previous function API. For instance, if version 0.1 of the package had a function
foo &amp;lt;- function(x, y = 5){ ... }  then one could add new functionality in say, version 0.2 without breaking the existing API with a definition that looked like:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>labnotebook Updates to configuration to be more portable and lightweight:
 Drop APIs for Mendeley and Github in favor of just pulling from atom/rss feeds. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t require a platform-specific API or authentication, and has proven more robust, if sometimes less flexible and fancy. Drop git-modified and sha timestamps. It&amp;rsquo;s nice having these on the pages and included in the rdfa, but the information is accessible from the git repository and from Github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Reading Looking for this in my notes and couldn&amp;rsquo;t find it: An excellent paper from the Software Sustainability Institute and friends outlining the need and possible structure for sustaining career paths for software developers. &amp;ldquo;The research software engineer&amp;rdquo;, Dirk Gorissen. Provides a good response to the software issues highlighted by climategate, etc.
Remote conferencing (Based on earlier unposted notes). With so much going on, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to be able to follow highlights from some conferences remotely</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Berkeley Collaborative Environment Trying out the Berkeley image (Essentially ubuntu 14.04 XFCE with ipython and RStudio installed, but finely tuned to improve user experience; e.g. solid colors for faster remote window connections.)
Highly recommend their paper for the first explanation I&amp;rsquo;ve actually been able to follow that provides a definition of &amp;ldquo;DevOpts&amp;rdquo; (essentially, using scripts rather than documentation to manage consistent cross-platform installation) and explains the differences and similarities between the various programs operating in this sphere, sometimes as alternatives and simultaneously.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Writing  Working on / finishing up slides for ESA talk and slides for hastingsfest  Exploring  Poking around a bit more in Docker yesterday, built some basic R containers for testing ropensci packages. https://github.com/ropensci/docker-ubuntu-r/tree/master/add-r-ropensci . Somewhat skeptical but still curious about the potential (or the need) to publish a docker image as a reproducible research object.
 Attempted to add Travis builds to the Docker repo (just for fun, eh?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics.html</guid>
      <description>compiling with R and C and parallel computing  Problem: cannot get the R code to take advantage of parallelization via openMP.
 Solution:
  C++ file mangles names in .so, changing the .C call. to get the object name:
objdump -x file.so  Carl Boettiger 03:01, 25 May 2010 (EDT): More standard solution: enclose cpp code in
 extern C {  
 Problem: Trouble getting R to export the C library to all nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual Progress Report</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report.html</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow will be meeting with my dissertation committee: Alan Hastings, Peter Wainwright, and Brian Moore. This provides a good opportunity to summarize the status of my current projects and my principle accomplishments for the year. Will try a tex&amp;rsquo;d document as I&amp;rsquo;ve done in previous years but here&amp;rsquo;s for some preliminary brainstorming.
 Summary: In the past year, I&amp;rsquo;ve published one paper, given 4 talks (CPB, NIMBioS, Berkeley, IIASA), read 144+ articles and wrote 9000+ lines of code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Picture Comparative Phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/big-picture-comparative-phylogenetics.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/big-picture-comparative-phylogenetics.html</guid>
      <description>A Task View on Phylogenetic Comparative Methods (in R on CRAN) has been released today, maintained by Brian O&amp;rsquo;Meara. Quite thorough and concise.
 Follow-up discussion on:
 List is useful, but would be nice to be able to expand / collapse the list to see more / less details about the functions available. More detail makes it harder to maintain, perhaps get the developers involved? List is also quite provocative source to realize what&amp;rsquo;s missing (there&amp;rsquo;s no way to estimate ancestral states under OU using existing software?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Survey</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/csgf-survey.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/csgf-survey.html</guid>
      <description>Wrote survey. Getting feedback and will send out this week.  previous comments
Wiki Tricks Exploring use of mvs to download and upload entries from openwetware. The mediawiki client is easy to install as described in the link. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have a tool to grab everything in my Notebook namespace, but with a little bash script I can grab all the entries in a particular notebook:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/entry-title.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/entry-title.html</guid>
      <description>Automated scripts for image uploads. Tag-based generation of a slideshow:


Running the script:
 ./flickr_slideshow *.png  Creates the html code that can be embedded into the notebook for a slideshow those images. Images only get the date-time tag as a unique id.


This one uses the mediawiki plugin. More formatting options could be incorporated of course. (Creates the thumbnail images down the right-hand side).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extending ape::phylo class to NeXML:</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/extending-apephylo-class-to-nexml.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/extending-apephylo-class-to-nexml.html</guid>
      <description>While working on the RNeXML package, I have recently I have been puzzling over extending S3 objects to share some of the nice properties of S4 objects and methods while continuing to function with the potentially huge library of functions written to work with them. SO:
To illustrate this issue, consider the S3 class phylo provided by the ape package and used by most of the 30+ packages that reverse depend or reverse import ape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/goals.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/goals.html</guid>
      <description>Model choice exercise with sdes general likelihood calculation from simulation  Test Case *dX*~t~ = α~t~(θ − X~t~)*dt* + σ*d*t
*d*α~t~ = − β

Approach  The linear approximation to the warning signals dynamics can be captured by the OU process, look for changing α SDE models will also provide some of the coarser approximations for the structured population dynamics. Formulations of these still to do.  Conditional probability Solution to the time dependent OU process, see Gardiner 4th ed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook tweaks: APIs in Ruby, Github hosting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notebook-tweaks-apis-in-ruby-github-hosting.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notebook-tweaks-apis-in-ruby-github-hosting.html</guid>
      <description>Crossref API and Faraday Looking at automating vita entries. The faraday gem looks like a nice general tool for API queries in Ruby (ht Martin Fenner)
 Example exploration  Mendeley API and omniauth  Omniauth appears to be a solution for Rails apps only? Not clear if it can be used in vanilla Ruby. Still stumped by this case; question on SO  Bisonomy and its API  RSS feeds too, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel R</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/parallel-r.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/parallel-r.html</guid>
      <description>Parallelized LR_bootstrap_all() and model_bootstrap_all() bootstrapping functions. Lets the bootstrapping of different models (or LRs between models) to be performed on different machines. Using the snowfall package in R for easy parallel computing. The parallel loop is done through the sfLapply() function. Had to get libraries and functions exported to all loops using sfLibrary() and sfExportAll(). R-sig-hpc mailing list was very helpful at getting this up and running at 4am.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primates</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/primates.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/primates.html</guid>
      <description>Primates project now has a Github repository. Updates are embedded from here.
 Experimenting with distributing code and data effectively. Pluses and minuses of three options:
   zipped file with R code and data. Requires setting working directory, harder to update. Subsequent uploads must include all the data, rather than incremental. Directly grab repository over github. Simple to update and access, stores only incremental changes. Requires knowledge of git R package: Nicely integrates data, code, and documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research.html</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapped against 2000 replicate simulations overnight on both the Anoles dataset and the Labrids dataset. Distributions that overlap zero represent replicates that choose the wrong model. The Anoles data below; the first column corresponds to the likelihood ratios shown in Butler &amp;amp; King (2004), comparing each model against BM.   The Labrid dataset:   Find matching figures for the case of parameters held fixed on more recent entry</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research.html</guid>
      <description>New Simulations  Now have code to run partitioned models on the Anoles dataset, compare partitioned models to the paintings chosen by Butler and King. Preliminary figures below. Models with _s are partitioned by my algorithm, others are the the original ones from earlier.   Also have examples with simulated data with a known number of partitions, to check the method. Tested with data produced at two peaks on the Labrid tree, the pattern seems similar to that of the Labrids &amp;ndash; comparisons involving any model with more than 2 peaks produce LR ratios that become very unlikely in either pairwise comparison.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research.html</guid>
      <description>Working on bootstrapping theta parameters bootstrapping multiple parameters doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem effective in the context of the boot package, despite claiming it can use a vector of stats. Certainly part of challenge is that different models have different numbers of parameters, so this isn&amp;rsquo;t a fixed size vector. Approaching manually for the moment, inhibits use of bootstrap confidence intervals function from the boot package. Some irregular behavior in bootstrapping parameters &amp;ndash; have to load package and then reload likelihood_bootstrap library source file or else bootstraps are NAs, needs further investigation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research.html</guid>
      <description>Sent Peter updated draft of Labrids manuscript Writing up logarithms manuscript finally&amp;hellip; Contacting Helen re. primates data Created Labrid Functional Morphology literature collection:  Research collected using Mendeley
 Started stochastic methods and model inference collection:  Research collected using Mendeley
Various To Do  Add Peter&amp;rsquo;s bootstrap references and books to stochastic methods and model inference library. Add Science of Science papers to Future of Science collection. Adding tags, abstracts, etc to Mendeley public Library Personal/extended task view (and opinion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solution to the strange behavior in ouch</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/solution-to-the-strange-behavior-in-ouch.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/solution-to-the-strange-behavior-in-ouch.html</guid>
      <description>Looks like my troubles actually stem from a bug in the code. I summarize the problem here, just as I posted in my query to R sig phylo. Essentially the program erroneously squares alpha at the moment, explaining the pattern I found yesterday. Giving it root alpha preemptively should be a good work around.

data(bimac) tree &amp;lt;- with(bimac,ouchtree(node,ancestor,time/max(time),species)) print(h2 &amp;lt;- hansen(log(bimac[&#39;size&#39;]),tree,bimac[&#39;OU.1&#39;],alpha=1,sigma=1))  The print command says alpha = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summary of Structured Population noise so far</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/summary-of-structured-population-noise-so-far.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/summary-of-structured-population-noise-so-far.html</guid>
      <description>Fig 1 Code b=5, ue= 0, ul = 0.001, up = 0, ua = 0.01, ae = .13*k, al = .01*k, ap = .15*k, cle = .2, cap = .1, cae = 5, V=volume
Fig 2 b=5, ue= 0, ul = 0.001, up = 0, ua = .001, ae = .1*k, al = .01*k, ap = .1*k, cle = 1, cap = .4, cae = 1, V=volume

System Size Expansion  Analytic calculation captures the noise propagation through the age structure correctly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ergodicity Question- Time averaging vs Ensemble averaging</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/the-ergodicity-question--time-averaging-vs-ensemble-averaging.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/the-ergodicity-question--time-averaging-vs-ensemble-averaging.html</guid>
      <description>11am &amp;ndash; 3pm
 Tried time averaging over the entire time window (set sample_size to 1 less than max time); in close agreement with the ensemble predictions (getting around 1355). Mystery doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to actually be a problem in the method, but just innate variability! Even over reasonable time-averages and ensemble averages there&amp;rsquo;s significant deviation from the expected variance! This variation around the warning signal/leading indicator is exactly what might frustrate the warning signal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals.html</guid>
      <description>bootstrapping models implemented improved handling of model classes &amp;ndash; included T, t0, N, and X0 in object def implemented plotting for model bootstrap difficulties with changePt model fit remain. fixed one source of trouble &amp;ndash; no longer passes zero-length data to OU.lik() when t_shift is outside the time interval.  Still giving errors on coercing lists into doubles for the saddle_node bifurcation simulated data set. &amp;ndash;fixed, was getting t_shift as a vector from time(X).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals with SDEs</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals-with-sdes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals-with-sdes.html</guid>
      <description>Summary  Have a functional likelihood calculation from the full individual-based simulation, see Friday. Accuracy needs more testing, and the computation is probably too slow for optimization routines. Have an implementation of the linear decrease in stability model with analytic conditional probability density. Needed a couple adjustments today. Need to add direct simulation to the warning signals package, currently retunrs only time-averaged/ensemble averaged stats. Can be approximated by setting the window equal to the timestep and ensembles equal to one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a few notes on various projects</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/a-few-notes-on-various-projects.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/a-few-notes-on-various-projects.html</guid>
      <description>warning-signals  Working on revisions for ews-review Grr, the challenges of open science &amp;ndash; can&amp;rsquo;t stick confidential reviews in ews-review repo where they belong, or track them on the issues tracker, without disclosing their contents. What are the terms of use for these things anyhow&amp;gt;
  phylogentics / pmc  Apparently pmc does have users &amp;ndash; at least one recognized that my Vignette is broken following the latest Gieger update.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio Submission</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ievobio-submission.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ievobio-submission.html</guid>
      <description>Quantifying Information in a Phylogenetic Tree: The Robustness of Phylogenetic Signal Since Felsenstein (1985)&amp;rsquo;s influential paper on phylogenetic contrasts, phylogenetically-based inferences of evolutionary patterns have gotten increasingly more complex (Hansen, 1997; Butler and King, 2004; Freckleton and Harvey, 2006; O&amp;rsquo;Meara et al., 2006; Pagel and Meade, 2006). More and more sophisticated models are applied to datasets of species mean traits on a phylogenetic tree in an attempt to answer such questions as reconstructing ancestral states, identify changes in rates of character evolution across time and across clades, identify the number and location of evolutionary optima or the strength of stabilizing selection.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>