<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Science on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/open-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Science on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 18:39:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/open-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a semantic notebook</title>
      <link>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 18:39:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</guid>
      <description>What would a semantic lab notebook look like? What would be possible with such a structure, ideally? What is already possible now? There&amp;rsquo;s a lot that can be done with an electronic notebook that adds value over a paper notebook: browsing by categories and tags, embedding links, time-stamping entries, searching the full text, and having automated trackbacks or pingbacks when a post is mentioned in another post or appears elsewhere on the web.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citation tools &amp; Future of Publishing</title>
      <link>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 23:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of rapid development in scientific tools based on a Wordpress platform recently, perhaps spurred in part by the recent Beyond-the-PDF and sessions in Science Online conferences. A new discussion group has emerged around these tools, as described by Martin Fenner.
I have been exploring better tools for citation management within my lab notebook. Recently I have been using the papercite plugin to add citations from my BibTeX files, which are generated from Mendeley, as I described earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Research  Wrote summary function using bootstrap confidence intervals for the bootstraps of the likelihoods directly. On interpreting the bootstraps of likelihoods directly:   The extent to which the distributions themselves are distinct provides an indication of the ability to distinguish between models on the given phylogenetic tree and the actual data. For instance, if the tree was a star tree and the data produced by either BM or OU1, then all distributions would fall on top of one another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Earlier today, Scott Collins, the president of the Ecological Society of America has announced that the society will now accept articles that have previously been posted on preprint servers. This comes on the heels of a growing discussion in our community. Ethan White has a good summary over on Jabberwocky Ecology.
Many voices have joined the discussion over the past month, and it is exciting and vindicating to see the Society engage and discuss these questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Wrapping up paper on waiting time to branching in adaptive dynamics. Cleaning up code from summer. Now in a local git repository in adaptiveDynamics/code Moved ensemble parallelization to higher level, so parallelization can be performed in R or C. Adding documentation  Current status  Calculates the waiting time to complete phase 1, phase 2, and phase 3 successfully from individual-based simulation.  Phase 1 ~ Completed when 2 branches exist over threshold Phase 2 ~ Completed when a third population has established over threshold exterior to a stable pair Phase 3 ~ Completed when two populations over threshold are separated in traitspace by more than finishline units</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Public code hosting  Project code now available through Github. Advantages to public hosting: Replication of adaptive dynamics simulations can be difficult, particularly in matching various nuisance parameters. While there is certainly much pedagogical value in individual researchers implementing their own simulations, verification and reproducibility of scientific results would be greatly facilitated by adapting an accepted open source code base and adding branches, etc. Researchers could much more immediately benefit from the work of their colleagues and spend more time implementing novel research and less reproducing it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Public code hosting  Project code now available through Github. Advantages to public hosting: Replication of adaptive dynamics simulations can be difficult, particularly in matching various nuisance parameters. While there is certainly much pedagogical value in individual researchers implementing their own simulations, verification and reproducibility of scientific results would be greatly facilitated by adapting an accepted open source code base and adding branches, etc. Researchers could much more immediately benefit from the work of their colleagues and spend more time implementing novel research and less reproducing it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Simulation Results (code)  Analytics (Analytics code)
Notebooks and files Looking at a better way to get figures into my online notebook. I often run simulations that generate figures which I look at, make some adjustments to the code based on the figure, and then delete or overwrite the figure without uploading it to my notebook, because it isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;finished&amp;rdquo; and uploading takes a lot of clicks, particularly when the code generates 36 figures in a run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/entry-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/entry-title/</guid>
      <description>Automated scripts for image uploads. Tag-based generation of a slideshow:


Running the script:
 ./flickr_slideshow *.png  Creates the html code that can be embedded into the notebook for a slideshow those images. Images only get the date-time tag as a unique id.


This one uses the mediawiki plugin. More formatting options could be incorporated of course. (Creates the thumbnail images down the right-hand side).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Seem to have successfully fixed the behavior when getting over parameterized models. See diffs against the git log for details.
 Will work on acceleration of code (avoiding refitting), meanwhile a little more trouble shooting and queuing some long runs.
 ace function fails on certain data sets for unknown reasons. Think rewriting this from scratch will be an important step.
  Mixture Models in Bayesian context  Josh sent me this paper regarding our discussion on model choice in Bayesian context last Friday.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>