<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Working Group on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/working-group/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Working Group on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/working-group/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Goals  Develop ideas for larger synthesis across systems Introduce scientists to the concept of workflow systems Introduce scientists to open data and methods sharing Gather requirements for collaboration tools that would allow scientists to use them and share data and workflows.  Participants  Ilkay Altintas, UC San Diego, Carl Boettiger, UC Davis, Erica Christensen, Utah State, Elsa Cleland, UCSD, Scott Collins, U New Mexico, Sam Fey, Dartmouth, Corinna Gries, U Wisconsin, Lauren Hallett, Berkeley, Stan Harpole, Iowa State, Dave Harris, UC Davis, Matt Jones, UC Santa Barbara, Sydney Jones, U New Mexico, Julie Ripplinger, Arizona State University, Andrew Rypel, WDNR, David Seekell, UVa, Elizabeth Siddon, U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>(Day 2 work) Hack-a-thon; no notebook entry but all progress appears in group Github repo: github.com/NCEAS/commdyn/. 78 Commits in 2 days, nice work team.
Discussion of challenges and opportunities in open data and ecological workflows
Synthesis and Reporting back
Group 1.5 Plan Product 1: Paper: Visualizing global change in long term community ecology studies: the strawmen?
 Lead: Sydney Jones  Long-term ecological research (LTER) sites have been collecting and publishing raw community ecology data for over 30 years from across the US and across a wide array of taxa.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>