<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Seminar on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/seminar/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Seminar on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 15:48:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/seminar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Jordan&#39;s bigdata talk in Math/Stats series</title>
      <link>/2012/04/05/jordans-bigdata-talk-in-mathstats-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 15:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/05/jordans-bigdata-talk-in-mathstats-series/</guid>
      <description>Really excellent talk by Professor Michael Jordan from the Berkeley Statistics department visiting us at Davis yesterday. Haven&amp;rsquo;t seen a talk cover technical content with remarkable clarity for the algorithms and insights involved, while also covering such a breadth of material. My notes didn&amp;rsquo;t really keep up, but transcribing some of my scribbling into electronic form will have to wait until I have more time. (Their pubs are probably a better reference anyway.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Pfaff seminar, meeting</title>
      <link>/2012/03/09/alex-pfaff--meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2012 10:34:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/09/alex-pfaff--meeting/</guid>
      <description>Notes from Alex Pfaff talk at UTK (during my visit for pdg-control meeting).
 average impact vs differential impact &amp;ndash; must compare against what would have happened to the area if unprotected (at current time/short-timescale, or in future?)
 Proximity is not a good proxy of similarity (i.e. bc we protect steep slopes but farm the flat land nearby)
 Instead use simple metrics available in GIS layers - distance from nearest road, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visuals for Communicating Uncertainty </title>
      <link>/2012/02/24/visuals-for-communicating-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2012 20:20:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/24/visuals-for-communicating-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>Visiting the question of communicating uncertainty in Marissa&amp;rsquo;s lab meeting, focusing on this excellent Science article (Spiegelhalter et. al. 2011). Noam and Jamie are leading the discussion, and suggested we pick a few favorite examples. None on my list really address the challenge of communicating uncertainty directly, though the first one probably comes closest. I think they do highlight some of the potential and the challenges of good data visualization though, which is certainly one of the essential building blocks to visual communication of uncertainty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Research, seminar (managing for resilience), talk (future of libraries), etc...</title>
      <link>/2012/02/21/tues-research--managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 19:20:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/21/tues-research--managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</guid>
      <description>research Stuff warningsignals  Exceeded wall time on NERSC, readjusting and running this again.  treebase  Working on treebase manuscript. Treebase Rewrote handling of server errors, added pauses to reduce load, etc.  PMC  A user pointed out my support for &amp;ldquo;white&amp;rdquo; model was incomplete. Fix is now on github (install instructions for development version are also now on github), will push to CRAN soon.
 Another user points out that pmc support for additional functions would be nice, such as rbrownie, fit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - various logistics, then checking likelihood calculation</title>
      <link>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2011 20:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci  rOpenSci wins runner up prize in PLoS + Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s Binary Battle! Write replies to interview questions with Mendeley. roxygenizing documentation for RMendeley &amp;ndash; about half done  pdg-control  Call with Jake scheduled for tomorrow Emails with Michael. I&amp;rsquo;ll implement delay intervals, he&amp;rsquo;ll add costs to adjustment. Need to fix/finish delay interval optimization calculation (exponent of matrix &amp;amp; beta)  Warning Signals Meeting with Alan
 Regime shifts Emphasize the RO curve in uncertainty analysis See (Dulvy et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steve Pacala - Storer lecture</title>
      <link>/2011/11/17/steve-pacala-storer-lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 23:16:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/17/steve-pacala-storer-lecture/</guid>
      <description>Excellent visit from a former advisor, Steve Pacala, at Davis for a Storer lecture.
Seminar  atmospheric CO2 is roughly half CO2 production, rest is being mitigated by the natural carbon sink
 Carbon sink is half ocean, half terrestrial
  A grim future:
 450ppm not feasible
 500ppm best case
 550ppm is likely even if we are largely successful
  Even worse if the terrestrial sink collapses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Loo Botsford, CPB seminar</title>
      <link>/2011/10/11/lou-botsford-cpb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2011 17:04:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/11/lou-botsford-cpb/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Effects of Fishing on the Sensitivity of Fisheries to Climate Variability&amp;rdquo; Truncation of age structure.
juvenation (younger population), maternal effects (first-year breeders are poor), genetic selection, ability to track environment (vs smoothing &amp;ndash; averaging over longer times).
Outline:
Empirical evidence for increased variability, model explanations  Story begins with Hsieh, et al 2006. Long time series, increasing fluctuations. (Hsieh et. al. 2006)
 Anderson et al no age structure model (Anderson et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matt Helmus visit</title>
      <link>/2011/10/07/matt-helmus-visit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2011 14:36:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/07/matt-helmus-visit/</guid>
      <description>Notes from presentation 1. Species-area curve:  Species sorting by environment. species clustering due to limited dispersal Random displacement (faster saturation) In-situ speciation looks like clustering Compare to colonization Phylogenetic species variability metric: compare phylogenetic covariance matrix to a star-phylogeny, not expected to increase with area.  $$ \frac{n \textrm{tr}C - \sum C }{n(n-1)}$$
2. Simulations:  species sort along an environmental gradient. BM trait determining position. : closely related species clustered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/10/04/tuesday-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2011 22:29:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/04/tuesday-9/</guid>
      <description>Hastings seminar: Forest Pest Outbreaks Schedule
Prof Dave Rizzo  Reviews major pest outbreaks (Major Forest Insect &amp;amp; Disease Conditions in the United States 2009 Update)  Mentions weekend&amp;rsquo;s NY Times piece, (and see author&amp;rsquo;s commentary), reviews major pest outrbreak trends.   David Kling Allee effects &amp;amp; Management (Gypsy moth). * Review review (Taylor &amp;amp; Hastings, 2005). * Simulation exploration: pmid: 19831081, * Also discuss (Tobin et. al. 2011).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matt Potts: Conserving Diversity in Tropical Landscapes</title>
      <link>/2011/05/27/matt-potts-conserving-diversity-in-tropical-landscapes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 21:27:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/27/matt-potts-conserving-diversity-in-tropical-landscapes/</guid>
      <description>My notes from Matt&amp;rsquo;s seminar: Theory and field work addressing getting beyond binary decision making. Malaysia. Tropical forest becoming oil palm, rice, rubber, tea.
Reserve Selection vs Landscape Reserve Design Optimality of Specialized vs Uniform Forest Management Uniform (sustainable forest management) vs very protected areas, ignore what&amp;rsquo;s done outside. More intensive disturbance.
An important ecological nonlinearity: What&amp;rsquo;s the most ubiquitous spatial pattern? Aggregated, random, uniform? (50 hectares is .5 km by km, or 120 English acres, tag every tree taller than 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steve Ellner&#39;s seminar</title>
      <link>/2011/04/07/steve-ellners/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 17:09:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/07/steve-ellners/</guid>
      <description>What started as three men and a chemostat&amp;hellip;
This is Part III of the talk &amp;ndash; some of you were in elementary school for the first two, so here&amp;rsquo;s a reminder:
Consumer-resource interactions are prone to cycle: due to delayed negative feedbacks. (note prey peaks are 1&amp;frasl;4-cycle shifted). Simulations, Larch Budmoth and parasitoids, (Kendall et. al. 1998)
Chaos should be common But it isn&amp;rsquo;t. we observe Stable : cycles : chaos 2 : 1 : $ \epsilon $ Zimmer 1999 (Zimmer, 1999)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brian O&#39;Meara discusses new algorithms approaches on Phylo</title>
      <link>/2011/03/30/brian-omeara-discusses-new-abc-approaches-on-phylo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2011 20:52:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/30/brian-omeara-discusses-new-abc-approaches-on-phylo/</guid>
      <description>Brian gave an excellent overview of Approximate Bayesian Computing (ABC) and described the TreEvo software he is developing with post-doc Barb Banbury. My notes from the seminar, with my own comments italics and a few added references
Intro / Motivation  Rates of model innovation is rather slow
 Can be impossible to specify in closed form (can&amp;rsquo;t specify median of binomial in closed form)
 Perhaps it would be faster if we didn&amp;rsquo;t have to wait for someone to come up with all the likelihood functions</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter&#39;s talk </title>
      <link>/2011/03/14/peters-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 22:29:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/14/peters-talk/</guid>
      <description>Peter spoke in Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s lab meeting about a spatially explicit Moran model, for which he derives Fisher&amp;rsquo;s wave equation and an ancestry process. Here&amp;rsquo;s what he says,
 the general plan is to describe a simple spatial model of adaptation (or, could be of invasion&amp;hellip;); and use it to derive (Fisher&amp;rsquo;s) traveling wave; the corrections that arise if you don&amp;rsquo;t assume the population is infinitely large; and describe how to follow lineages back through the expanding wave.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylo: Luke Harmon</title>
      <link>/2011/02/25/phylo-luke-harmon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2011 14:36:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/25/phylo-luke-harmon/</guid>
      <description>My notes on Luke Harmon&amp;rsquo;s excellent talk on Phyloseminar this morning. See the recording of Luke&amp;rsquo;s actual talk to know what he said, below are my thoughts and notes to myself having watched the talk.
Luke summarizes his goal rather nicely as:
 Analyzing the data that people actually have to answer the questions they actually want to know
 For him, this focuses on incomplete trees and non-Brownian models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Data: Plans for a UC Davis workshop</title>
      <link>/2011/02/01/the-future-of-data-preparing-researchers-to-face-new-funding-and-publishing-policies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 09:40:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/01/the-future-of-data-preparing-researchers-to-face-new-funding-and-publishing-policies/</guid>
      <description>I have been working with several of the faculty of UC Davis to prepare a workshop for our department to (1) help make our researchers aware of the new requirements for NSF proposals and journal submissions with regard to data archiving, (2) To explore what new opportunities this creates and what tools exist that will help our researchers take maximum advantage of it, and (3) to engage our research community in the discussion of future standards for sharing, standardizing, rewarding and funding the archiving of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McElreath: A Bayesian approach to hierarchical modeling, using R to build our own estimator from scratch</title>
      <link>/2011/01/26/mcelreath-a-bayesian-approach-to-hierarchical-modeling-using-r-to-build-our-own-estimator-from-scratch/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2011 17:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/26/mcelreath-a-bayesian-approach-to-hierarchical-modeling-using-r-to-build-our-own-estimator-from-scratch/</guid>
      <description>CPB workshop continues, introduction to Bayesian inference.
McElreath discusses (slides):
 Bayes Theorem  $$ P(\theta | D) = \frac{Pr(D|\theta) Pr(\theta )}{Pr(D)} $$
 Philosophy of Priors, Uninformative Priors
 Confidence intervals / credible intervals for free
 Computing the posterior: Directly or by MCMC
  Nice visual example of updating prior as we add data:
[gist id=&amp;ldquo;797795&amp;rdquo;]
 King Markov and the chain islands.
 Evaluating: Burn in , autocorrelation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McElreath Hierarchical Models</title>
      <link>/2011/01/24/mcelreath-hierarchical-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2011 16:03:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/24/mcelreath-hierarchical-models/</guid>
      <description>CPB workshop on hierarchal modeling starts off today with Richard McElreath&amp;rsquo;s introduction.[ref]These are my own notes as taken during the seminar and may not accurately reflect everything. I merely confirm with the speaker that my notes are publicly visible. My own commentary/thoughts indicated in square brackets. As these notes are taken directly during seminar (on my droid phone &amp;ndash; saves me transcribing, later) , please forgive typos and shorthand.[/ref] &amp;ldquo;This is a workshop, not a job talk, meaning I&amp;rsquo;m going to give away the tricks and you have to learn something.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Felsenstein (web) seminar</title>
      <link>/2011/01/24/felsenstein-web/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2011 11:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/24/felsenstein-web/</guid>
      <description>Joe Felsenstein on phyloseminar (watch here). This morning. [ref]These are my own notes as taken during the seminar and may not accurately reflect everything. I merely confirm with the speaker that my notes are publicly visible. My own commentary/thoughts indicated in square brackets.[/ref] Discusses bridging population genetics &amp;amp; comparative methods: where does covariation in traits across a phylogeny come from?
Morphometrics Using morphometrics (digitized landmarks [though now we can do spherical harmonics, CT scans, etc]) to evolve on a phylogeny under BM rather than use that data to infer phylogeny.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robert Hijmans on Models to predict sp response to climate change</title>
      <link>/2011/01/19/robert-hijmans-on-models-to-predict-sp-response-to-climate-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2011 12:53:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/19/robert-hijmans-on-models-to-predict-sp-response-to-climate-change/</guid>
      <description>Notes from seminar.[ref]These are my own notes as taken during the seminar and may not accurately reflect everything. I merely confirm with the speaker that my notes are publicly visible. My own commentary/thoughts indicated in square brackets. [/ref] Robert speaks to an utterly packed room. Predicting future range of species: 4 topics. 1 cross-validation, 2 niches, 3 unit (sp?), 4 mechanism. Presence-absence predictions from machine learning, maxent.
Opening: AUC for measure of fit- lousy stat!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPB : David Collar</title>
      <link>/2010/12/01/cpb--david-collar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2010 00:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/01/cpb--david-collar/</guid>
      <description>Identifying ecological constraint on morph and function using phylogenies. 2007 CPB grad, losos post doc, now postdoc w Rita.
Indep origin of &amp;lsquo;bass&amp;rsquo; cranial morph. Also unique patterns- stonefish. Phylo comparative methods to address why and how. Three types of factors on morphology: ecological, time!, intrinsic (genetic, behavior) constraints. Outline:
I. determinants of morph diversification.
II. Complex traits.
I. Diversification rate vary by habitat? (Dragon lizards- diverse morph, diverse habitat). Reconstruct history of habitat use (4 types), (assign discrete traits) then stoch character maps to reconstruct (paint) tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues seminar</title>
      <link>/2010/11/16/tues/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2010 17:47:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/16/tues/</guid>
      <description>Sarah Dalrymple seminar. Rick Karban&amp;rsquo;s excellent intro: &amp;ldquo;unlike the rest of these seminars, Sarah will tell us something new.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Sarah&amp;rsquo;s really out there.&amp;ldquo; Also mentions TAC and art teaching.
Ants, Jeff pine &amp;amp; fire Fire suppression dramatic impacts. Prescribed under story burns work! ie Angora fire in Tahoe, 2007. Discover rings of unburned soil around base of tree, reducing damage&amp;hellip; undescribed!
More common in recently burned ( 30 yrs. What makes the rings?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Leo Polansky Seminar (all notes cover published results only)
 Wavelet analysis does a nice trick of seeing frequency-domain spectra change over time, rather than being entirely in frequency space or entirely in time space.
 higher rank elephants decrease their movement more in dry, resource-poor season than low rank. Guarding the good territory? I wonder if this is a stochastic effect - asset protection, where you take more risk when you have low assets than when you have higher assets, a feature that would dissappear in a deterministic environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Reviewing arg, reviewing. so much time.
Seminar Kate Richerson gave a fanstastic presentation to mega group yesterday showing her integration of behavior and dispersal in krill dynamics. She derives the krill&amp;rsquo;s behavioral movement patterns through a stochastic dynamic programming solution rather than just dictate it to the dispersal model directly.
Reading .
 Provicative stuff in PNAS Perretti et. al. (2013). It would be nice to see the comparison against the generating model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infering Partially Observable Markov Processes with Iterative Particle Filtering</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/infering-partially-observable-markov-processes-with-iterative-particle-filtering/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/infering-partially-observable-markov-processes-with-iterative-particle-filtering/</guid>
      <description>Excellent talk by Ed Ionides at UC Davis today (led me to miss Weds session of Data to Knowledge).
Ed Ionides six problems of Bjonstead and Grenfell: an appeal for arbitrary nonlinear partially observed vector valued stochastic models.
POMP doesn&amp;rsquo;t mix well in the winbugs.
simulation-based algorithm (plug-and-play)
Think of a process being defined by:
 rprocess() dprocess() rmeasure() dmeasure()  In general we need some subset of these processes:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>