<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Knitcitations on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/knitcitations.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Knitcitations on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/knitcitations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/07/18/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/07/18/notes/</guid>
      <description>CRAN trivia When should you bump version for a (rejected) resubmission?  Once accepted, any change other than to the metadata (essentially the DESCRIPTION file) needs an increased version. For submissions, we prefer (but do not insist on) a new number of each attempt.
 &amp;ndash;Prof Brian Ripley
Using non-CRAN repositories in SUGGESTS or ENAHANCES More dubious tricks, from Yihui:
 FYI, here is how R core checks dependencies: https://github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/06/12/knitcitations-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/06/12/knitcitations-updates/</guid>
      <description>Used some down-time while traveling to hammer out a long overdue update to my knitcitations package.
My first task inovled a backwards-compatible update fixing a few minor issues (see NEWS) and providing pandoc style inline citations v0.6-2, on CRAN.
I followed this with a ground-up rewrite, as I summarize in NEWS:
v1.0-1 This version is a ground-up rewrite of knitcitations, providing a more powerful interface while also streamlining the back end, mostly by relying more on external libraries for knitty gritty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a few notes on various projects</title>
      <link>/2013/04/16/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/16/notes/</guid>
      <description>warning-signals  Working on revisions for ews-review Grr, the challenges of open science &amp;ndash; can&amp;rsquo;t stick confidential reviews in ews-review repo where they belong, or track them on the issues tracker, without disclosing their contents. What are the terms of use for these things anyhow&amp;gt;
  phylogentics / pmc  Apparently pmc does have users &amp;ndash; at least one recognized that my Vignette is broken following the latest Gieger update.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/22/semantic-citations-for-the-notebook-and-knitr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/22/semantic-citations-for-the-notebook-and-knitr/</guid>
      <description>I have on ocassion been exploring the use of semantic markup in the notebook. In this post I illustrate how I am handling semantic citations. One of the more intriguing ideas is the ability to add semantic meaning to citations through the CITO ontology of Shotton (2010). Citation counts form a central part of academic discourse, but contain very little information regarding the reason for the citation. Most notably, &amp;lsquo;negative&amp;rsquo; citations refuting a claim carry just the same weight as those confirming or relying upon a claim.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>knitcitations</title>
      <link>/2012/05/30/knitcitations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/05/30/knitcitations/</guid>
      <description>EDIT: Note that this package has evolved quite a bit from this initial post. While the basic interface is the same, support for additional features and some choices in formatting differ from what is presented here. Please see the README for the latest introduction to the package. Readers may also be interested in the more recent post discussing the introduction of several new features including semantic tools in the knitcitations package</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>