<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wrightscape on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/wrightscape.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wrightscape on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 10:39:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/wrightscape/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Catching up</title>
      <link>/2012/04/19/catching-up.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 10:39:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/19/catching-up.html</guid>
      <description>Catching up on notebook entries for last week and the beginning of this week in one go here. In the process of wrapping up a variety of older projects, so this is kinda all over the place.
rfishbase  Create function table, finalize functions Add support for references. Done, see getRefs. (And isn&amp;rsquo;t it awesome that you can link to a specific linenumber (i.e. line 280) in github by adding #L280 to the end of the url?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday / Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 23:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday.html</guid>
      <description>rfishbase updated to Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback writing intro section on Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy. wrightscape update project repository. Scripts mostly in demos, results in notebook. Notebook makes is easy to get the most recent writeup on the topic, from where I can start to track back the history, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide a good at-a-glance view of the analyses I&amp;rsquo;ve run side-by-side. Moving the R script demos/ into markdown knitted files in inst/examples/ and rerunning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - wrightscape runs and various other things</title>
      <link>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 18:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11.html</guid>
      <description>pdg-control  plots for changing costs Report out to Training Problem II group.  ggplot note defining functions that return a ggplot object can be tricky. If you compute some objects in the plot function (stats etc), those stats are not stored by the object (due to lazy evaluation, usually a very nice time-saving feature), so the plot cannot be produced unless the function returns those things to the global environment (or from wherever the plot will be printed/evaluated).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday - wrightscape meetings, PDG meeting</title>
      <link>/2011/12/05/monday-wrightscape-meetings-pdg-meeting.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 18:45:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/05/monday-wrightscape-meetings-pdg-meeting.html</guid>
      <description>Wrightscape &amp;ndash; added a user utility to to specify custom model types, such that some subset of the total number of regimes can share certain parameters.
Peter Meeting  Derivation &amp;ndash; provide clear examples of the differences and by how much it matters. Expected result from the biology: the jaw lever traits should show greater changes than the other traits after a release of constraint. Based on previous studies, expect most of the action to be around the intramandibular joint innovation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>