<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Evolution on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/categories/evolution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Evolution on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/evolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/26/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/26/notes/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML Character metadata EML provides a nice illustration of the kind of metadata we would want to typically accompany character trait data; at minimum, at the attribute level.
Some of this is already there &amp;ndash; we know if states are continuous or discrete, what possible states they can take on, and can add labels to state nodes to define what the symbols mean (however, perhaps an additional meta annotation node would be preferred).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/17/rnexml-metadata-queries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/17/rnexml-metadata-queries/</guid>
      <description>(From issue #20)
Basic metadata queries a question of how the user queries that metadata. Currently we have a metadata function that simply extracts all the metadata at the specified level (nexml, otus, trees, tree, etc) and returns a named character string in which the name corresponds to the rel or property and the value corresponds to the content or href, e.g.:
birds &amp;lt;- read.nexml(&amp;quot;birdOrders.xml&amp;quot;) meta &amp;lt;- get_metadata(birds)  prints the named string with the top-level (default-level) metadata elements as so:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/10/17/rnexml-semantic-considerations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/17/rnexml-semantic-considerations/</guid>
      <description>Some very good feedback from Hilmar as I tackle some of the semantic capabilities of NeXML in RNeXML. As the complete discussion is already archived in the Github issues tracking, (see in particular #26 and #24) I only paraphrase here.
One of the central advantages we can offer in programmatic generation of NeXML in the R environment is the ability to validate names and enhance the metadata included in the resulting nexml file using programmatic queries to taxonomic name resolution services such as ITIS, EOL, NCBI, as provided in the taxize package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/10/16/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/16/notes/</guid>
      <description>RNeXML  Example methods for metadata: https://github.com/ropensci/RNeXML/issues/20#issuecomment-26457772 Closes #19 https://github.com/ropensci/RNeXML/issues/19#issuecomment-26459110 Discussion of best identifiers for OTUs #24. Now waiting on Scott for choice of implementation  Misc R puzzle In R&amp;rsquo;s S4 methods, I can define methods with different signatures, i.e. different object classes for the same function call. But can I alter the names and number of arguments for a method?
As usual, see Github for details on commits and issues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it time to retire Pagel&#39;s lambda?</title>
      <link>/2013/10/11/is-it-time-to-retire-pagels-lambda/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/11/is-it-time-to-retire-pagels-lambda/</guid>
      <description>Pagel&amp;rsquo;s $\lambda$ (lambda), introduced in Pagel 1999 as a potential measure of &amp;ldquo;phylogenetic signal,&amp;rdquo; the extent to which correlations in traits reflect their shared evolutionary history (as approximated by Brownian motion).
Numerous critiques and ready alternatives have not appeared to decrease it&amp;rsquo;s popularity. There are many issues with the statistic, some of which I attempt to summarise below.
The $\lambda$ statistic is defined by the Brownian motion model together with a transformation of the branch lengths: multiply all internal branches by $\lambda$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extending ape::phylo class to NeXML:</title>
      <link>/2013/10/07/nexml-phylo-class-extension/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/07/nexml-phylo-class-extension/</guid>
      <description>While working on the RNeXML package, I have recently I have been puzzling over extending S3 objects to share some of the nice properties of S4 objects and methods while continuing to function with the potentially huge library of functions written to work with them. SO:
To illustrate this issue, consider the S3 class phylo provided by the ape package and used by most of the 30+ packages that reverse depend or reverse import ape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/23/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/23/notes/</guid>
      <description>nonparametric bayes Reading  Arnqvist, G. 2013 Editorial rejects? Novelty, schnovelty! Trends in ecology &amp;amp; evolution 28, 448-9. (doi:10.1016/j.tree.2013.05.007) Accounting for Complementarity to Maximize Monitoring Power for Species Management. 27, 988-999. (doi:10.1111/cobi.12092) Nes, E. H. Van, Hirota, M., Holmgren, M. &amp;amp; Scheffer, M. 2013 Tipping points in tropical tree cover: linking theory to data. (doi:10.1111/gcb.12398) Millar, R. B. 2002 Reference priors for Bayesian fisheries models. , 1492-1502. (doi:10.1139/F02-108) Mcallister, M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/09/lost-branches/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/09/lost-branches/</guid>
      <description>Just read Lost Branches on the Tree of Life in PLoS Biology and couldn&amp;rsquo;t agree more! I too am frequently frustrated by the lack of deposition or replies to email requests for data. The 16% reply rate seems consistent with other such studies. I agree with the general message that what is most needed is a cultural shift towards these expectations. I loved this paper overall but nonetheless cannot resist a few nitpicks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/07/rnexml-milestone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/07/rnexml-milestone/</guid>
      <description>We have also recently reached the first milestone in RNeXML. We can now read NeXML files into R and convert to the popular phylo format from the ape package, as well as writing the ape::phylo trees out into valid NeXML. We can also add basic metadata such as author, license, title and description to the file.
Development notes At the heart of this package is an internal S4 representation of the schema.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/08/29/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/29/notes/</guid>
      <description>Digging through some old stuff in the course of correspondance on related issues, I came across a few outstanding puzzles I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to wrap up one day:
 Drift effecs &amp;ndash; some difficulties Waiting Time  and some actual results that could deserve some renewed attention too.
 Phase 1 Routes to branching  Also raises an interesting new question that could be addressed in this context: can we formulate a similar approach to the stochastic escape from an adaptive peak?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/08/28/rnexml-coding/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/28/rnexml-coding/</guid>
      <description>test_ape.R unit tests now passing. Should still revise the coercion methods in nexml_write.R to something more clever. We aren&amp;rsquo;t coercing a tree to a nexml, we are building a nexml from a tree. Likewise handling the otu assignments of species names should be done directly 11:20 am 2013/08/28 start cleaning up old read/write methods obsoleted by toNeXML/fromNeXML methods 10:59 am 2013/08/28 inherited classes now replace all the original classes 10:54 am 2013/08/28 All inheritance-based classes appearing in inst/examples/trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/07/22/xml-parsing-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/22/xml-parsing-strategies/</guid>
      <description>Writing out some advice for our GSOC student on XML parsing. (Now filed as RNeXML/#11
Here is some quick background on different ways we might go about extracting NeXML into an R object we want to work with. We can use S4 classes, R&amp;rsquo;s native data.frame and list types, or extract specific terms of interest with xpath. I illustrate each of these below using the example &amp;ldquo;trees.xml&amp;rdquo; in your repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/04/23/we-need-more-object-oriented-design-in-comparative-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/23/we-need-more-object-oriented-design-in-comparative-methods/</guid>
      <description>The bad news is that the latest Geiger version (which is much improved in all respects) breaks my little pmc package, owing to changes in how fitContinuous output is structured. The good news is that the new geiger is much better than the old one, and that the pmc package is pretty trivial. So this should not be read as a complaint, but I think as a scientific developer community as a whole we could learn a few simple lessons here, which can help our code more reproducible and extensible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a few notes on various projects</title>
      <link>/2013/04/16/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/16/notes/</guid>
      <description>warning-signals  Working on revisions for ews-review Grr, the challenges of open science &amp;ndash; can&amp;rsquo;t stick confidential reviews in ews-review repo where they belong, or track them on the issues tracker, without disclosing their contents. What are the terms of use for these things anyhow&amp;gt;
  phylogentics / pmc  Apparently pmc does have users &amp;ndash; at least one recognized that my Vignette is broken following the latest Gieger update.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/14/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/14/notes/</guid>
      <description>Research  consolidate and revise EWS text(?) replies to Luke and Brian on model choice  Notebook meta  fix google-analytics plugin (still needs to get toggle working?) tests of notebook-parsing.Rmd. New errors on ; somehow in straight XML parsing, ignoring for the moment. Opened a few new issues around improving site semantics. (#59, #60)  ropensci  Resubmit rfishbase &amp;ndash; silently load to local, not global namespace. Updated data cache (and ASCII-ify and compress).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/10/24/evolutionary-covariance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/24/evolutionary-covariance/</guid>
      <description>Thinking through disparity measures while writing my thoughts in R&amp;hellip;
Load some sample data
library(geiger) data(geospiza) dat &amp;lt;- treedata(geospiza$geospiza.tree, geospiza$geospiza.data$wingL)  To find the disparity relative to a particular model, we must compute the variance-covariance matrix for that model
X &amp;lt;- dat$data V_bm &amp;lt;- vcv(dat$phy) mean_X &amp;lt;- geiger:::phylogMean(V_bm, X) bm_disparity &amp;lt;- t(X-mean_X) %*% V_bm %*% (X-mean_X)  I believe this needs to be scaled by the Brownian rate parameter of the trait, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution and iEvobio conference notes</title>
      <link>/2012/07/09/evolution-conf-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/09/evolution-conf-summary/</guid>
      <description>Saturday  Jeremy Brown Graham Slater (Education Data Symposium) Cecile Ane Joe Felsenstein Lars Schmitz Carl Boettiger Liam Revell Brian O&amp;rsquo;Meara (Leithan McGonigle)  Sunday  Marie-Josee Fortin Emma Goldberg 10:45 rm 209 Networks Symposium Jeremy Fox 1.30p Rm 201 (Adaptation B) Schluter 2:15p Canada 2-3 Rosie Redfield public lecture  Monday  9:00 Michael Landis, 203 9:30 Dick Gumolkiowicz 214 10:30 Dean Adams 11 (Cavender-Bares, 214) (Bolnick, 213) 11:30 Mark McPeek 214  Tuesday  Luke Harmon 9am rm 214 Luke Mahler 9am rm 210 Rafael Maia 9:15a rm 210 Sam Price 11:15a rm 210 Liam Revell 11:30 Canada 2-3 Dan Rabosky 2:30pm Canada 2-3 Tanja Stadler 3pm Canada 2-3 Chris Martin 3pm rm 213  Also: ievobio Day 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2012 Conference, Day 1</title>
      <link>/2012/07/08/evolution-day1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/08/evolution-day1/</guid>
      <description>Fantastic first day at Evolution. Spent the morning in the SSB Sympossium organized by Jeremy Brown, &amp;ldquo;Predictive approaches for assessing the fit of evolutionary models&amp;rdquo;. Really covered both methods assessing model fit (posterior predictive simulations) and approximate likelihood approaches, which are also simulation-based. Then the afternoon in the second SSB Symposium on emerging methods for comparative phylogenetics, organized by Liam Revell and Cecile Ane, which included my talk. Lots of great talks, but Cecile&amp;rsquo;s was perhaps the most striking results I saw presented all day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>wrightscape / release of constraint</title>
      <link>/2012/07/03/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/03/notes/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a table of all the comparisons, indicating which is the preferred model in each pairwise comparison. (In my outline, Figure 4 shows the bm3 v a3 for KT and open lever ratio, and Fig 3 shows the actual parameter values for those models). This table is all for the case that allows shifts at both pharyngeal and the intramandibular transitions. I have graphs of the actual parameter values as well (which we need to see if the constraint has increased or decreased at the transition, and by how much), but gets complex quickly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <link>/2012/05/10/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/05/10/notes/</guid>
      <description>Partially Observable Stochastic Processes (cont.)  Reading a bit more about pomp. Looks like SCM and PMCMC offer nicely Bayesian inference tools using the same framework (rprocess and dmeasure), making a nice platform for implementing multiple methods. Almost feels like having the likelihood equation in hand again. A bit more skeptical about nonlinear forecasting and probe matching, as they feel even more heuristic or arbitrary. I suppose that&amp;rsquo;s just the price of having only rmeasure instead of dmeasure available though.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project tracking (Evolution)</title>
      <link>/2012/04/27/evolution-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/27/evolution-notes/</guid>
      <description>Evolution I&amp;rsquo;m also still wrapping up a variety of projects on the Evolution front.
treebase  Dynamic manuscript. Reorganize, simplify? add, document, employ the additional functions to avoid sapply commands. Prune examples? iEvoBio challenge entry?  Wrightscape  Start synthesizing documents Evidence for release in open lever ratio and kt Illustrating the different models Consider updated data format outputs and graphical processing functions for the model choice steps  fishbase  submitted!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/03/19/monday-treebase-manuscript-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2012 20:21:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/19/monday-treebase-manuscript-writing/</guid>
      <description>Catching up on unfinished work: today has been spent mostly working over my little treebase applications note. I&amp;rsquo;m still deciding what/how to present in terms of the meta-analysis section &amp;ndash; looking at the classic trends on diversification rate statistics: $\gamma$ statistic (Pybus &amp;amp; Harvey, 2000) and diversification rate, and dependence on number of taxa. Not sure how best to handle issues of data choice, quality, or to just average over the available data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Research, seminar (managing for resilience), talk (future of libraries), etc...</title>
      <link>/2012/02/21/tues-research-seminar-managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 19:20:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/21/tues-research-seminar-managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</guid>
      <description>research Stuff warningsignals  Exceeded wall time on NERSC, readjusting and running this again.  treebase  Working on treebase manuscript. Treebase Rewrote handling of server errors, added pauses to reduce load, etc.  PMC  A user pointed out my support for &amp;ldquo;white&amp;rdquo; model was incomplete. Fix is now on github (install instructions for development version are also now on github), will push to CRAN soon.
 Another user points out that pmc support for additional functions would be nice, such as rbrownie, fit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday </title>
      <link>/2012/02/12/sunday-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 22:14:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/12/sunday-6/</guid>
      <description>phylogenetics  Exploring display of phylogeny. Unlabled, painted fan?   tweaking release-of-constraint plot - vary alpha, less strong? release at T/2? Animated version?  Creating paintings of phylogenies Creating from a specified set of taxa is a somewhat common task for me. Wrightscape supports doing this for both ouch and ape trees.
 ape-based phylogenies ouch-based phylogenies use some legacy maticce functions  intra_ancestor &amp;lt;- mrcaOUCH(c(&amp;quot;Chlorurus_sordidus&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Hipposcarus_longiceps&amp;quot;), labrid$tree) intramandibular &amp;lt;- paintBranches(intra_ancestor, labrid$tree, c(&amp;quot;other&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;intramandibular&amp;quot;)) pharyngeal_ancestor&amp;lt;-mrcaOUCH(c(&amp;quot;Bolbometopon_muricatum&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Sparisoma_radians&amp;quot;), labrid$tree) pharyngeal &amp;lt;- paintBranches(pharyngeal_ancestor, labrid$tree, c(&amp;quot;other&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;pharyngeal&amp;quot;)) two_shifts &amp;lt;- paintBranches(c(pharyngeal_ancestor, intra_ancestor), labrid$tree, c(&amp;quot;wrasses&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;pharyngeal&amp;quot;, intramandibular&amp;quot;) )  The ouch-trees can be converted back to ape trees in a way that can plot them, but for some reason break the fan-plot mode but not the standard phylogram plot mode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is your phylogeny informative?</title>
      <link>/2012/01/19/is-your-phylogeny-informative/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 14:10:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/19/is-your-phylogeny-informative/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday my paper (Boettiger et. al. 2012) appeared in early view in Evolution (author&amp;rsquo;s preprint),As the open access copy doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear on pubmed for a while, you can access my author&amp;rsquo;s copy here. so I&amp;rsquo;d like to take this chance to share the back-story and highlight my own view on some of our findings, and the associated package on CRAN.Just submitted, meanwhile, the code is always on github.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t set out to write this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>wrightscape examples</title>
      <link>/2012/01/04/wrightscape-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 12:48:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/04/wrightscape-examples/</guid>
      <description>[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;phylogenetics&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2012-01-03 7:00:37&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2012-01-03 22:23:37&amp;rdquo;]
 kt and open seem the best focal traits. Unclear what good null traits to use would be.
 Unclear if anything is gained by indep thetas in this example.
 Performance of alpha v theta?
  Edited plotting of likelihood comparisons, just grouped by trait to get common axis. (Difficult to get intelligent zooming on facet_grid to ignore the outliers). Trying such as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: pmc package, latex to word attempts</title>
      <link>/2012/01/03/tuesday-pmc-package-latex-to-word-attempts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2012 18:49:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/03/tuesday-pmc-package-latex-to-word-attempts/</guid>
      <description>Back from Oz.
Evolution submission: Latex to word Final submission needs editable copy. No great solutions for latex to word, despite quite a few options:
 tex2rtf is a fast solution to get something, but not successful on images or equations. Ended up going with this after all.
 pandoc is a generic converter to many types, but has only partial support for latex input. Does okay on text, but fails on even simple things like italics and natbib citations</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/12/09/friday-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2011 13:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/09/friday-9/</guid>
      <description>Wrightscape/pmc  Writing up derivation from Thursday properly / for manuscript. Writing up test cases for method2, direct evaluation of covariance matrix for comparisons Minor revisions submitted to Evolution  pdg-control To Do  Implement the NCO. Implement HS SDP Closer read of (Sethi et. al. 2005), (Su &amp;amp; Peterman, 2012) and Woodward &amp;amp; Tomberlin  Warning signals  Allee effects in linear programming with different classes. Timescales of noise using van Kampen expansion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/12/08/thursday-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2011 11:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/08/thursday-11/</guid>
      <description>Another day of working on 4 different projects at once.
Warning signals  review Alan pulses manuscript
 review (Dulvy et. al. 2003) Paper discussing the data you want $ \neq $ the data you want
  No way in Anchoveta data, look at time series:
Example in the cod data using only up until 1991 data:
 Way forward &amp;ndash; construct the step-wise predictor of probabilities. Add the economic costs of both.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - wrightscape runs and various other things</title>
      <link>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 18:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11/</guid>
      <description>pdg-control  plots for changing costs Report out to Training Problem II group.  ggplot note defining functions that return a ggplot object can be tricky. If you compute some objects in the plot function (stats etc), those stats are not stored by the object (due to lazy evaluation, usually a very nice time-saving feature), so the plot cannot be produced unless the function returns those things to the global environment (or from wherever the plot will be printed/evaluated).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday -- two insights</title>
      <link>/2011/12/06/tuesday-two-insights/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2011 21:46:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/06/tuesday-two-insights/</guid>
      <description>Control &amp;amp; Optimization Dominique Bonvin visit  two-step control (optimize parameters, optimize mean-square error between model and measurement also by parameter adjustment) fails when reality isn&amp;rsquo;t in the model set. Problem is under-determined (N free variables, 4N equations). (converges, but onto the wrong optimum).
 Better solution &amp;ndash; adjust the penalty/regularization terms to to get better agreement between model and data
 Bonvin approach &amp;ndash; adjust the control instead (NCO Control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday - wrightscape meetings, PDG meeting</title>
      <link>/2011/12/05/monday-wrightscape-meetings-pdg-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 18:45:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/05/monday-wrightscape-meetings-pdg-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Wrightscape &amp;ndash; added a user utility to to specify custom model types, such that some subset of the total number of regimes can share certain parameters.
Peter Meeting  Derivation &amp;ndash; provide clear examples of the differences and by how much it matters. Expected result from the biology: the jaw lever traits should show greater changes than the other traits after a release of constraint. Based on previous studies, expect most of the action to be around the intramandibular joint innovation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More labrid plots</title>
      <link>/2011/12/05/more-labrid-plots/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 10:24:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/05/more-labrid-plots/</guid>
      <description>Intramandibular likelihood comparisons
Parameter zooms:
Pharyngeal likelihood comparisons
Both shifts:
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;phylogenetics&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-12-03 8:00:37&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-12-04 23:23:37&amp;rdquo;]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release of constraint</title>
      <link>/2011/12/04/release-of-constraint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2011 13:41:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/04/release-of-constraint/</guid>
      <description>(uncertainty estimation to follow).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday - updated wrightscape results - simulated examples</title>
      <link>/2011/12/02/friday-updated-wrightscape-results/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2011 22:35:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/02/friday-updated-wrightscape-results/</guid>
      <description>Consider two simulated datasets, one under a release of constraint (left) one under an increase in sigma (right). Can we correctly discriminate between these models?
Parameter differences:
Likelihood differences:
Yup.
Repeated with effect-size scaled to be roughly equivalent for both traits. Wondering if it&amp;rsquo;s easier to plot parameters out separately like this. Error bars show median and 25&amp;frasl;75 % quantile range, with barplots showing the means (note that high outliers makes mean often larger than median).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thrusday - corrected calculation, implementing.  </title>
      <link>/2011/12/01/thrusday-corrected-calculation-implementing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2011 23:33:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/01/thrusday-corrected-calculation-implementing/</guid>
      <description>Implementing Wednesday night&amp;rsquo;s calculations. Should transcribe full derivation from paper notebook, meanwhile (revealing how chaotic my work process really is):
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;equations&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-12-04 11:00:37&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-12-04 11:39:37&amp;rdquo;]
Day&amp;rsquo;s log of plots:
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;phylogenetics&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-12-01 8:00:37&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-12-01 23:23:37&amp;rdquo;]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - various logistics, then checking likelihood calculation</title>
      <link>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2011 20:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci  rOpenSci wins runner up prize in PLoS + Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s Binary Battle! Write replies to interview questions with Mendeley. roxygenizing documentation for RMendeley &amp;ndash; about half done  pdg-control  Call with Jake scheduled for tomorrow Emails with Michael. I&amp;rsquo;ll implement delay intervals, he&amp;rsquo;ll add costs to adjustment. Need to fix/finish delay interval optimization calculation (exponent of matrix &amp;amp; beta)  Warning Signals Meeting with Alan
 Regime shifts Emphasize the RO curve in uncertainty analysis See (Dulvy et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday debugging</title>
      <link>/2011/11/29/tuesday-debugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2011 10:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/29/tuesday-debugging/</guid>
      <description>Wrote seven unit tests to identify source of how/why I can get $ \alpha $&amp;rsquo;s to be larger in the parrotfish group than wrasses (when only $alpha $ varies across regimes) on the same trait for which $ \sigma $&amp;rsquo;s are larger (when only they vary). Tests successively restrict pattern into the likelihood equation, some treatment of the regimes must be wrong.
Unit tests.
Nov 29, 2011  also need to double-check calc of lca_matrix &amp;ndash; needs to obey same sc… …  52a5d0bf12  Browse code</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: submodels for full traits</title>
      <link>/2011/11/28/monday-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 11:00:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/28/monday-11/</guid>
      <description>Two shifts alpha sigma likelihood Pharyngeal shift alpha sigma likelihood Intramandibular shift alpha sigma likelihood Intramandibular shift (parrotfish only) alpha sigma likelihood Troubleshooting It seems alpha is often higher in the regime that has a the higher sigma when variance is restricted to sigma. This cannot be right.
Creating unit tests:
Sigma behaves correctly in the following way. Simulate data where regimes have different sigmas.
require(wrightscape) data(labrids) s1_spec &amp;lt;- list(alpha = &amp;quot;global&amp;quot;, sigma = &amp;quot;indep&amp;quot;, theta = &amp;quot;global&amp;quot;) s1 &amp;lt;- multiTypeOU(data = dat[&amp;quot;close&amp;quot;], tree = tree, regimes = pharyngeal, model_spec = s1_spec, control = list(maxit=5000)) # Order of entries in sigma is the order regime names are given by levels (alphabetical) names(s1$sigma) &amp;lt;- levels(pharyngeal) s1$sigma[&amp;quot;other&amp;quot;] &amp;lt;- .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: wrightscape, ggplot, wp memory</title>
      <link>/2011/11/25/friday-wrightscape-ggplot-wp-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2011 20:32:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/25/friday-wrightscape-ggplot-wp-memory/</guid>
      <description>more sub-model comparisons wrightscape sub-models:
 a1 independent alphas, global theta, sigmas
 bm &amp;ldquo;brownie&amp;rdquo; (alpha = 0, indep sigmas)
 a2 independent alpha, theta, global sigma
 s1 indep sigma, global alpha, theta
 s2 indep sigma, theta, global alpha
  Basic Nelder Mead Simulated annealing associated parameter estimates
This approach is really not finding a very robust solution.
Plotting with stats_summary() Using stats_summary instead of melt and cast computations and line and ribbon geometries for adding statistical layers to plots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>wrightscape and sensitivity to initial conditions</title>
      <link>/2011/11/17/wrightscape-and-sensitivity-to-initial-conditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 23:08:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/17/wrightscape-and-sensitivity-to-initial-conditions/</guid>
      <description>Seems ouma performs poorly, though the sign of the effect seems correct. Starting conditions cause this.
Even starting conditions: improves the fit and flips the sign of the result.
More parameters: addendum Longer runs using simulated annealing can still get stuck.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wainwright Retreat to Hastings Reserve</title>
      <link>/2011/11/12/of-labrids-and-dubious-convergence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2011 21:36:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/12/of-labrids-and-dubious-convergence/</guid>
      <description>Two-day mini conference with Wainwright lab, Mike Alfaro lab, Rita Mehta lab, Tim Higham lab at the Hastings reserve, with everyone (about 30 of us) presenting, and discussions on convergence and on modularity.
more labrid trait evolution alpha &amp;amp; sigma models on two shifts, not converged runs. should really consider the mcmc or at least simulated annealing.
Peter proposes looking at model adequacy by deviance of a observed traits from what is expected under the model (by replicate simulations).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Auteur plots for reef fish jaws and monkey brains -- needs tweaking</title>
      <link>/2011/11/10/auteur-plots-for-reef-fish-jaws-and-monkey-brains-needs-tweaking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2011 17:22:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/10/auteur-plots-for-reef-fish-jaws-and-monkey-brains-needs-tweaking/</guid>
      <description>Looking at the diversification patterns from Auteur. Longer rjmcmc runs aren&amp;rsquo;t showing a significant difference, but more attention needed in parameters such as initial merge-split probability perhaps? Seems to overestimate the change points.
Remains true for the primate brains example:
Set up to run on carver cluster, copy over the saved rda file and all files matching the random string already saved as outputs. Full labrid example on 20 cores still exceeds the allocation capacity for an R vector.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday&#39;s reading</title>
      <link>/2011/11/04/fridays-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2011 13:14:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/04/fridays-reading/</guid>
      <description>Reading Catching up on journal table-of-contents/rss readings.
News Australia Researchers unhappy (unknown, 2011)
Climate change and Open Science Nature debate on the Berkeley climate team&amp;rsquo;s (BEST) press release in advance of publication. (unknown, 2011) Editor critiques the stunt:
 Richard Muller, the physicist in charge, even told the BBC: &amp;ldquo;That is the way I practised science for decades; it was the way everyone practised it until some magazines — particularly Science and Nature — forbade it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Labrids &amp; Parrotfish, method1</title>
      <link>/2011/11/01/labrids-parrotfish-method1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 08:57:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/01/labrids-parrotfish-method1/</guid>
      <description>Parrotfish only: Shift at intramandibular joint in BM rate only. Shift in constraint, $ \alpha $ at intramandibular innovation. Labrids: Wrasses vs parrotfish Shift in BM rate Shift in constraint, $ \alpha $ Compare to: method2</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Labrid submodels</title>
      <link>/2011/10/26/labrid-submodels/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2011 15:49:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/26/labrid-submodels/</guid>
      <description>Updates to labrids results:
 Results from Parrotfish tree &amp;amp; 2-partition Labrid tree on full model.  Full model, Labrids Pharyngeal Shift 
Alphas Sigmas Full Model, Intramandibular Shift .
Labrid tree, multi-sigma model, both shifts Surprising less powerful at identifying the differences.
Note that this still estimates OU models, and hence has a global alpha, and unique thetas:
LABRID TREE, MULTI-alpha, BOTH SHIFTS Parrotfish tree, multi-sigma model: Parrotfish tree, multi-alpha model: Labrid pharyngeal only, multi-sigma model: Labrid pharyngeal, multi-alpha Labrid intramandibular only, multi-sigma model: Labrid intramandibular, multi-alpha Full model plots with: method2_plots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday notes: package work mostly.</title>
      <link>/2011/10/25/tuesday-notes-package-work-mostly/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2011 19:18:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/25/tuesday-notes-package-work-mostly/</guid>
      <description>Treebase release  write updated tutorial.
 cran needs mac and windows binaries.
  Trying devtools win_builder(); emailing Kurt. Nevermind, just got the email saying the binary has been built.
 write email announcement  rfishbase data formatting My problem turned out not to be about &amp;ldquo;\&amp;rdquo; at all, these were octal encodings of symbols used in the XML data, eg: Cape Bojador (26°N)
which xmlValue() would read in using the octal encoding &amp;rdquo;Cape Bojador (26\302\260N)&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2011/10/25/treebase-package-on-cran/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2011 19:06:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/25/treebase-package-on-cran/</guid>
      <description>My treebase package is now up on the CRAN repository. (Source code is up, the binaries should appear soon). Here&amp;rsquo;s a few introductory examples to illustrate some of the functionality of the package. Thanks in part to new data deposition requirements at journals such as Evolution, Am Nat, and Sys Bio, and data management plan requirements from NSF, I hope the package will become increasingly useful for teaching by replicating results and for meta-analyses that can be automatically updated as the repository grows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday - some parrotfish &amp; labrid runs on method2</title>
      <link>/2011/10/20/thursday-some-parrotfish-runs-on-method2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2011 16:20:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/20/thursday-some-parrotfish-runs-on-method2/</guid>
      <description>Running:
 farm cluster, c0-17 method2_parrotfish.R &amp;ndash; Done. Below.
 farm cluster, c0-27 method2_labrids.R (with three partitions)
 farm cluster, c0-13 method2_labrids_phar.R (two partitions)
 farm cluster, c0-19 method2_labrids_intra.R (two partitions)
  Parrotfish Phylogeny The .y indicates the trait has been size-corrected. Parameters reported from estimations in the full model. All sets converged except open lever ratio. Error bars indicate 1 standard deviation estimated from the likelihood curvature. Lighter color indicates the presence of an intramandibular joint, as coded in the phylogeny above.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matt Helmus visit</title>
      <link>/2011/10/07/matt-helmus-visit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2011 14:36:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/07/matt-helmus-visit/</guid>
      <description>Notes from presentation 1. Species-area curve:  Species sorting by environment. species clustering due to limited dispersal Random displacement (faster saturation) In-situ speciation looks like clustering Compare to colonization Phylogenetic species variability metric: compare phylogenetic covariance matrix to a star-phylogeny, not expected to increase with area.  $$ \frac{n \textrm{tr}C - \sum C }{n(n-1)}$$
2. Simulations:  species sort along an environmental gradient. BM trait determining position. : closely related species clustered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/10/04/tuesday-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2011 22:29:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/04/tuesday-9/</guid>
      <description>Hastings seminar: Forest Pest Outbreaks Schedule
Prof Dave Rizzo  Reviews major pest outbreaks (Major Forest Insect &amp;amp; Disease Conditions in the United States 2009 Update)  Mentions weekend&amp;rsquo;s NY Times piece, (and see author&amp;rsquo;s commentary), reviews major pest outrbreak trends.   David Kling Allee effects &amp;amp; Management (Gypsy moth). * Review review (Taylor &amp;amp; Hastings, 2005). * Simulation exploration: pmid: 19831081, * Also discuss (Tobin et. al. 2011).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday, wordpress backups, pmc edits</title>
      <link>/2011/09/30/friday-wordpress-backups-pmc-edits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 17:51:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/30/friday-wordpress-backups-pmc-edits/</guid>
      <description>Wordpress local copy  configured mysqldump backup, following dreamhost wiki (added cron job manually instead of in panel).  edit local wp-config.php to use localhost. Get the database name, user name and password from the lines above it, which are used later.
define(&#39;DB_HOST&#39;, &#39;localhost&#39;); // ...and the server MySQL is running on  create user: log in as root
mysql -u root -p  and create user
mysql&amp;gt; create database database_name mysql&amp;gt; create user &#39;username&#39;@&#39;localhost&#39; identified by &#39;password&#39;; mysql&amp;gt; create database database_name mysql&amp;gt; grant usage on *.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/29/thursday-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2011 16:46:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/29/thursday-10/</guid>
      <description>9-9:20 Updating research statement (home page). 9:20 -9:40 Updating notebook: Review, Tuesday &amp;amp; Wednesday meetings coffee 9:50 Application. 10-11:30:  Forage fish dynamics, Sanchirico and Essington Jim gives the broad overview, central question: What are the benefits/costs of a % reduction in the catch C of forage fish N:
$$ \Delta C \downarrow \to \Delta N \to \Delta F, \Delta M \Delta S$$
F predator commercial fisheries, M marine mammals, S seabirds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetics - Research Proposal</title>
      <link>/2011/09/29/phylogenetics-research-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2011 15:20:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/29/phylogenetics-research-proposal/</guid>
      <description>Evolution has shaped all ecological communities. It has tested their resilience in experiments we could never perform. Now can it help us identify what characteristics make a community resilient or vulnerable to external forces?
Anthropogenic influences such as invasive species, climate change, and urbanization pressure ecosystems everywhere on the planet. Some collapse suddenly, others appear remarkably resilient. What makes some systems more vulnerable, and how could we identify them? Ecologists have long sought to understand the factors most influencing this stability, but the scale is immense and the problem complex &amp;ndash; making controlled experimentation difficult and limited.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - Berkeley visits</title>
      <link>/2011/09/28/wednesday-berkeley-visits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 09:25:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/28/wednesday-berkeley-visits/</guid>
      <description>Consultation call with Rebecca Lawrence, F1000. F1000 is exploring offering a data publishing platform, and we discussed some of the potential challenges (submission incentives, data review/reproducible review, meta-data standards).   anyone who might be interested in working with us to get this project off the ground, with a scientific PhD background, a reasonable understanding of data sharing/mining issues and some knowledge of technical issues (not necessarily a coder but I guess it might help) then do let me know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/26/monday-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 15:31:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/26/monday-10/</guid>
      <description>Phylogenetics paper  Grayscale the figures  Moore &amp;amp; Coop PBG 270: Phylo methods for exploring correlations between character traits and lineage rates.
 Models ((Are the generalized birth-death models (e.g. Kendall 1948) good limit to interesting process? somtimes. ))    detecting variation in rates
 locating shifts along branches
 locating shifts in time
 correlates of differential rates (_e.g. _traits; our subject for today/course).
 Parameter estimation</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: ropensci, manuscript edits</title>
      <link>/2011/09/23/friday-ropensci-manuscript-edits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2011 11:03:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/23/friday-ropensci-manuscript-edits/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci Conference Call Catalyst grant  Reviewed budget. Karthik will merge current proposals, Carl will review. Goal: send out next week. Ask Mark Hahnel to look it over  Blog posts  Carley planning to make guest blog post within the next week.  Mendeley/Plos Binary battle  Carl will file entry form. Karthik push edits to rplos Scott will add rplos tutorial to ropensci.org Carl will add rmendeley tutorial to ropensci.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/22/thursday-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 17:51:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/22/thursday-9/</guid>
      <description>Sent off review. finally.
Sanchirico seminar with Tim Essington (U Washington). Goal: Prepare for a review on forage fisheries.
Outline  background background Fishery interactions marine mammal/seabird interactions Climate &amp;amp; forage fish Fishmeal (Demand side) direct consumption (Demand side) Vitamin supp / health benefits (Demand side) Non-market value marine mammals Synthesis  Forage-fish: &amp;ldquo;foundation species&amp;rdquo; in marine ecosystems, get energy from zooplankton/upwelling to high-level predators (high-market target fisheries). Sardines/pilchards, anchovies, sandeels, krill, herrings, capelin, menhaden.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood expressions for branching processes</title>
      <link>/2011/09/10/likelihood-expressions-for-branching-processes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2011 14:29:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/10/likelihood-expressions-for-branching-processes/</guid>
      <description>Lineage-through-time approach Nee, then Paradis (Paradis, 2003) introduces unresolved tips
Distribution of branch-lengths approach Note that in any Markov branching process, only node depth, not topology, influence the likelihood.
See also:  Notes on bootstrapping in laser
 Earlier Notes on distribution derivation from Kendall 1948
 My derivation of the analytic probability of N individuals in pure birth (from van Kampen approximation)
  (manual list)
Refs Kendall, D.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>discriminating early bursts</title>
      <link>/2011/09/08/discriminating-early-bursts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2011 23:08:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/08/discriminating-early-bursts/</guid>
      <description>Looking at cases when early burst can be discriminated from OU, a la Harmon et al 2010 (Harmon et. al. 2010). Fixed models can be told apart. Rather trivially, none of these models can be told apart if initially estimated from Brownian data. Rather encouraging: models estimated from common data can be told apart. 600 taxa tree
Still works on 60 taxa, identifying OU correctly when sim under OU (left), and EB for EB data (right):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rfishbase demo: Are there more Goby or Labrid species on reefs?</title>
      <link>/2011/09/02/rfishbase-demo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2011 12:59:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/02/rfishbase-demo/</guid>
      <description>I have updated the package to 0.0-3 alpha, having all the target functionality now. Improved error handling, downloading of data, processing. Get the source or windows binary here. I now download the full database and cache it locally for faster querying. Just about any kind of manipulation is then possible and fast.
For instance, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick demo based on a question from Peter Wainwright: &amp;ldquo;are there more gobys or labrids on reefs?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/31/wednesday-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2011 12:09:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/31/wednesday-7/</guid>
      <description>Reading Wait, the storage effect is often evolutionarily unstable? Yikes. (Snyder &amp;amp; Adler, 2011). Will have to read this more closely.
 Vasseur &amp;amp; Fox nice AD paper in PNAS Am Nat (Vasseur &amp;amp; Fox, 2011), ((One day Am Nat will finish registering the doi for these papers?))   Contrary to previous verbal arguments that suggest that character convergence leads to neutral stability, coadaptation of competing consumers always leads to stable coexistence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/30/tuesday-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2011 22:11:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/30/tuesday-8/</guid>
      <description> Completed review for Methods.
 First read-through of review/resubmission for THEE.
 Working on Evolution manuscript
 Wrightscape: root should have the option of being fixed at phylogenetic mean for all models. Do root estimates occur far from this currently?
 Check graph color schemes, seem inconsistent.
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: scaling wrightscape examples</title>
      <link>/2011/08/29/monday-scaling-wrightscape-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2011 18:27:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/29/monday-scaling-wrightscape-examples/</guid>
      <description>syntaxHighligher isn&amp;rsquo;t working. no idea why, posted to forums.
 Still no luck compiling gsl on carver. Can&amp;rsquo;t install gsl R package or compile wrightscape C code. posted C issue to NERSC, R issue to statscicomp.
   Commits to taxize pushed to Scott.
wrightscape parrotfish example Convergence test: with simple (common) initial values (alpha=.1, sigma=1), the different methods behave mostly appropriately: outer nested models out-perform inner ones, and likelihoods roughly agree between ouch package methods and wrightscape equivalents:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday: scaling, runs</title>
      <link>/2011/08/28/sunday-scaling-runs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2011 22:33:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/28/sunday-scaling-runs/</guid>
      <description>laptop: ubuntu upgrades: 10.04 LTS -&amp;gt; 10.10 -&amp;gt; 11.04, geesh.
Set up for running primates.R in likelihood mode with abstracted parallelization:
Carver trouble getting wrightscape installed: even after module load gsl, cannot find gsl library. Testing on zero in mpi mode, 16. Testing on farm, mpi mode with snow, 16 cores.
hmm, high (9%) memory usage on primates.R on zero&amp;hellip; monitoring situation closely&amp;hellip; Only .3% on farm so far, which has 24G instead of zero&amp;rsquo;s 32Gig RAM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rropensci and some taxonomy in R with taxize</title>
      <link>/2011/08/26/rfishbase-and-some-taxonomy-in-r-with-taxize/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2011 23:16:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/26/rfishbase-and-some-taxonomy-in-r-with-taxize/</guid>
      <description>rfishbase Went through demo of rfishbase with Tomomi. Improved error handling, added a few data types and a few use cases.
I always forget that I have to drop nulls by indexing, not my return values of sapply.
x[!sapply(x, is.null)]  Very annoyed with fishbase id numbers (being discontinuous listings and unable to query xml by anything more intelligent). Querying all fishbase ids 1:30000, I get only 999 fish. hmm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: rropensci, Rmpi, manuscripts, ...</title>
      <link>/2011/08/23/tuesday-rfishbase-rmpi-manuscripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2011 15:10:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/23/tuesday-rfishbase-rmpi-manuscripts/</guid>
      <description>rfishbase In answer to Tomomi&amp;rsquo;s question from last week, have basic functionality as an R package on github, rfishbase. Learned some slightly richer XML parsing in the process.
XML Notes Had to identify blocks by a child node that specifies the identity, and then find the sibling node that contains the content I needed. Goes something like this:
&amp;lt;dataObject&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dc:identifier&amp;gt;FB-Size-2&amp;lt;/dc:identifier&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dc:description&amp;gt; Text I need &amp;lt;/dc:description&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/dataObject&amp;gt;  Which I parsed in R as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic Year 2011 Summary</title>
      <link>/2011/08/21/academic-year-2011-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2011 23:46:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/21/academic-year-2011-summary/</guid>
      <description>Brief summary of events for this past academic year, as submitted to my dissertation committee.
TALKS  Model Choice for Phylogenetic Comparative Methods, Evolution 2010 Computational Methods for comparative inference (poster), DoE CSGF Meeting, 2010. My experiment with open notebook science, iEvoBio 2010 Power in Phylogenetic Comparative Methods, SICB 2011 Open Notebook Science - Connections to databases. Science Online, 2011 General model of evolution for continuous traits on phylogenies, Evolution 2011 Automated meta-analyses via an R - TreeBASE package, iEvoBio 2011 Early Warning Signals, ESA 2011.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: reviewing edits, ropensci, computers.</title>
      <link>/2011/08/18/thursday-reviewing-edits-fishbase-computers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2011 15:03:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/18/thursday-reviewing-edits-fishbase-computers/</guid>
      <description>Graham &amp;amp; Peter meeting Going over review and figuring out how to address issues. Plan: Will write our line-by-line responses under the reviewer comments in the Google Doc. Peter and I will implement remaining changes on the .tex file, then we&amp;rsquo;ll compose the reply letter from the notes under the comments and include the latex-diff.
Brief topic notes from today&amp;rsquo;s meeting:
 set up different take on layout: lambda, AIC, power</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrightscape: a brief tutorial</title>
      <link>/2011/08/17/wrightscape-a-brief-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 14:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/17/wrightscape-a-brief-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>While the wrightscape package is still in active development, I realize the code base doesn&amp;rsquo;t contain any introductory examples. So as a first tutorial, here&amp;rsquo;s a short walk-through of the package. We begin by loading the package and a few useful additional packages:
require(wrightscape} # My package for this analysis require(auteur) # for the data only require(maticce) # to create paintings  We&amp;rsquo;ll load a data set of 233 taxa of primates with their body sizes(REDDING et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday:</title>
      <link>/2011/08/16/tuesday-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2011 19:04:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/16/tuesday-7/</guid>
      <description> Finished first round of edits and sent off to Graham and Peter.
 Exploring wrightscape runs on additional data sets
 Exploring migrating code into MPI
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: Evolution manuscript revisions; early burst models, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/08/16/monday-evolution-manuscript-revisions-early-burst-models-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2011 12:13:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/16/monday-evolution-manuscript-revisions-early-burst-models-etc/</guid>
      <description>Evolution Manuscript Edits Received the reviews of our evolution manuscript back with relatively straight-forward edits. (Yay!)
Need better citations of the early history in phylogenetic comparative methods, which is quite rich. Reviewer pointed me to an early book chapter by AW Edwards and LL Cavalli-Sforza introducing Brownian motion model in 1964, of which Joe Felsenstein has a nice description (of this and other work) in his 1988 review(Felsenstein, 1988).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: ESA, appendix, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/07/25/monday-esa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 23:22:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/25/monday-esa/</guid>
      <description>Reading Gene expression as a continuous phenotypic trait &amp;ndash; establishing signal for selection over drift. (Bedford &amp;amp; Hartl, 2009) OU vs BM (or just estimation of selection in the OU model relative to tree length) would have been an obvious way to do this, but the paper tries to make the argument that scaling the data and then comparing
$$\frac{\sigma^2}{2\alpha} $$
is some indication.
Model choice section on warning signals Trying to figure out whether or not to remove this section (previously Appendix H: Model Choice and Model Adequacy).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcasing the latest phylogenetic methods: AUTEUR</title>
      <link>/2011/07/20/showcasing-the-latest-phylogenetic-methods-auteur/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 15:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/20/showcasing-the-latest-phylogenetic-methods-auteur/</guid>
      <description>While high-speed fish feeding videos may be the signature of the lab, dig a bit deeper and you&amp;rsquo;ll find a wealth of comparative phylogenetic methods sneaking in. It&amp;rsquo;s a natural union &amp;ndash; expert functional morphology is the key to good comparative methods, just as phylogenies hold the key to untangling the evolutionary origins of that morphology. The lab&amp;rsquo;s own former graduate, Brian O&amp;rsquo;Meara, made a revolutionary step forward in the land of phylogenetic methods when he unveiled Brownie in 2006, allowing researchers to identify major shifts in trait diversification rates across the tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#ievobio Day 2</title>
      <link>/2011/06/22/ievobio-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 23:44:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/22/ievobio-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Day 2 is every bit as packed as day 1, and then some do to the higher concentration of lightning talks. Other coverage of #ievobio is starting to find it&amp;rsquo;s way to the web:
 Nico Cellinese
 Scott Chamberlain
 Rob Guralnick
  Meanwhile, my scratchpad of notes from day 2, tweet-style.
My Lightning Talk Gave my lightning talk in this session, slides:
R interface to TreeBASE</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Day 4 / #ievobio Day 1</title>
      <link>/2011/06/21/evolution-day-4-ievobio-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2011 23:44:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/21/evolution-day-4-ievobio-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Start of the ievobio conference, simultaneously the forth day of evolution. ievobio conference was very busy, luckily given the nature of the conference it is also largely well documented online. My notes are again archived primarily in tweet form below. My personal highlights of the day included the Keynote by Cladio Silva on Provenance &amp;ndash; essentially supporting reproducible research workflows &amp;ndash; and examples through his vistrails software, and Mark Yoder&amp;rsquo;s demonstration of mx at the software bazaar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Day 3</title>
      <link>/2011/06/20/evolution-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2011 23:44:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/20/evolution-day-3/</guid>
      <description>Talks  David Babst: Patterns of diversification on large species level supertree of extinct graptolites &amp;ndash; Actually, more on methods for making such a supertree for extinct taxa than on diversification analysis, but excellent talk.
 Gene Hunt: _Using fossils to test the link between speciation and phenotypic evolution &amp;ndash; _another highlight of the talks, really looking at cladeogeneic vs anaogenic models of evolutionary change, modifying the approach of Folmer Bokma</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides from my talk at Evolution 2011</title>
      <link>/2011/06/20/slides-from-my-talk-at-evolution-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2011 20:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/20/slides-from-my-talk-at-evolution-2011/</guid>
      <description>A general model of continuous character evolution [iframe http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/8371419 425 355]
View more presentations from Carl Boettiger
As highlighted in the last slide (following acknowledgments), clicking on the results graphs will take you to the image repository, which records when the result was generated in my workstream, and provides a link to the script, software package and data to replicate. Code is parallel, examples shown took between 2 and 12 hours on a 16-core cpu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Day 2</title>
      <link>/2011/06/19/evolution-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2011 23:44:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/19/evolution-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Second day of the conference. Many of the talks I most want to see are coming up Monday and Tuesday, and I have a bit more to do to prepare my own talk, so I take it a bit light on sessions. Highlight of the day was definitely the discussion with Mark McPeek and the other journal editors during and following the &amp;ldquo;Happy hour with the editors&amp;rdquo; session, which was perhaps the best event of the conference, despite a rather unimpressive attendance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Conference Day 1</title>
      <link>/2011/06/18/evolution-conference-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2011 21:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/18/evolution-conference-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Morning Sessions SSB Symposium 8:30 - noon: Unified Approaches for Understanding Patterns of Character Evolution and Diversification  Stacey Smith (U. of Nebraska-Lincoln) and Boris Igic (U.of Illinois-Chicago) - &amp;ldquo;Introduction to models of character state-dependent diversification&amp;rdquo;  Introduces the BiSSE model.
 Richard Fitzjohn (U. of British Columbia) - &amp;ldquo;Stochastic mapping incorporating differential diversification&amp;rdquo;  BiSSE comparison to traditional discrete-trait transition rate which ignores the correlation.
 Folmer Bokma (Umeå University) - &amp;ldquo;Estimating speciation and extinction with incomplete phylogenies&amp;rdquo;   Emma Goldberg (University of Illinois-Chicago) - &amp;ldquo;Modes of speciation and character change from phylogenetic trees&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: more labrid &amp; parrotfish wrightscape examples</title>
      <link>/2011/06/17/friday-more-labrid-parrotfish-wrightscape-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2011 15:16:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/17/friday-more-labrid-parrotfish-wrightscape-examples/</guid>
      <description>Runs from yesterday: MLE comparison of full labrid pharyngeal innovation (all parrotfish), alpha-v-sigma: Unfortunately, the all-variable mcmc over labrid tree was unsuccessful.
Pure-brownie vs pure diversification ends up with the surprisingly opposite conclusion from the sigmas-alphas on parrotfish close ratio:
Clearly a convergence problem but with which model? (see parameter distributions adjacent; following in photostream archive).
Luckily this is not the case in the full labrid (size-corrected, protrusion, pharyngeal innovation) model set:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrightscape labrid/parrotfish results; Evolution pres</title>
      <link>/2011/06/16/wrightscape-labridparrotfish-results-evolution-pres/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 22:14:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/16/wrightscape-labridparrotfish-results-evolution-pres/</guid>
      <description>Analysis Summarizing recently completed runs:  Reviewing last night&amp;rsquo;s runs. Some mcmcs complete:  Labrid prot.y alpha  and some crashed mcmc&amp;rsquo;s on Zero launched Tuesday night. (gape.y, close, open don&amp;rsquo;t seem to want to run)
 the sigma-theta Vs alpha-theta on parrotfish (size-corrected) protrusion (over intramandibular innovation), which looks indistinguishable:
  sigma-theta vs alpha-theta, parrotfish prot.y alpha v sigma also indistinguishable on this data, see yesterday.
Closing, alpha vs sigma, parrotfish (intramandibular, 200 reps) Alpha Sigma Comparison Would like nicer with more replicates, but clearly distinguishable, as were yesterday&amp;rsquo;s when theta could also vary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday MCMC and MLEs for wrightscape</title>
      <link>/2011/06/15/wednesday-mcmc-and-mles-for-wrightscape/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2011 22:36:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/15/wednesday-mcmc-and-mles-for-wrightscape/</guid>
      <description>Wrote plotting function for wrightscape MCMC analysis
 added support to write MCMC to a file.
 exploring divergent MCMCs. more checks on NaNs
 trying MLE initiated MCMC
 Revising talk for evolution
 tweaks to socialR reporting &amp;ndash; include error message, exit with status=1, fewer time sigfigs; see gitlog.
   Max likelihoods &amp;amp; bootstraps Parrotfish protrusion (size corrected, 400 reps) If thetas are different and not allowed to vary, the alpha model will obviously do worse than the sigma model, even if it is correct.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday - Evolution/wrightscape talk &amp; sundry</title>
      <link>/2011/06/14/tuesday-evolutionwrightscape-talk-sundry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2011 23:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/14/tuesday-evolutionwrightscape-talk-sundry/</guid>
      <description>Computing For today&amp;rsquo;s analyses run history (with result/code links): see tweeting_cpu account or its search history (from Topsy)
Analysis/Summary MCMC over parrotfish tree on protrusion doesn&amp;rsquo;t converge when alpha and sigma are both free to vary.
MLE approach, (size-corrected) protrusion (12hr run)
Vary both theta and sigma:
Vary alpha and theta:
alpha-theta wins over theta-sigma:
git ids/urls git codes must be obtained at start of run, together with commit, or link will point to the wrong code!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday -</title>
      <link>/2011/06/13/monday-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2011 13:06:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/13/monday-7/</guid>
      <description> Algorithms group meeting Evolution presentation warningsignals runs complete and troubleshooting finalizing power in phylogenies manuscript cover letter, supplement, final check through, etc.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mcmc and bootstrapped likelihood runs on parrotfish tree</title>
      <link>/2011/06/09/mcmc-and-bootstrapped-likelihood-runs-on-parrotfish-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2011 16:48:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/09/mcmc-and-bootstrapped-likelihood-runs-on-parrotfish-tree/</guid>
      <description>Thursday Overview  Alan Meeting
 Still running scripts, see below
 pmc vignette
  To Do  Got Duncan&amp;rsquo;s ROAuth utilities for RMendeley, still need to test.
 Testing Scott&amp;rsquo;s rplos functions
 Send Alan the paragraph for edits.
  Computation Running on one  n 15: sim_general_mcmc.R MCMC of general model with 8 x 1e6 reps. alpha diverged. DEAD
 n14 Retry above with 8 x 1e6 and with less general model: sigma, theta indep only.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: Simulated model fit analysis on wrightscape, parrotfish tree</title>
      <link>/2011/06/08/wednesday-simulated-model-fit-analysis-on-wrightscape-parrotfish-tree/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2011 13:03:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/08/wednesday-simulated-model-fit-analysis-on-wrightscape-parrotfish-tree/</guid>
      <description>Reviewed last night&amp;rsquo;s simulations, see yesterday&amp;rsquo;s post.  Simulated data testing: Fitting the general model well on the parrotfish tree even with clear simulated data seems hard. Simulating with alpha(intramandibulars) = .01, and others = 20, and fitting general model and the alpha-only independent model (release of constraint model). The release model MLE recovers reasonable values: alpha(intra) = 1.7, alpha(others) = 21.8, while the general model fit is clearly struggling even with SANN.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: Parrotfish/wrightscape runs and code modification</title>
      <link>/2011/06/07/tuesday-parrotfishwrightscape-runs-and-code-modification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2011 23:47:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/07/tuesday-parrotfishwrightscape-runs-and-code-modification/</guid>
      <description>Runs: Mon midnight: parrotfish.R with updated SANN parameters and corrected output parameter labeling (always {Xo, alpha, sigma, theta} ordering), implemented on zero, nice 19. General model (&amp;ldquo;wright&amp;rdquo;) still not outperforming others, so still un-converged.
[flickr]5808279169/[/flickr]
 MCMC runs of gape.y and close on one, at nice 19 and 18 1e5 reps. (Alex running matlab nice 10). protrusion.y at nice 11, 1e6 reps.
 open at nice 18 on zero, 1e6 reps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parrotfish in wrightscape</title>
      <link>/2011/06/06/parrotfish-in-wrightscape/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 17:54:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/06/parrotfish-in-wrightscape/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapping option Needs a method to pass the optional optim arguments to the update function, such that update uses the same algorithm as the initial fit. Required being a little clever:
[gist id=&amp;ldquo;1010999&amp;rdquo;]
Done. but perhaps we won&amp;rsquo;t always want to bootstrap under this? I suppose it is good practice but slow! Shoot, now I need a lot of really large computers really soon.
Excellent suggestion for better ways to do this from statscicomp list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday: git with latexdiff, TreeBASE and PMC package updates, bounds on lambda</title>
      <link>/2011/06/04/saturday-git-with-latexdiff-treebase-and-pmc-package-updates-bounds-on-lambda/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2011 21:27:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/04/saturday-git-with-latexdiff-treebase-and-pmc-package-updates-bounds-on-lambda/</guid>
      <description>bounds on lambda: Updated the pmc wrappers for fit_continuous to pass bounds on lambda to the bootstrapping Monte Carlo functions. Settled on passing all options explicitly after quite a bit of effort. Looking for way to pass a function all of it&amp;rsquo;s arguments as a named arguments in a list; statscicomp list suggested do.call() function; quite brilliant.
Considering user workflow for wrappers. Conceptually, makes sense for user to run the standard package fit routines first, and then pass the results to pmc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/06/03/friday-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 17:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/03/friday-5/</guid>
      <description>A day&amp;rsquo;s agenda  Scott&amp;rsquo;s got us going on aR package forPLoS API, released Tuesday. Checked over the package and did some basic reorganization to put it in R package form. lots of feedback on my FF question on pw vs private for delayed-disclosure entries. warning signals manuscript package, figures, writing 9-11a Going through Peter&amp;rsquo;s revisions 11-1p Meeting with Peter &amp;amp; Graham 1-2p Meeting with Mikaela, Betta for GTC 2-4 PDG on Brian&amp;rsquo;s Autoparts paper 4-5:30  Colored git diff&amp;rsquo;s etc (from progit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: PMC, confidence intervals; screen code-tricks</title>
      <link>/2011/05/31/tuesday-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2011 14:38:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/31/tuesday-5/</guid>
      <description>PMC  Final read through of manuscript from me and Peter.
 Looking at confidence intervals in fitContinuous? Package used to use the hessian from optim, but it was later removed due to errors. I added this back manually and attempt a few estimates. Given the Hessian (likelihood surface curvature) this is approximated by
sqrt(diag(solve(out$hessian)))
 See conf_interval_ex.R. i.e for Geospiza tree is:
[1] SE sigma: +/ 0.6763731 SE lambda: +/- 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/30/monday-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2011 23:44:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/30/monday-6/</guid>
      <description>Power in Phylogenies Paper (PMC)  Working through / incorporated Graham&amp;rsquo;s edits Added confidence intervals discussion tweaks to associated pmc package Exploring confidence intervals (and lack thereof) in literature on comparative methods. Pagel (1999) (Pagel, 1999) includes them, but few other papers do. He does not include any discussion about how these are calculated. Seems Sweave makes sense for the recreate-figures code from the cached data-files, but perhaps not for the entire analysis code-base (in demos/).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/29/sunday-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2011 23:24:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/29/sunday-2/</guid>
      <description>Completed phylogenetic power manuscript updates based on Peter&amp;rsquo;s comments. Graham will read Monday. Took a whack at updating the treebase package with a method for grabbing nexus character matrices. Seegithub issues log, querying Emmanuel on this one. Local directory management / cleanup  Prepare annual progress report for committee  Phylogenetics Power manuscript. Nearly there. (SICB presentation) Warning signals manuscript resubmission. (Presenting at ESA) Generalized comparative method/release of constraint &amp;ndash; method done, time to write.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End of NCEAS &amp; the legacy of synthetic data</title>
      <link>/2011/05/22/end-of-nceas-the-legacy-of-synthetic-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2011 15:40:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/22/end-of-nceas-the-legacy-of-synthetic-data/</guid>
      <description>The upcoming termination of NSF funding for NCEAS has recently been receiving a bit of attention, including this nice piece in Science (Stokstad, 2011). I was particularly intrigued by Oikos&amp;rsquo;s treatment of this, in which Oikos editor Jeremy Fox writes,
 that&amp;rsquo;s probably NCEAS&amp;rsquo; biggest legacy-the sense that the answers to all, or at least many, of our questions are already out there, in existing data that just needs to be pulled together&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms group: MCMCMC</title>
      <link>/2011/05/19/algorithms-group-mcmcmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2011 12:52:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/19/algorithms-group-mcmcmc/</guid>
      <description>Discussed $\text{MC}^3$, the Metropolis coupled Markov Chain Monte Carlo, in Monday&amp;rsquo;s algorithms group meeting, just getting around to posting code. The MrBayes paper is a good reference for this (Altekar et. al. 2004). Ourpractice example needed some debugging. I re-wrote a general purpose mcmcmc function in R to illustrate the algorithm, below. Recall that it modifies our original MCMC in two ways. The normal proposal step gets weighted by temperature, allowing heated chains to step downhill more often.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/19/thursday-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2011 10:52:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/19/thursday-5/</guid>
      <description>Finish and post core notes from yesterday. Debugging locale problem in phylo packages = success. Emmanuel has already patched drop.fossils() in the ape package, will see if Gieger and TreeSim try to handle locale issue directly too. Problem in comparisons:  &amp;gt; Sys.setlocale(locale = &amp;quot;&amp;quot;) # default locale using UTF8 # message deleted &amp;gt; &amp;quot;-1&amp;quot; &amp;gt; 0 [1] TRUE &amp;gt; Sys.setlocale(locale = &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;) # message deleted &amp;gt; &amp;quot;-1&amp;quot; &amp;gt; 0 [1] FALSE   Posted MCMCMC notes from algorithms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Birth-death Tutorial for PBG Core</title>
      <link>/2011/05/18/birth-death-tutorial-for-pbg-core/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2011 23:55:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/18/birth-death-tutorial-for-pbg-core/</guid>
      <description>Ran a introductory tutorial on birth-death models for phylogenetic trees in R today for Peter Wainwright&amp;rsquo;s section of the Pop Bio Core sequence. Notes below, in a manner that may suggest I was better organized than reality might attest. Luckily the firsties are brilliant&amp;hellip;
Getting Started Code is shown section by section with results in the following examples. If you prefer, you can download my full code file here, but you will have to comment out my flickr plotting utilities before it will run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: Parrotfish results, MCMCMC testing, APIs</title>
      <link>/2011/05/17/tuesday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2011 22:55:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/17/tuesday-3/</guid>
      <description>Finished review for TE
 Shared post on TreeBASE API
 Reviewed Scott&amp;rsquo;s updates to dryad R API, adjusted formatting.
 Looking at documentation for the OAI-MPH queries, don&amp;rsquo;t seem to be as rich as Phylo-ws queries. This is why treeBASE metadata searches tend to download the full metadata set into R and query that. Looks like we&amp;rsquo;ll need to take a similar approach to Dryad, as it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like there&amp;rsquo;s a way to query the API by author name at all?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TreeBASE in R: a first tutorial</title>
      <link>/2011/05/16/treebase-in-r-a-first-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2011 19:46:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/16/treebase-in-r-a-first-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>My TreeBASE R package is essentially functional now. Here&amp;rsquo;s a quick tutorial on the kinds of things it can do. Grab the treebase package here, install and load the library into R.
TreeBASE provides two APIs to query the database, one which searches by the metadata associated with different publications (called OAI-PMH), and another which queries the phylogenies directly (called Phylo-ws). They have somewhat redundant functions, but for our purposes the second one returns the actual data, while the first returns metadata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: Fun with databases continued</title>
      <link>/2011/05/12/thursday-fun-with-databases-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2011 20:32:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/12/thursday-fun-with-databases-continued/</guid>
      <description>Dryad Hilmar pointed out the documentation for machine access to Dryad fileson the wiki, much nicer than guessing from the XML. (Good thing too, since it&amp;rsquo;s a bit more complicated than I thought). Wiki describes four steps:
 Get the dryad short-identifier for the datafile
 look up the METS reference using that identifier
 parse the XML returned by METS to find the bitstream url
 Query the bitstream url and presto!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: Treebase</title>
      <link>/2011/05/11/wednesday-treebase/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2011 15:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/11/wednesday-treebase/</guid>
      <description>TREEBASE PACKAGE:
 Modified treebase package to return the treebase id in the phylo class as phy$id, so that I can use the id to query the appropriate meta data.
 Modified the package with the option to return only max number of trees,
try(xpathApply(search_returns, paste(&amp;quot;//rdf:li[position()&amp;lt; &amp;quot;, max_trees, &amp;quot;]&amp;quot;, sep=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;), function(x){  &amp;hellip;
 Modified to check for branch lengths and remove trees without branch lengths from the returned set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interfaces for databases: TreeBASE, Dryad, DataONE</title>
      <link>/2011/05/10/interfaces-for-databases-treebase-dryad-dataone/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 09:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/10/interfaces-for-databases-treebase-dryad-dataone/</guid>
      <description>Next Steps Treebase  (See Sunday&amp;rsquo;s post) - Phylo-ws implemented, but a few extra functions would strengthen the interface a bit: limit the number of trees returned, querying trees for branch lengths,
 RaXML pipeline for returning rough branch lengths conditioned on the given topology, user documentation, more test examples.
 Implement OAI-PMH test cases for treebase: For instance, query all records after a given date (or all possible other queries), i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: meetings, notebook</title>
      <link>/2011/05/09/monday-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2011 23:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/09/monday-4/</guid>
      <description>Coop &amp;amp; Moore 270: Species Trees Discussing Bucky paper (Ane et. al. 2006)
Approach of BEST and *BEAST (last time): Prior probability on gene trees P(G|S), given species trees. Goal: Posterior of species trees,
$$ P(S|X) = \intG \Pi{\ell} \left[ P(X{\ell}|G{\ell}) P(G_{\ell}|S) \right] P(S) dG $$
$$ P(G{\ell}|S) = \Pi{b \in S} P(Hb(G{\ell})|S_b) $$
Uses a Dirchlet process model for clustering genes by topologies. All genes in a cluster agree to share a common topology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday: a few Treebase R package updates</title>
      <link>/2011/05/08/sunday-a-few-treebase-r-package-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 23:16:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/08/sunday-a-few-treebase-r-package-updates/</guid>
      <description>Working on a few updates to the TreeBASE package. This flushes out the basic functionality provided by the phylo-ws API now. Needs a bit more testing of the possible queries and some bells and whistles options. Meanwhile, going to start looking at the metadata side with the OAI-PMH API. With this I should be able to grab metadata associated with a tree or the tree associated with the metadata. Should also be able to extend the queries over to other databases such as Dryad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: parrotfish analysis</title>
      <link>/2011/05/05/thursday-parrotfish-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2011 16:57:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/05/thursday-parrotfish-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Summarizing parrotfish data under the single shift at the intramandibular joint. See version stable code for data loading/transforms (parrotfish_data.R), and for plots (parrotfish.R) as shown, and for analysis functions (loop_models_traits_regimes.R). Models are named by the parameter which is regime-dependent. Results are shown sorted by likelihood, so the best model is on top, and likelihood values are scaled by the weakest model.
Tree: alpha is favored in all the ratio traits, sometimes substantially.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Parrotfish data set analysis</title>
      <link>/2011/05/04/weds-parrotfish-data-set-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2011 23:16:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/04/weds-parrotfish-data-set-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Parrotfish  Need better convergence error handling.
 Need to remedy: &amp;ldquo;Function cannot be evaluated at initial parameters&amp;rdquo; errors &amp;ndash; Occur when attempting very large values of alpha, resulting in NaN output (trouble with exponentials of alpha in calculations).
 Changed summaries to group by painting, so compare models and traits. Less natural than comparing across painting for a single trait since that allows comparisons both across models and across paintings, but makes sense when comparing only a single partition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: phylogenetics- wrightscape coding</title>
      <link>/2011/05/03/tuesday-phylogenetics-wrightscape-coding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 23:31:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/03/tuesday-phylogenetics-wrightscape-coding/</guid>
      <description>Writing methods to loop wrightscape models over lists of different traits, regimes, and model specifications. Easy to end up with large-dimensional output, challenge for visualization. Experimenting with different groupings.
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;phylogenetics&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-05-03 00:00:00&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-05-03 23:59:59&amp;rdquo;]
See code: loop_models_traits_regimes.R
Routine attempts hansen fit for initial estimates of alpha and sigma. Could be greatly improved. Should extend attempts to guess initial conditions for optimization. Should add better convergence testing, simulated annealing option.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>treeBASE R interface: proposal for #iEvoBio</title>
      <link>/2011/05/03/treebase-an-r-interface-proposal-for-ievobio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 21:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/03/treebase-an-r-interface-proposal-for-ievobio/</guid>
      <description>Lightning Talk Proposal  I will present the R package treeBASE, which provides an R implementation of the treeBASE phylows API. This package makes it possible to search and import data from this database of published phylogenetic trees easily from within an R script. Recent data archiving requirements at major evolutionary journals such as The American Naturalist (Whitlock et. al. 2010) and Evolution (Fairbairn, 2011) to deposit data used in the study on the Dryad digital repository (and deposit accompanying trees in TreeBASE), along with new requirements for data management from funderssuch as NSF are rapidly changing the landscape of data availability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/03/monday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 11:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/03/monday-3/</guid>
      <description>Today:
 Application for CPB travel funds. DONE
 Faxed receipts from Felsenstein&amp;rsquo;s visit. DONE
  Seminar on Species trees Coop/Moore Seminar on *BEAST (Heled &amp;amp; Drummond, 2009) and BEST (Liu et. al. 2008).
Essential differences: BEST uses Mr. Bayes to compute probabilities over gene trees (over uniform prior). Then estimates the species tree by importance sampling from this distribution to reflect constraints under a convergence model. Integrates over effective population sizes rather than estimating (highly uncertain anyway), requires rooting, and a rather fast/loose implementation of ultra-metricizing trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: Notes on Labrids, notes on Transforms and size-corrections</title>
      <link>/2011/04/29/friday-notes-on-labrids-notes-on-transforms-and-size-corrections/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2011 22:19:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/29/friday-notes-on-labrids-notes-on-transforms-and-size-corrections/</guid>
      <description>The specific traits were:
Oral Jaw traits
 mouth-closing lever ratio (Close),
 mouth-opening lever ratio (Open), kinematic
 transmission coefficient of the oral jaws four-bar linkage (Jaw KT),
 adductor mandibulae (AM) muscle mass,
 premaxillary protrusion distance (Prot),
 gape width (Gape),
  Exterior to the Oral Jaws, not expected to become unconstrained:
 levator posterior (LP) muscle mass: (Pharyngeal jaw muscle)
 sterno-hyoideus (SH) muscle mass, (Primarily buccual cavity)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Notes, presentation prep treebase error handling</title>
      <link>/2011/04/28/thursday-reading-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2011 13:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/28/thursday-reading-notes/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Oikos journal recently started a rather nice blog. A journal long responsible for some of the best examples of developing and confronting ecological theory with empirical results, with an commendable emphasis on general principles and synthesis, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to see them enter the Web2.0 ecosystem. Editor Jeremy Fox has a nice introduction to the goals of the blog &amp;ndash; check out the &amp;ldquo;new ideas&amp;rdquo; categories for worthwhile reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/04/27/wednesday-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2011 21:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/27/wednesday-4/</guid>
      <description>7:30-9:30 Review for Theoretical Ecology
 Profiling wrightscape   Compile with profiling (-g -pg flags, in make profile). Run
valgrind --leak-check-full ./wrightscape.exe  to remove memory links. Run
valgrind --tool=callgrind kcachegrind callgrind.out.&amp;lt;###&amp;gt;  For profiling information
Troubleshooting implementation of restricted-domain functions. Cannot be wright_tree since they have to know their likelihood method. Will need an indicator to their type. Some troubleshooting of the simulation method too: my pmc&amp;rsquo;s montecarlotest() is set up so that simulate() can return the data set directly that is passed to update() or return a list object with the dataset in $rep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing phylognenies in TreeBASE from R</title>
      <link>/2011/04/26/accessing-phylognenies-in-treebase-from-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2011 14:10:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/26/accessing-phylognenies-in-treebase-from-r/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve recently ((25 April, 8 April)) begun a project to see if I can search for and load phylogenies from TreeBASE directly into R. Thanks to the rather brilliant API in place (documented on the treeBASE wiki) for TreeBASE, some advice from Rutger Vos (TreeBASE developer), and some xpaths R code from Gabe Becker (stats grad student, UC Davis), I have a (mostly) working demonstration. As I get a chance, I&amp;rsquo;ll be adding the rest of the queries available in the API, improve the error handling and give some more thought to a user interface.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TreeBASE interface continued...</title>
      <link>/2011/04/25/treebase-interface-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2011 10:11:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/25/treebase-interface-continued/</guid>
      <description>Returning to exploration of treeBASE interface and my attempt to implement an R interface the API (earlier entry)
Rutger Vos has gotten me started, pointing out that the handling of the metadata interface is done separately from the handling of the content (phylogenies and matrices).
Meta data Meta-data interface uses the Open Archives Initiative Protocol for Metadata Harvesting (OAI-PMH) which has a beginners tutorial. The tutorial provides broad background about the initiative and the basic xml schema, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t find it particularly accessible or get a clear idea of how interacting with the protocol works.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>wrightscape profiling</title>
      <link>/2011/04/24/wrightscape-profiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2011 18:50:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/24/wrightscape-profiling/</guid>
      <description>Optimization at the R level is substantially slower than at the C level:
system.time(wright_test = wright(data,tree,regimes, alpha=ou2@sqrt.alpha^2, sigma=ou2@sigma)) user system elapsed 82.157 0.068 82.346 system.time(ws2 = wrightscape(trait, labrid$tree, regime=labrid$regimes, (ou2@sqrt.alpha)^2, ou2@sigma, theta=ou2@theta[[1]])) iter: 229, llik = 34.750, size = 0.000, par values = 0.000069 2.456353 0.000026 0.225234 0.973002 0.488713 user system elapsed 4.964 0.000 4.971  This is possibly due to repeating the lca matrix calculation. As it&amp;rsquo;s not done in a separate R function yet, the profiler cannot tell us this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Release of constraint in labrids?</title>
      <link>/2011/04/22/release-of-constraint-in-labrids/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2011 18:45:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/22/release-of-constraint-in-labrids/</guid>
      <description>Started writing outline, assembling references
 Reviewed brownie-lite as an alternative model to compare the release-of-constraint, but looks like it will be easier just to modify wrightscape code to keep parameters fixed or global.
 Writing a wrapper to move the likelihood function for wrightscape to up to the R level.
 Figure out which function to pass up: easiest is to build off of fit_model, but just evaluate, don&amp;rsquo;t optimize the likelihood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/04/20/wednesday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2011 22:24:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/20/wednesday-3/</guid>
      <description>Reading  GrrlScientist disagrees with M. Nielsen (and I add my 2c: Open Science might not give you the credit you need to get a job in today&amp;rsquo;s science culture, but hey, in all probability, neither will the traditional strategy, so have fun). Nature says: Too many PhDs Some useful tools for data visualization: particularly want to try:Fusion Tables, Gephi, DataViz Mendeley groups don&amp;rsquo;t display (or share) stars. Can only sort A-Z or by most recent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TreePar: changing rates of evolution</title>
      <link>/2011/04/17/treepar-changing-rates-of-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2011 18:11:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/17/treepar-changing-rates-of-evolution/</guid>
      <description>Review &amp;amp; Comments on Article T. Stadler&amp;rsquo;s article Mammalian phylogeny reveals recent diversification rate shifts (Stadler, 2011) describes her new TreePar package, evaluating shifts in the mammalian phylogeny (from and analyzed by (Bininda-Emonds et. al. 2007)) as an example.
The heart of the article is the calculation of the likelihood for a branching process model with rate shifts at specified times. This approach is dramatically more powerful and less susceptible to spurious conclusions than the earlier approach of looking for a shift in slope in the lineage-through-time (LTT) plot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/04/16/friday-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Apr 2011 20:00:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/16/friday-4/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Arxiv has several articles on the EM-algorithm from J. Statistical Science unknown, unknown. What makes this distinct from applying any traditional optimization routine (Nelder-Mead, simulated annealing, etc) to the likelihood function? Just in that it determines the probability distribution as well as maximum?
 UPDATE ON EM: brief discussion with Graham, Peter, Yaniv on this, now my impression is: Not necessarily get the distribution, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t just generically take a function and minimize it, but may not calculate the likelihood at each step.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TreeBase: exploratory exercises in database-driven phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/2011/04/08/treebase-exploratory-exercises-in-database-driven-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 15:18:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/08/treebase-exploratory-exercises-in-database-driven-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>Taking a look at the TreeBase database for potential project with Gabe &amp;amp; Duncan&amp;rsquo;s Large Data seminar. It would be interesting to get a working knowledge of the database and the API, making large-scale meta-analyses easy. Many studies seem to select taxa based on what they have in their own lab rather than re-use existing phylogenies, not because it is better suited to answering the questions but because it is more familiar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative methods paper status/to-do</title>
      <link>/2011/04/06/comparative-methods-paper-statusto-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 11:56:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/06/comparative-methods-paper-statusto-do/</guid>
      <description>Finished revisions yesterday after rewriting introduction considerably. Following Graham&amp;rsquo;s comment, taking a closer look at aic error along power curves:
&amp;gt; load(&amp;quot;../../pmc/demos/5594495254.Rdat&amp;quot;) &amp;gt; require(pmc) &amp;gt; aic &amp;lt;- 2 &amp;gt; aic_errors_size &amp;lt;- sapply(1:(length(n)), function(i) sum(size[[i]]$null_dist &amp;gt; aic)/size[[i]]$nboot ) &amp;gt; aic_errors_shape &amp;lt;- sapply(1:length(lambda), function(i) sum(shape[[i]]$null_dist &amp;gt; aic)/shape[[i]]$nboot ) &amp;gt; data.frame(n, aic_errors_size) n aic_errors_size 1 10 0.1945 2 20 0.2405 3 40 0.1800 4 60 0.1590 5 80 0.0750 6 100 0.1015 7 150 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution manuscript revisions</title>
      <link>/2011/04/04/phylogenetics-manuscript-revisions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2011 22:48:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/04/phylogenetics-manuscript-revisions/</guid>
      <description>Heard back from Graham Friday on manuscript revisions. Notes on reviewing edits:
 Reconsider title? (Currently: &amp;ldquo;is your phylogeny informative? estimating power in phylogenetic trees&amp;rdquo;). Suggestions from Graham/Brian?
 1000 taxa, 500 taxa seem to break the ouch package inferences.
 Add table for AIC comparisons etc
 Does AIC work better/worse on the lambda = 0 trees?
n[1:3] [1] 10 50 100 aic_errors_size &amp;lt;- sapply(1:(length(n)-2), function(i) sum(size[[i]]$null_dist &amp;gt; aic)/size[[i]]$nboot ) aic_errors_size [1] 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few large data problems in Ecology &amp; Evolution</title>
      <link>/2011/03/31/a-few-large-data-problems-in-ecology-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2011 11:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/31/a-few-large-data-problems-in-ecology-evolution/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve joined a student-led seminar with Gabriel Becker in the Statistics department on dealing with large data, primarily in R. Offered to say a few words about large data problems in my field for a few minutes, so making some notes.
Large dataBases  Genebank: $ &amp;gt; 10^8$ sequences. Phylogenetic inference
 Morphological databases: Specialized databases with semantic tools (Dahdul et. al. 2010)
 NEON observatories data Keller et. al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brian O&#39;Meara discusses new algorithms approaches on Phylo</title>
      <link>/2011/03/30/brian-omeara-discusses-new-abc-approaches-on-phyloseminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2011 20:52:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/30/brian-omeara-discusses-new-abc-approaches-on-phyloseminar/</guid>
      <description>Brian gave an excellent overview of Approximate Bayesian Computing (ABC) and described the TreEvo software he is developing with post-doc Barb Banbury. My notes from the seminar, with my own comments italics and a few added references
Intro / Motivation  Rates of model innovation is rather slow
 Can be impossible to specify in closed form (can&amp;rsquo;t specify median of binomial in closed form)
 Perhaps it would be faster if we didn&amp;rsquo;t have to wait for someone to come up with all the likelihood functions</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Approximate Bayesian Computing (algorithms) methods</title>
      <link>/2011/03/19/approximate-bayesian-computing-abc-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 11:07:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/19/approximate-bayesian-computing-abc-methods/</guid>
      <description>Erick Matsen  asked me about the question at the end of Luke Harmon&amp;rsquo;s phyloseminar critiquing Approximate Bayesian Computing ABC methods. The question wasn&amp;rsquo;t any more specific, though Luke recognized the paper. Searching the literature didn&amp;rsquo;t turn anything up, asking Leo through the MCMC group on Mendeley I think this is the paper:
﻿Robert, C.P. et al. Lack of confidence in ABC model choice. PNAS I, 8(2011). (arXiv)
Seems a more pointed critique to ABC then Templeton&amp;rsquo;s discussion (Templeton, 2010) particularly as the lead author is a critic of Templeton (Berger et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sam&#39;s Practice talk</title>
      <link>/2011/03/18/friday-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 16:37:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/18/friday-2/</guid>
      <description>Notes from: Sam Price&amp;rsquo;s Practice Job Talk for Hull, UK, next week, in Wainwright lab:
 Diversification of mammals predated KT event(Bininda-Emonds et. al. 2007) (also considerably later, but not right after) Ecological shift in wrasses to parrotfishes(Price et. al. 2010). No evidence of elevate rates of evolution. But, scraping parrotfishes do show difference (starting from base of Hipposcarus-Scarus common ancestor). Multiple transitions to/from reef living. 2x faster on coral reefs!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model identifiability in phylogenetic inference GTR&#43;I&#43;G</title>
      <link>/2011/03/15/models-in-phylogenetic-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 13:07:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/15/models-in-phylogenetic-inference/</guid>
      <description>Another phylogenetics paper (Perelman et. al. 2011) using GTR+I+G inspired me to look back over the discussion and objections with this model. This model is the basis of 100s of publications, 40 alone in Sys Bio in 2006(Allman et. al. 2008). There&amp;rsquo;s a decent discussion on Dechronization about the issue. There&amp;rsquo;s some treatment of identifiability on this issue, such as 2001 Sys Bio (Rogers, 2001) which suggests this is possible and a nice paper in Adv.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter&#39;s talk </title>
      <link>/2011/03/14/peters-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 22:29:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/14/peters-talk/</guid>
      <description>Peter spoke in Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s lab meeting about a spatially explicit Moran model, for which he derives Fisher&amp;rsquo;s wave equation and an ancestry process. Here&amp;rsquo;s what he says,
 the general plan is to describe a simple spatial model of adaptation (or, could be of invasion&amp;hellip;); and use it to derive (Fisher&amp;rsquo;s) traveling wave; the corrections that arise if you don&amp;rsquo;t assume the population is infinitely large; and describe how to follow lineages back through the expanding wave.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega evolution Tutorial: behind the scenes difficulties in R packages</title>
      <link>/2011/03/07/bodega-phylogenetics-tutorial-behind-the-scenes-difficulties-in-r-packages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 21:22:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/07/bodega-phylogenetics-tutorial-behind-the-scenes-difficulties-in-r-packages/</guid>
      <description>Just finished my tutorial for comparative methods on continuous traits in R, which I&amp;rsquo;ll be presenting on Wednesday with Justen Whittall. The tutorial is up on the Bodega Phylogenetics Wiki, together with the necessary data files.
Errors that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t happen: a few package bugs in simulation functions Assembling the tutorial exposed a few more frustrations in the R packages. Consider simulating OU with rTraitCont:
## Load the libraries, simulate a tree require(geiger) require(TreeSim) tree &amp;lt;- sim.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is BM nested in OU?  Understanding likelihoods of ouch</title>
      <link>/2011/02/25/is-bm-nested-in-ou-understanding-likelihoods-of-ouch/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2011 20:16:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/25/is-bm-nested-in-ou-understanding-likelihoods-of-ouch/</guid>
      <description>A quick run of the example ouch code given by
 ?bimac  will produce something of a surprise for most users:
require(ouch) data(bimac) tree &amp;lt;- with(bimac,ouchtree(node,ancestor,time/max(time),species)) h1 &amp;lt;- brown(log(bimac[&#39;size&#39;]),tree) h2 &amp;lt;- hansen(log(bimac[&#39;size&#39;]),tree,bimac[&#39;OU.1&#39;],sqrt.alpha=1,sigma=1) c(&amp;quot;BM LogLik&amp;quot;=h1@loglik, &amp;quot;OU LogLik&amp;quot;=h2@loglik) BM LogLik OU LogLik 17.33129 15.69682  These models are supposed to be nested, right? Set OU&amp;rsquo;s $ \alpha $ parameter to zero and you get BM, so how does it manage to do worse in log likelihood?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylo: Luke Harmon</title>
      <link>/2011/02/25/phyloseminar-luke-harmon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2011 14:36:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/25/phyloseminar-luke-harmon/</guid>
      <description>My notes on Luke Harmon&amp;rsquo;s excellent talk on Phyloseminar this morning. See the recording of Luke&amp;rsquo;s actual talk to know what he said, below are my thoughts and notes to myself having watched the talk.
Luke summarizes his goal rather nicely as:
 Analyzing the data that people actually have to answer the questions they actually want to know
 For him, this focuses on incomplete trees and non-Brownian models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega evolution Workshop: Continuous Characters R session planning</title>
      <link>/2011/02/19/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-continuous-characters-r-session-planning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 03:45:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/19/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-continuous-characters-r-session-planning/</guid>
      <description>Preparing for the Bodega Phylogenetics workshop. I&amp;rsquo;ll be covering the R tutorial followingJusten Whittall&amp;rsquo;s introduction to continuous characters:
 In my intro lecture i will discuss Felsenstein 1985 (including a little phylo signal), then follow with some alternatives (including the OU model). I can also discuss the tree transformations ala Pagel&amp;rsquo;s kappa, delta, etc. and mention multivariate approaches to detecting correlated characters in a phylogenetic context.
 I&amp;rsquo;m toying with the idea of a brief (~1hr) phylogenetic signal / model inference exercise:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/02/18/friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2011 15:21:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/18/friday/</guid>
      <description>Spoke with Prof. Jim Carey about getting Data Mangement Workshop videocast with Cametasia (and possibly Adobe Connect for live streaming). Jim has worked with Entomology seminar series, and UCTV on videocasting seminars, see his recent PLoS Biology paper Carey et. al. 2010.  Spoke with Marissa about some of the resources at NCEAS. Learned a bit about data standards from FGDC and NBII. Working on manuscript revisions (phylogenetics) Writing (warning signals) Revised Weds post, reviewing context for Goldman 1993 Goldman, 1993 relative to original simulation-based parametric bootstrap of Cox&amp;rsquo;s statistic as illustrated in (McLachlan, 1987) in mixture models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/02/17/thursday-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2011 23:55:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/17/thursday-4/</guid>
      <description>Mostly working on manuscript revisions throughout this week. Haven&amp;rsquo;t really learned to integrate this workflow into the notebook. In some ways it makes more sense not to, as it interrupts the flow of the research description. But then it looks like I&amp;rsquo;m not doing anything when I have nothing meaningful in the entry. Perhaps I should just put a heading saying &amp;ldquo;Writing.&amp;rdquo;
Morning&amp;rsquo;s reading: Reproducible Research  Victoria Stodden highlights the Journal of Biostatistics approach to Reproducible Research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/02/14/monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2011 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/14/monday/</guid>
      <description>Excellent CPB visiting weekend with perspective students Thurs evening - Sunday morning. Hosting students, etc doesn&amp;rsquo;t make for much of a research entry Friday. Catching up with many things today.
 ESA registration. Topics, Abstract
 Checking in with Alan
 Data workshop: create &amp;amp; post advertisement, map out subject areas
 Reading: Syst Bio issue
 Updated pubmed author alerts
 Checking in with Peter &amp;amp; Graham on revisions</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/02/10/thursday-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2011 17:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/10/thursday-2/</guid>
      <description>Organizing for Future of Data workshop. Confirming time/room booking, etc. Science makes open access a special issue on Dealing with Data  Hosting visiting prospective CPB student, scheduling events. Going over edits questions with Peter R. on phylogenetics manuscript. Editing/pruning plugins &amp;ndash; starting to choke my Wordpress hosting. Folks at DreamHost have been very helpful, hopefully no key plugins are off. Apparently deactivating doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily prevent plugin from contributing to the memory load.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetic Monte Carlo for the Laser package</title>
      <link>/2011/02/09/phylogenetic-monte-carlo-for-the-laser-package/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2011 18:17:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/09/phylogenetic-monte-carlo-for-the-laser-package/</guid>
      <description>Laser simulations: First ensuring example has expected behaviour, can in general get the expected likelihood differences between fits of Yule and birth-death models.
Estimated models had been appearing identical in the runs (on left), seems to have been a bug. Distributions appear roughly the same across different tree sizes and values of death rate. General pattern of likelihood tests is reminiscent of the lambda models: high variability in likelihood ratios under bd simulations relative to the pure-birth simulations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes during revisions on phylogenetics manuscript</title>
      <link>/2011/02/08/notes-during-revisions-on-phylogenetics-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2011 13:47:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/08/notes-during-revisions-on-phylogenetics-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>I have made the revisions to attempt to address Graham&amp;rsquo;s annotations and Peter&amp;rsquo;s comments. (revisions are also up on the git repo.) I have added a brief section introducing the models immediately after the introduction. I also rewrote more of the PMC method to include definitions of p and power in the context of comparing model likelihood ratios. I moved the AIC section up before I talk about the other comparisons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>more Phylogenetic signal metrics &amp; Brownie comparison</title>
      <link>/2011/01/31/more-phylogenetic-signal-metrics-brownie-comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 16:31:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/31/more-phylogenetic-signal-metrics-brownie-comparison/</guid>
      <description>Blomberg&amp;rsquo;s K estimates on trees of different sizes. Estimates differ across the distribution of possible data generated by BM model and generated from white noise. In principle, the K statistic should be able to distinguish between data simulated between these two. Of course, the ability to do this depends on the size and structure of the phylogenetic tree &amp;ndash; Blomberg&amp;rsquo;s K is not an estimate of whether the phylogeny is sufficiently structured as to be informative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Bokma 2010: evolution in drifts and jumps</title>
      <link>/2011/01/31/notes-on-bokma-2010-evolution-in-drifts-and-jumps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 12:15:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/31/notes-on-bokma-2010-evolution-in-drifts-and-jumps/</guid>
      <description>Bokma 2010 asks if there is an analytic expression for the likelihood in the evolutionary model he describes.
The trait value of the process is determined by two things &amp;ndash; a Brownian motion random walk (diffusion) with rate parameter $ s_a^2$ and speciation events. Under a speciation event, the trait jumps to a new value that differs from it&amp;rsquo;s parent&amp;rsquo;s by some amount chosen from zero-mean normal distribution with variance $ s_c^2$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetic Signal metrics</title>
      <link>/2011/01/28/phylogenetic-signal-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2011 17:52:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/28/phylogenetic-signal-metrics/</guid>
      <description>Blomberg&amp;rsquo;s K distribution under data simulated from BM on the geospiza tree (red) compared to simulating independent random draws from the Normal distribution.
Would be good to compare with differing size trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Felsenstein (web) seminar</title>
      <link>/2011/01/24/felsenstein-web-seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2011 11:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/24/felsenstein-web-seminar/</guid>
      <description>Joe Felsenstein on phyloseminar (watch here). This morning. [ref]These are my own notes as taken during the seminar and may not accurately reflect everything. I merely confirm with the speaker that my notes are publicly visible. My own commentary/thoughts indicated in square brackets.[/ref] Discusses bridging population genetics &amp;amp; comparative methods: where does covariation in traits across a phylogeny come from?
Morphometrics Using morphometrics (digitized landmarks [though now we can do spherical harmonics, CT scans, etc]) to evolve on a phylogeny under BM rather than use that data to infer phylogeny.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shape as well as size influence power of phylogeny</title>
      <link>/2011/01/21/shape-as-well-as-size-influence-power-of-phylogeny/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2011 17:34:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/21/shape-as-well-as-size-influence-power-of-phylogeny/</guid>
      <description>Finished the runs comparing the power to detect different strengths of selection using different size phylogenetic trees all generated under pure-birth process simulation, and then under trees of the same size but gradually lengthening the tips, (or rather shortening everything but the tips) using the lambda transformation, which puts the informative differences deep in the past where they are less reflected in the stationary state. Bure-birth (also the constant rate birth-death) trees on the other hand are particularly twiggy and quite informative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating phylogenetic signal (lambda) on large trees</title>
      <link>/2011/01/20/estimating-phylogenetic-signal-lambda-on-large-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 19:21:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/20/estimating-phylogenetic-signal-lambda-on-large-trees/</guid>
      <description>Used a simulated tree of 600 taxa to show that lambda distribution continues to improve with larger taxa. Recall the results with 13 taxa and with 23 taxa:
[flickr size=&amp;ldquo;small&amp;rdquo; float=&amp;ldquo;left&amp;rdquo;]5370016511 [/flickr]
[flickr size=&amp;ldquo;small&amp;rdquo; float=&amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo;]5370635360 [/flickr]
compare to 281 taxa and then 600 taxa:
[flickr size=&amp;ldquo;small&amp;rdquo; float=&amp;ldquo;left&amp;rdquo;]5310150538 [/flickr]
By 281 taxa the distribution is at least centered on the true value. The width of that distribution gets somewhat tighter with more taxa, though the increase is marginal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution- wrightscape</title>
      <link>/2011/01/11/phylogenetics-wrightscape/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2011 15:38:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/11/phylogenetics-wrightscape/</guid>
      <description>Interesting meeting with Peter to discuss a variety of issues in comparative phylogenetics. Short notes:
 Transforming data, log data
 Trends in directions in convergent traits
 multivariate inference
 Manuscript
  Wrightscape First have to test PMC to make sure it works with OUCH classes. Also adding PMC-required wrappers for wrightscape. Ended up modifying PMC to handle the case of simulate functions that return replicates, like these packages do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylo Monte Carlo for diversification rates</title>
      <link>/2011/01/09/phylo-monte-carlo-for-diversification-rates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2011 13:28:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/09/phylo-monte-carlo-for-diversification-rates/</guid>
      <description>Writing function wrappers for geiger functions to perform Phylogenetic Monte Carlo. Any object that has methods defined for update.objecttype (object, data) and simulate.objecttype(data), and loglik.object(object) should be able to use the montecarlotest() function. OUCH almost does this but not quite, since the datatype returned by &amp;lsquo;simulate&amp;rsquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t match that needed by &amp;lsquo;update&amp;rsquo;. OUCH also uses S4 class styles.
Wrote wrappers for ouch functions such that the ouch models will work with the same montecarlotest() code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finishing up my #SICB Presentation</title>
      <link>/2011/01/02/finishing-up-my-sicb-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2011 21:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/02/finishing-up-my-sicb-presentation/</guid>
      <description>Finished up my SICB presentation tweaks, slides now up on slideshare, flying off to the conference tomorrow. Created this in OpenOffice, started adding animations and then decided it would be more reliable to just duplicate slides to have parts appear (really just for the explanation of the likelihood ratio distributions under each model). Next time think I&amp;rsquo;ll stick with my usual inkscape slides tied together with latex beamer, the lack of vector images in this one is not ideal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative evolution: Is the data informative?</title>
      <link>/2010/12/31/comparative-phylogenetics-is-the-data-informative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2010 21:22:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/31/comparative-phylogenetics-is-the-data-informative/</guid>
      <description>Working on my SICB talk, going a little further into the example of fitting the lambda model on the Anoles data to illustrate the ways in which we may lack sufficient data for the question.
 The dataset may not contain adequate signal of the parameter / phenomenon in question
 The dataset may not be adequately large
  Anoles data set (23 taxa):
This first image shows the distribution of lambda values estimated from many datasets all simulated under a lambda = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DoE renewal and a year in review</title>
      <link>/2010/12/24/doe-renewal-and-a-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2010 03:24:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/24/doe-renewal-and-a-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>This time of year I have to file my renewal for my DOE Fellowship, including a statement of accomplishments and a summary of the computational aspects of my work. Seemed like a good idea to jot these down in my notebook as well:
synopsis of accomplishments over the year: In January I passed my qualifying exam, advancing to candidacy where my dissertation remains my only requirement. In March I attended the phylogenetics workshop in Bodega Bay, an internationally known week-long training program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sun: Visualizing my coding over the past year</title>
      <link>/2010/12/20/sun-visualizing-my-coding-over-the-past-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2010 00:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/20/sun-visualizing-my-coding-over-the-past-year/</guid>
      <description>Not really working today, as holidays approach, but came across the Gource toolkit for creating video visualization from git development (inspired by the Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s example). So in the spirit of year-in-review reflections, here&amp;rsquo;s my development from the past year (just for the phylogenetic statistics work).
Quality is a little too poor to read file names, more entertaining than practical. Other user icons appear in December corresponding with my move to running the code from Amazon cloud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thurs: writing section on comparing to AIC</title>
      <link>/2010/12/16/thurs-writing-section-on-comparing-to-aic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2010 22:50:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/16/thurs-writing-section-on-comparing-to-aic/</guid>
      <description>Phylogenetics writing still continues.
AIC Error rates
Choosing by having &amp;lt; 5% probability of rejecting the simpler model when it is true.
Choosing the equal-likelihood division:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Example sets &amp; more EC2</title>
      <link>/2010/12/15/weds-example-sets-more-ec2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2010 16:24:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/15/weds-example-sets-more-ec2/</guid>
      <description>A bit delayed from having to rerun analyses on EC2 (still learning&amp;hellip;) More to run today (lambda trials for Anoles &amp;ndash; should really recode this in C!).
Trying to decide if its best to start off with the power curves and work backwards or build up from the basics. Probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter too much which. Also figuring out which examples to present first:
Where the painted trees are the following:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: evolution thoughts while writing...</title>
      <link>/2010/12/14/tues-phylogenetics-thoughts-while-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2010 17:06:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/14/tues-phylogenetics-thoughts-while-writing/</guid>
      <description>Again spending most of the day writing. (Maybe) processing some ideas in writing by writing in my notebook as I make my edits.
Ideas I&amp;rsquo;m trying to get across in today&amp;rsquo;s edits Parameter estimation is more demanding of the data than model choice. Knowing if a value is different from zero is easier than knowing what it is.
Code updates to-do  Need to add S3 wrapper functions for ouch so both can call montecarlotest() in the pmc package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/12/13/back-to-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 10:56:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/13/back-to-writing/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Practice SICB Presentation</title>
      <link>/2010/12/08/practice-sicb-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2010 22:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/08/practice-sicb-presentation/</guid>
      <description>Gave my practice talk for Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology in Wainwright lab this afternoon, after (not quite) finishing the presentation. Trying to figure out the best way to introduce these ideas to a broad audience (same challenge as with the manuscript).
Talk storyboard:
Looking at other talks in my session: Macroevolution I - Methods and Character Evolution, looks like a reasonably sophisticated group.
Good feedback from the Wainwright Lab:  Emphasize: Currently we worry that we don&amp;rsquo;t have the right models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping out SICB Presentation: Is your phylogeny informative?</title>
      <link>/2010/12/07/mapping-out-sicb-presentation-is-your-phylogeny-informative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2010 22:42:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/07/mapping-out-sicb-presentation-is-your-phylogeny-informative/</guid>
      <description>Assembling material/outline for my SICB presentation in January, will be giving a practice talk in the Wainwright lab on Wednesday. 15 minute presentation with 5 minutes for questions.
 Designing presentation in &amp;ldquo;storyboard&amp;rdquo; format in Inkscape. Will figure out if I convert to slides or not.
 Simulations under the Anoles dataset to show posterior distributions of lambda. Exploring the connection between the likelihood of a parameter under each model to that of the distributions of the likelihood ratio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>follow up from Fri discussions: Revisiting post-predictive evaluation</title>
      <link>/2010/12/06/follow-up-from-fri-discussions-revisiting-post-predictive-evaluation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2010 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/06/follow-up-from-fri-discussions-revisiting-post-predictive-evaluation/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago, a seminar prompted me to take a closer look at a particular post-predictive evaluation technique applied reasonably often in our recent literature,see earlier entry. I think by phrasing the approach more concisely and precisely it will be clear what the difficulty is.
As usual, we consider some data $ \vec X$ and a set of $ N$ models specified by parameters, $ \lbrace \vec \theta_1, \vec \theta_2, \vec \ldots \theta_N\rbrace $, then we can express the likelihood of the model as the probability of the data under the given model and parameter values:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPB : David Collar</title>
      <link>/2010/12/01/cpb-seminar-david-collar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2010 00:58:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/01/cpb-seminar-david-collar/</guid>
      <description>Identifying ecological constraint on morph and function using phylogenies. 2007 CPB grad, losos post doc, now postdoc w Rita.
Indep origin of &amp;lsquo;bass&amp;rsquo; cranial morph. Also unique patterns- stonefish. Phylo comparative methods to address why and how. Three types of factors on morphology: ecological, time!, intrinsic (genetic, behavior) constraints. Outline:
I. determinants of morph diversification.
II. Complex traits.
I. Diversification rate vary by habitat? (Dragon lizards- diverse morph, diverse habitat). Reconstruct history of habitat use (4 types), (assign discrete traits) then stoch character maps to reconstruct (paint) tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Challenges in estimating phylogenetic signal</title>
      <link>/2010/11/29/challenges-in-estimating-phylogenetic-signal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 07:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/29/challenges-in-estimating-phylogenetic-signal/</guid>
      <description>Uncertainty in estimate of lambda illustrated by simulating 1000 data sets on the Geopsiza tree under a model with lambda = 0.62. Shows the high uncertainty in estimating lambda at all, despite the power in the estimate at this value.
(Code)
Will fill this out further later. Will be interesting to compare at different base values of lambda used for the simulation.
Have updated the codbase to provide bootstraps of parameters as part of the monte carlo output.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in simple tests</title>
      <link>/2010/11/22/power-in-simple-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2010 08:00:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/22/power-in-simple-tests/</guid>
      <description>Exploring power in simple tree models. With the smaller tree from the _geospiza _dataset, (14 tips, left) is less than yesterday&amp;rsquo;s in the bimaculus Anoles (with 23 tips, right)
(code)
Also wrote the OUCH-based wrapper function to fit tree transformation parameters. Unfortunately it currently transforms from ape to ouch format repeatedly (in order to use ape&amp;rsquo;s tree transforms, need to write native ouch-format transforms), so it may not be any faster.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two questions</title>
      <link>/2010/11/21/two-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 21:53:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/21/two-questions/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about a few elements of the Monte Carlo approach that seem to be particularly subtle in interpretation. Thought I&amp;rsquo;d write them out here as a separate examples to help think through them. Thoughts?
Question 1 Should the Monte Carlo simulations use the maximum likelihood test and null model estimated from the data (as in McLachlan 1987, Goldman 1993, Huelsenbeck 1996) or draw from the distribution of model parameters for each simulation?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sat: evolution -- porting tree transformations to OUCH?</title>
      <link>/2010/11/20/sat-phylogenetics-porting-tree-transformations-to-ouch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2010 23:36:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/20/sat-phylogenetics-porting-tree-transformations-to-ouch/</guid>
      <description>The overnight runs yesterday using the geiger models bm and lambda on the (transformed) Anoles dataset don&amp;rsquo;t seem to converge, spooling jobs that continue running even when R exits &amp;ndash; probably that same problem in ape somewhere that was fixed by writing the tree out to Nexus and re-reading it, a very strange and subtle bug. Will try this and restart the runs. 
Ordered as: bm_v_lambda_origdata.png, delta_v_lambda.png, bm_v_lambda.png (data simulated under OU), each with 100 replicates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fri: extending Geiger to Monte Carlo method</title>
      <link>/2010/11/19/fri-extending-geiger-to-monte-carlo-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2010 19:51:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/19/fri-extending-geiger-to-monte-carlo-method/</guid>
      <description>Completing my extension of geiger into object oriented design whereby I can easily apply the Monte Carlo approach to test fits using function calls to model fits such as update() and simulate(). A quick convenient example: AIC would prefer (though not by munch) the delta transform model over the Brownian motion model; a conclusion not supported by the Monte Carlo test, which suggests there is not enough power to choose between these models:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thurs: evolution likelihood</title>
      <link>/2010/11/18/thurs-phylogenetics-likelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 20:05:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/18/thurs-phylogenetics-likelihood/</guid>
      <description>Back to writing for today. Working on discussion of non-nested models. Looking at the reverse comparison, can get the reverse p value. The case of OU.3 vs the OU.4 model doesn&amp;rsquo;t show either test to be significant at the 95\% confidence level,but the case of OU.3 vs OU.15 (lets every species in the top two clades be unique) does:
The reverse p value easily rejects this silly OU.15 model, though AIC vastly prefers it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds</title>
      <link>/2010/11/18/weds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2010 08:06:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/18/weds/</guid>
      <description>Great discussion in Monte Carlo Seminar with Rannala on the two rate estimation papers. See in-text notes, but focus on mechanisms of speciation and extinction as intrinsic (lineage specific) or extrinsic (perhaps spatially specific or global).
Calculation of the likelihood function for the rates seems straight forward. Start by imaging the pure-birth model, simply allow branch lengths as draws from the exponential distribution of parameter lambda. Allowing extinction: probability a lineage speciates (as before) and then survives to present day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution today:  Discussion groups, writing, etc</title>
      <link>/2010/11/15/phylogenetics-today-discussion-groups-writing-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 22:37:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/15/phylogenetics-today-discussion-groups-writing-etc/</guid>
      <description>Interesting discussion of a Lenski paper in Wainwright&amp;rsquo;s 270.
Barrick, J.E. et al. Genome evolution and adaptation in a long-term experiment with Escherichia coli. Nature 461, 1243-7(2009).
Seems to focus on surprise of continuing linear rate of increase in beneficial mutations, though statistics don&amp;rsquo;t seem to confirm. Curious about uncertainty in assay of fitness estimates (seem to go down at times, but surely not fixing deleterious mutations). General difficulties in setup of exponential growth with applications of classic constant population size, but maybe we&amp;rsquo;re all missing something.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: Post-predictive verification exploration; writing and figures</title>
      <link>/2010/11/11/thursday-post-predictive-verification-exploration-writing-and-figures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 20:47:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/11/thursday-post-predictive-verification-exploration-writing-and-figures/</guid>
      <description>On Post-predictive Verification Considering the kind of post-predictive verification I was discussing with Dan on Tuesday. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the simple birth-death branching process. Starting from the master equation, the linearity gives us an accurate model as a Gaussian process where the systematic van Kampen expansion gives us the Fokker Planck equation whose solution is completely specified by its first two moments:
[latex] \frac{dN}{dt} = (\lambda - \mu) N \</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution statistics </title>
      <link>/2010/11/11/phylogenetics-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 08:13:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/11/phylogenetics-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the best way for representing the Monte Carlo Likelihood approach visually, including comparison power and comparison to AIC.
Blue line is AIC, dotted red line is real data. Red line to the right of blue line indicates test model is rejecting the null model by AIC score. Solid distribution are likelihood ratios simulated under null, dotted are simulated under test.
The p-value is the integral of the null distribution lying right of the observed likelihood ratio in the real data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday - SDEs then back to phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/2010/11/10/tuesday-sdes-then-back-to-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2010 19:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/10/tuesday-sdes-then-back-to-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>Nice meeting with Sebastian this morning, reviewed my spectral approach problem (see anything in Stochastic Population Dynamics / warning signals in the past week) and the multivariate SDE problem Peter posed Oct 30th. No solutions yet but some ideas to get started.
With regards the SDE problem, note that it reduces to:
$$ dX_1 = B_2 d B_1 $$
and note also that if this were $$ dX_1 = B_1 d B_1 $$ this would be a classic exercise in intro SDEs we can look up in Oksendal,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday and some phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/2010/11/08/monday-and-some-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 22:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/08/monday-and-some-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>Working on paper revisions. Added a separate demo file just for generating the figures and analysis used in the manuscript, called likelihood_manuscript.R Need to clean and reorganize the package files and demos.
Added full species names and islands to the tip labels of the tree. Adjusting which example paintings/regimes to include, currently focusing on the original OU.LP model (now calling it OU.3 following Brian&amp;rsquo;s recommendation for simplicity), OU.4, (originally OU.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: Evolution reading, writing</title>
      <link>/2010/11/05/friday-evolution-reading-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 18:21:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/05/friday-evolution-reading-writing/</guid>
      <description>Read through the article for Monday&amp;rsquo;s PBG270, a 2009 Nature paper from the Plotkin lab on mutational robustness and the rate of evolution. They consider an interesting little setup. Start with a Moran model (individual born, may mutate, choses who to replace at random), but allow the following mutational structure (landscape). Of P possible genotypes, each can only move to one of K neighbors by a single mutation. Call the genotype(s) of optimal fitness C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short note: Trait diversification rates controlled by other traits</title>
      <link>/2010/10/30/short-note-trait-diversification-rates-controlled-by-other-traits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/30/short-note-trait-diversification-rates-controlled-by-other-traits/</guid>
      <description>Peter posed an interesting question to me this afternoon: can we infer a model in which the rate of evolution in one trait (say, its Brownian diversification rate parameter) depends on the value of another trait (say, linearly and assume the other trait depends on Brownian motion). Without all those assumptions we write this generally as:
$$ dX_t = f_x(X_t, Y_t) dt + \sigma_x(X_t, Y_t) d W_t $$ $$ dY_t = f_y(Y_t) dt + \sigma_y(Y_t) d W_t $$ (subscripts do not imply derivatives in my notation)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status update</title>
      <link>/2010/10/15/status-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/15/status-update/</guid>
      <description>Actually out of town this day, but draft off to co-authors, will review Friday. meanwhile time to get back to some warning signals work, will be in other notebook for rest of the week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing continues</title>
      <link>/2010/10/14/writing-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/14/writing-continues/</guid>
      <description>Deleting large sections is a great way to spur better writing. Revised organization substantially, discussion somewhat loose still. But basic framework all in place. draft off to Peter and Graham!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2010/10/13/wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/13/wednesday/</guid>
      <description>Monte Carlo  Reading Sanderson&amp;rsquo;s nonparametric rate smoothing and semi-parametric r8s papers in Monte Carlo with Rannala. Comments on articles in text, but great discussion today, particularly Bruce&amp;rsquo;s take on this style of approach.   Sanderson, M.J. Estimating absolute rates of molecular evolution and divergence times: a penalized likelihood approach. Molecular biology and evolution 19, 101-9(2002). Sanderson, M.J. A Nonparametric Approach of Rate Constancy to Estimating Divergence Times in the Absence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>a day of writing</title>
      <link>/2010/10/12/a-day-of-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/12/a-day-of-writing/</guid>
      <description>Figuring out the best way to present the critique of AIC, introduction to the method, introduction to the power test. Seeking inspiration from Huelsenbeck 1996 and digging farther back into the literature:

 Cox, D.R. Further results on tests of separate families of hypotheses. Journal of the Royal Stastical Society 24, 406-424(1962). Cox, D.R. Tests of Seperate Families of Hypotheses. Proceedings of the 4th Berkeley Symposium, University of California Press 105 - 123(1961).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Still writing</title>
      <link>/2010/10/11/still-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/11/still-writing/</guid>
      <description>Ah, back after being in bed almost a week with flu. Back to writing manuscript, reworking the presentation of the actual method. Much of the day caught up in Watson&amp;rsquo;s practice orals (applying computational mechanics to inhibitory neuron circuits), checking in with Yun on his orals and then GTC. too many delays, hope I feel fully better soon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LR Manuscript</title>
      <link>/2010/10/05/lr-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/05/lr-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Still writing. Working on the comparisons to AIC section. Things to think about adding: Explicitly show p values on bootstrap What are we calling this thing anyway? After Hulsenbeck &amp;amp; Bull, 1996: ``likelihood heterogeneity test All-different seems to have some stability/convergence problems, perhaps a less aggressive example would be better? &amp;ndash;Carl Boettiger 19:46, 5 October 2010 (EDT) Stability issues resulted from different fitting methods in initial fit vs. bootstraps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2010/10/04/monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/04/monday/</guid>
      <description>7:30 &amp;ndash; 8:30 Read ﻿article for Wainwright&amp;rsquo;s 270:  Streisfeld, M.a. &amp;amp; Rausher, M.D. Population Genetics, Pleiotropy, and the Preferential Fixation of Mutations During Adaptive Evolution. Evolution no-no(2010).doi:10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01128.x
Interesting approach, methods description a little light and both prediction and interpretation of pattern of mutations in coding, cis-reg, and transcription factor sites seems a little loose. Detailed notes on article in Mendeley. More comments after the discussion section at 1pm today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Ratio Paper</title>
      <link>/2010/10/03/likelihood-ratio-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/03/likelihood-ratio-paper/</guid>
      <description>Higher resolution power plot for Anoles tree Figure (below right) shows power for increasing alpha in the Anoles tree. The vertical line shows the estimated value of alpha for the body-size data &amp;ndash; unlikely that a tree of this size can detect selection that is this weak even if it were present. Consequently, this fit should not be taken as evidence that BM is a better fit than the OU, but rather that the data is insufficient to inform this analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics Updates</title>
      <link>/2010/09/30/adaptive-dynamics-updates/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/30/adaptive-dynamics-updates/</guid>
      <description>The numerical coexistence time simulations are still running, (Server rest brought down these runs two weeks ago, and they take a few weeks to do all the replicates) meanwhile here are the rest of the analytic set (and one simulation that finished). See code for parameters etc. (Below in frame)


EVE Seminar: Brad Shaffer A rather good talk on the California Tiger salamander, emphasizing intersection of ecological and evolutionary investigation in a conservation, management-oriented context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/09/15/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/15/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio/phylogenetic signal manuscript.

scrap notes from more literature combing  Cheverud 1985 autocorellational model, extended by Gittlman &amp;amp; Kot 1990 Grafen 89, Pagen &amp;amp; Harvey 89 extending PIC to polytomies Harvey &amp;amp; Mace 82, Harvey &amp;amp; Clutton Brock 85 taxonomic rather than phylogenetic  From Blomberg et al: &amp;ldquo;The three best-justified phylogenetically based statistical methods can all be applied with a star phylogeny, in which case they yield results that are exactly the same as a conventional analysis (phylogenetically independent contrasts: Felsenstein 1985; generalized least squares: Grafen 1989; Martins and Hansen 1997; Garland and Ives 2000; Rohlf 2001; Monte Carlo simulations: Martins and Garland 1991; Garland et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/09/14/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/14/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio/phylogenetic signal manuscript</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/09/13/peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/13/peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>SICB conference  Abstract &amp;ndash; sent   Phylogenetic comparative methods have become all but ubiquitous in only a few decades, forcing us to reconsider if information from a phylogenetic tree can justify the results. Existing approaches to this question have been inadequate and do not scale with tree size or the ability to resolve branches. For instance, selection between phylogenetic models typically based on information criteria fails to adequately reflect this uncertainty, and can lead to preference for arbitrarily complicated models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting with Sam</title>
      <link>/2010/09/07/meeting-with-sam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/07/meeting-with-sam/</guid>
      <description>Discussing elements of likelihood ratio manuscript and review results from release of constraint data. Figure out what to include in one manuscript, what order to present elements in, and what examples are necessary.
 Phylogenetic Signal introduction. Need for examples? A good example where phylogenetically independent contrasts is misleading, but lambda/K definition of phylogenetic signal is also misleading. Power in phylogenetic tree:  Likelihood ratio and model choice: Monte Carlo LR approach, support in the literature http://openwetware.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution Research Abstract</title>
      <link>/2010/09/04/hello-world-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2010 16:51:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/04/hello-world-2/</guid>
      <description>Comparative methods in evolutionary biology use phylogenetic trees to explore the origins and maintenance of biodiversity. I develop methods to extend the kinds of questions we can ask and also to test the statistical limits of our ability to make evolutionary inferences through such a periscope into the past. I am particularly interested in detecting evolutionary regime shifts &amp;ndash; locations in evolutionary history where the governing rules or parameters shift suddenly &amp;ndash; as well as more general questions of model choice, informativeness &amp;amp; identifiability in phylogenetic inference.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/2010/09/01/entry-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/01/entry-title/</guid>
      <description>Automated scripts for image uploads. Tag-based generation of a slideshow:


Running the script:
 ./flickr_slideshow *.png  Creates the html code that can be embedded into the notebook for a slideshow those images. Images only get the date-time tag as a unique id.


This one uses the mediawiki plugin. More formatting options could be incorporated of course. (Creates the thumbnail images down the right-hand side).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2010/08/31/tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/31/tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Much of today&amp;rsquo;s activity included in yesterday&amp;rsquo;s.
Recording Reading Still looking for a good way to capture time snapshots of what I&amp;rsquo;ve read. Perhaps the Mendeley API will have a good solution. Here I try twapper-keeper to create an rss of my tweets on a given day, and the google api, but not very ideal solutions. Checked a variety of ways to filter rss feeds by date so that it would just show the current ones, none seem to manage this though.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/08/30/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/30/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Simulation Results (code)  Analytics (Analytics code)
Notebooks and files Looking at a better way to get figures into my online notebook. I often run simulations that generate figures which I look at, make some adjustments to the code based on the figure, and then delete or overwrite the figure without uploading it to my notebook, because it isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;finished&amp;rdquo; and uploading takes a lot of clicks, particularly when the code generates 36 figures in a run.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood ratio ToDo</title>
      <link>/2010/08/27/likelihood-ratio-todo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/27/likelihood-ratio-todo/</guid>
      <description>Inclusion of power figure, discussion of power. (include comparison to smaller trees?)  Code ToDo  Fix parallelization &amp;ndash; lower-level parallelization in LR_boot function seems to have high memory and processing overhead. Parallelize over alpha only. Funny that sfSapply at lower level conflicts when inside an upper-level sfSapply call? Can the lower level be put into sequential mode? Requires more experimenting, probably with simple test functions.
 Create package around power analysis, including ability to test bootstraps</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Ratio Paper- Power in Trees</title>
      <link>/2010/08/26/likelihood-ratio-paper--power-in-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/26/likelihood-ratio-paper--power-in-trees/</guid>
      <description>Power in Trees tests (Results from single OU simulation per alpha, run yesterday) 2000 replicates gives a cleaner picture of the critical alpha, though with low alpha values the estimates of p are quite variable. Also more variable on the smaller trees. Even arbitrarily large alpha aren&amp;rsquo;t significant on the 5-taxa primate tree. On the small geospiza tree (13 taxa) from the geiger package we find:
0.5735 0.29 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Ratio Manuscript</title>
      <link>/2010/08/25/likelihood-ratio-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/25/likelihood-ratio-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Graham &amp;amp; Peter Meeting Some comments on Neyman Pearson and approaches &amp;gt; In the phylogenetics world, Huelsenbeck has a paper doing this: &amp;ldquo; A Likelihood Ratio Test to Detect Conflicting Phylogenetic Signal&amp;rdquo; and there&amp;rsquo;s a good introduction to the paper.
This is great, nice to know there&amp;rsquo;s a basis for it.
&amp;gt; I see that in the paper John references, &amp;ldquo; Statistical tests of models of DNA substitution &amp;ldquo;, they call what you&amp;rsquo;re doing &amp;ldquo;Monte Carlo&amp;rdquo;, and refers to some sort of resampling-the-data equivalent as the bootstrap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/08/19/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/19/writing/</guid>
      <description>revising likelihood ratio manuscript &amp;ndash; added a section of conceptual examples to link the model choice and phylogenetic signal sections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/08/13/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/13/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Wrote the code for a better interface to simulate coexistence times and creating contour plots from the results.  see code</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/08/12/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/12/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Created plotting functions for:   waiting time distribution by phase, (cumulative and difference), distribution of number of failures before invasion of dimophism can occur and after it has occurred (indicating if mutational rate is more limiting or mutational step size (selection gradient). Adding to the pairwise invasibility plot the locations where dimorphism collapses, color coded by the time of collapse.  Exploring branching time distributions in different regimes by phase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/08/11/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/11/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Adding demos directory for the simulations to create the figures in User:Carl Boettiger/Notebook/Comparative Phylogenetics/2010/05/03 and User:Carl Boettiger/Notebook/Comparative Phylogenetics/2010/05/04 Updating the contour plot figure as per suggestions by Rupert and Ulf:  Branching times, original figure
 use more points for the simulation, and don&amp;rsquo;t put them on a regular grid, but maybe draw them from a uniform distribution, so as not to create spurious impressions of symmetry. You could then maybe also use the tripack package to draw colored Voronoi cells instead of same-sized symbols.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood ratio update</title>
      <link>/2010/08/10/likelihood-ratio-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/10/likelihood-ratio-update/</guid>
      <description>Sent drafts of Likelihood ratio paper to Peter Wainwright (Sunday 08/08) and Graham Coop (Monday 08/09)  Wrightscape  Sent Peter more information on the release of constraint results in the Labrid system. Starting wrightscape manuscript.  Changes to wrightscape.R  added a tree plotting function to the wrighttree class. labels on parameter bootstrap distributions for labrids in last week&amp;rsquo;s entry reversed wrasses and parrotfish. I&amp;rsquo;ve updated the software so that the plotting function takes care of the labeling automatically (when these were made it had to be added manually, while the automation of the data conversions and the painting by clade reversed the label assignments).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Batch Data</title>
      <link>/2010/08/05/batch-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/05/batch-data/</guid>
      <description>Some of the nexus files don&amp;rsquo;t seem to read into R. Opening and saving the file in figtree solves this.  Data Sets Labrid traits &amp;ndash;Carl Boettiger 00:52, 11 August 2010 (EDT) Note: labels on parameter bootstrap distributions have reversed wrasses and parrotfish. I&amp;rsquo;ve updated the software so that the plotting function takes care of the labeling automatically (when these were made it had to be added manually, while the automation of the data conversions and the painting by clade reversed the label assignments).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Format functions</title>
      <link>/2010/08/04/data-format-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/04/data-format-functions/</guid>
      <description>Spent much of the day trying to code an intelligent data-preprocessing function. Seems to mostly be working now, see github for details. Testing on a variety of datasets.
 Currently the function assumes paintings can be specified by common ancestors of a set of tips, assumes non-overlapping clades. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t error-check for this either.
 should also have more output processing functions, particularly to return a &amp;ldquo;phylo&amp;rdquo; object together with paintings (see earlier existing code in my Comparative-Phylogenetics repository).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/08/03/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/08/03/writing/</guid>
      <description>Finished a draft of manuscript on Likelihood ratio, sent to Sam and Peter Ralph.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit Day 3</title>
      <link>/2010/07/31/open-science-summit-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/31/open-science-summit-day-3/</guid>
      <description>see previous day for links to more details on summit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit day 2</title>
      <link>/2010/07/30/open-science-summit-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/30/open-science-summit-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Full day (really &amp;ndash; no breaks, lunch served during talks) of talks at the open science summit&amp;hellip;
Amazingly well web-captured conference, in addition to streaming on fora.tv, complete transcripts of talks are available thanks to someone with fast fingers.
Also through the back-channel, particularly the links it shares:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit</title>
      <link>/2010/07/29/open-science-summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/29/open-science-summit/</guid>
      <description>First day of the Open Science Summit, began with excellent panel discussion including Cameron Neylon, Victoria Stodden, Peter Murray-Rust and Jason Hoyt. Followed by great lineup of short talks, but behind schedule and no breaks.
 Conference Schedule Backchannel twitter archive A neat backchannel question proposing site used for the conference.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cetartiodactyle data</title>
      <link>/2010/07/28/cetartiodactyle-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/28/cetartiodactyle-data/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the cetartiodactyle data (unreleased) Nelder-Mead fails to converge or improve upon the hansen model. Likelihood scores differ little:  &amp;gt; bm@loglik [1] -362.6228 &amp;gt; ou1@loglik [1] -364.9039 &amp;gt; ws1$loglik [1] -362.7616 &amp;gt; ou2@loglik [1] -361.6976 &amp;gt; ws2$loglik [1] -361.2542  See Cetaceans code.

Fig. 1 The Brownian Motion model is preferred to the OU.1 model (left). Two separate optima are supported over a single optima (right).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameter Estimates for Labrid-Parrotfish model</title>
      <link>/2010/07/27/parameter-estimates-for-labrid-parrotfish-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/27/parameter-estimates-for-labrid-parrotfish-model/</guid>
      <description>See fast_boot and plot.wrightscape functions in code. Gape size

See fast_boot and plot.wrightscape functions in code Jaw Protrusion
Figures show strong evidence for the relax of constraint hypothesis, as the strength of selection (alpha parameters) appears to have substantially weakened in both morphological traits in the parrotfish clade relative to the wrasses clade. The wrasses show strong preference for OU model with substantial stabilizing selection, while the Parrotfish estimate almost zero stabilizing selection (Brownian model, clear phylogenetic signal).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parrotfish Model choice</title>
      <link>/2010/07/26/parrotfish-model-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/26/parrotfish-model-choice/</guid>
      <description>code, Gape data
code, Protrusion data
For both the gape data and the jaw protrusion data, the model treating parrotfish clade as a separate regime using ouch (differing optima) is not supported (even though it does have better AIC score for the protrusion data). The model using my new method allowing alpha and sigma to differ is strongly supported, providing support for the &amp;ldquo;release of constraint&amp;rdquo; hypothesis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/07/23/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/23/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio manuscript.  Labrid Herbivory data Parrotfish gape shows significant differences for independent OU models (alpha, theta, sigma different) than wrasses. While the two-peak ouch model gets no support, allowing alpha and sigma to very results in a strongly significant model improvement.
code
&amp;gt; ws2$ ws2$alpha ws2$data ws2$loglik ws2$regimes ws2$sigma ws2$theta ws2$tree ws2$Xo &amp;gt; ws2$theta [1] 0.2245493 0.9569619 &amp;gt; ws2$alpha [1] 2.943846e+00 4.995744e-06 &amp;gt; ws2$sigma [1] 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/07/22/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/22/writing/</guid>
      <description>Working on likelihood ratio manuscript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/07/21/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/21/writing/</guid>
      <description>working on likelihood ratio manuscript.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>/2010/07/20/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/20/writing/</guid>
      <description>working on Likelihood ratio manuscript. Some more literature review and outlining.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wainwright Meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/07/19/wainwright-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/19/wainwright-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussed goals and appropriate approach. Settled on linear order rather than trying to directly implement the full MCMC over paintings solution directly. Breaks into four steps/manuscripts:
 Phylogenetic signal and model choice in Comparative Methods: Likelihood ratio approach Detecting changing constraints in evolution: varying alpha and sigma across the tree Bayesian approach for all existing continuous trait comparative methods MCMC over possible histories to infer number of niches</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parrotfish-Wrasse example</title>
      <link>/2010/07/15/parrotfish-wrasse-example/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/15/parrotfish-wrasse-example/</guid>
      <description>Painting the tree with parrotfish as a separate regime from wrasses, I find significant support for a model with separate optima with differential strengths of selection and diversification as well with respect to fin angle.  code
The painting for this tree (click for larger and zoom in):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organizing analyses, data, codes</title>
      <link>/2010/07/14/organizing-analyses-data-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/14/organizing-analyses-data-codes/</guid>
      <description>Codes  Should have a suite of likelihood tools as a package Suite of data manipulation functions, mostly to and from ape/ouch  
idealized workflow:
 Read in nexus file and csv data. Call model fit for each model to be tested (BM, one peak, multiple peaks, multiple peaks with independent selective forces)  
 A function checks tree and data for matches, discards those without match. This could be done automatically by the model fit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping the independent alpha-sigma models</title>
      <link>/2010/07/13/bootstrapping-the-independent-alpha-sigma-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/13/bootstrapping-the-independent-alpha-sigma-models/</guid>
      <description>I compare in a robust framework the likelihood that species mean trait values are generated by Brownian motion, a single peak OU model, or a model with different regimes (postulated in the literature) in which the selective strength (alpha) and diversification rate (sigma) are fixed across the entire tree or allowed to vary by selective regime. (Regimes are defined as branches with different values for the selective optimum).
The parametric bootstrap of the likelihood ratio statistic provides a rigorous way to quantify the probability that the model choice is correct: the probability that the data was produced by the test model vs the null model is assured by the Neyman-Pearson lemma.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multivariate normal random variables</title>
      <link>/2010/07/12/multivariate-normal-random-variables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/12/multivariate-normal-random-variables/</guid>
      <description>GSL lacks a multivariate normal random variable option, so have implemented one using the eigenvalue decomposition (default method in the R function rmvnorm). Function should consider doing error handling (i.e. warning if covariance matrix isn&amp;rsquo;t positive definite or if the vectors given don&amp;rsquo;t match dimensions), though these may be mostly unnecessary cost. Also uses a general blas matrix multiplication when one of the matrices is just sqrt(eigenvalues) on the diagonal, so this could possibly be sped up considerably using the correct blas matrix multiply.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Status - Thoughts</title>
      <link>/2010/07/09/status---thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/09/status---thoughts/</guid>
      <description>Goal: BM vs OU vs proposed multipeak OU model with and without global alpha/sigma. Anoles dataset, carex dataset, labrids?
 Added ape2ouch_all function based on maticce to convert file formats. Might be worth checking against my current implementation. Meanwhile it&amp;rsquo;s really the converting trees back from ouch to ape that gives the ace function trouble. something about ordering of the nodes, even though that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t matter in the phylo format.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary Regime Shift examples</title>
      <link>/2010/07/08/evolutionary-regime-shift-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/08/evolutionary-regime-shift-examples/</guid>
      <description>Time to get more data and examples to start testing methods, particularly for cases in where regime shifts are hypothesized by painting a tree. Starting a Mendeley public collection for the literature in Web of Science that actually applies either the OUCH or Brownie framework to identify shifts in rates of continuous trait evolution.
Research collected using Mendeley

now I&amp;rsquo;ll have to see how hard it is to obtain both the trees and trait data&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multitype OU process interfaces</title>
      <link>/2010/07/07/multitype-ou-process-interfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/07/multitype-ou-process-interfaces/</guid>
      <description>Removing old implementations from the R package, so will need to grab them from the version history from now on to access the original linear implementations.
 Nelder-Mead simplex algorithm seems quite sensitive to starting conditions. Seeding it with values fit from the hansen algorithm (global alpha and sigma), it rapidly improves the log likelihood score (going up from 25 to 30, which is just barely significant according to AIC).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing the multi-type OU process- continued</title>
      <link>/2010/07/02/generalizing-the-multi-type-ou-process--continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/02/generalizing-the-multi-type-ou-process--continued/</guid>
      <description>Efficiency updates:
 As expected, calculating the last common ancestor on the fly was responsible for a significant (&amp;gt;50%) fraction of the computational effort, so it&amp;rsquo;s worth calculating this once for the tree and storing the information. Current profiling table:   % cumulative self self total time seconds seconds calls us/call us/call name 57.14 0.08 0.08 1604986 0.05 0.05 calc_gamma 35.71 0.13 0.05 802493 0.06 0.16 calc_var 7.14 0.14 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multitype OU Processes with varying alpha and sigma</title>
      <link>/2010/07/01/multitype-ou-processes-with-varying-alpha-and-sigma/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/01/multitype-ou-processes-with-varying-alpha-and-sigma/</guid>
      <description>Been meaning to sit down and work this one out for a while; somehow travel and conferences helped out with that &amp;ndash; now I only have to transcribe some dozen messy hotel notepad sheets to get the calculations into this lab notebook. Meanwhile, 15 hours on a train from Portland was just the right amount of time to code up the approach, which is now implemented at the C level for the Anoles dataset; code in the wrightscape project on github.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio day two</title>
      <link>/2010/06/30/ievobio-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/30/ievobio-day-two/</guid>
      <description>Program:

My Lightning talk on Open Science:
Ievobio
View more presentations from cboettig.
Also in Nature Proceedings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio day one</title>
      <link>/2010/06/29/ievobio-day-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/29/ievobio-day-one/</guid>
      <description>Program:
conference twitter
 Lunch with O&amp;rsquo;Meara &amp;amp; Price, discussing working group potential
 Dinner with Nescent folks on Dryad project and others</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2010 Day 3</title>
      <link>/2010/06/28/evolution-2010-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/28/evolution-2010-day-3/</guid>
      <description>Chris Martin: Trophic innovation drives exceptional rates of morphological diversification in two adaptive radiations of Cyprinodon pupfishes  Fantastic story of exceptional rates of evolution and trophic novelty in two tropical lakes. (8:45, Adaptation 9, talk 097002)
 David Plachetzki: Deep homology and the evolution of animal senses: insights from Cnidaria  Cnidarians have homologous proteins to opsins and taste receptors!
 Jeremy Yoder: Coevolution and gene flow in obligate pollination mutualism  Two species of joshua tree each with its own pollinator yucca moth.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2010 Day 2</title>
      <link>/2010/06/27/evolution-2010-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/27/evolution-2010-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Clay Cressler : Can you trust evolutionary parameters estimated by complex phylogenetic comparative methods? A simulation study with OUCH
 Jeet Sukumaran (Mark Holder lab) Performance and robustness of phylogeographic analytical studies
  Tests common macroscopic models of inferring population structure (i.e. via coalescent) an individual based simulation model.
 Graham Slater, Luke Harmon, Liam Revell, Marc Suchard, Mike Alfaro. Estimating rates of phenotypic evolution and speciation from incomplete trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2010</title>
      <link>/2010/06/26/evolution-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/26/evolution-2010/</guid>
      <description>Carl Boettiger A new phylogenetic comparative method: detecting niches and transitions with continuous characters  My slides:
A new phylogenetic comparative method: detecting niches and transitions with continuous characters
View more presentations from cboettig.
 Joe Felsenstein A comparative method for discrete and continuous characters using the threshold model
 Lynsey McInnes: Deep-time changes to equilibrium diversity &amp;ndash; a simulation study of th power to detect rule changes from reconstructed phylogenies</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference Thursday</title>
      <link>/2010/06/24/csgf-conference-thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/24/csgf-conference-thursday/</guid>
      <description>Conference Agenda</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference Day 2</title>
      <link>/2010/06/23/doe-csgf-conference-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/23/doe-csgf-conference-day-2/</guid>
      <description>DoE CSGF Conference, Day 2
Conference Agenda

Fellows Poster Session Photo credit Michelle King, Krell Institute. Others in the photo are: Devin Matthews, University of Texas at Austin, DOE CSGF fellow (dark blue CSGF shirt) and Jeff Lewandowski, Computational Science and Discovery Magazine.


Presented my poster which qualified as a finalist in the competition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference- Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2010/06/22/csgf-conference-tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/22/csgf-conference-tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Conference Agenda

HPC Survey Results Presented the results of my survey of the computational habits and tools of CSGF fellows and alumni. See my Survey summary. Slides, data, etc available on my github repository.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference- HPC Workshop</title>
      <link>/2010/06/21/csgf-conference-hpc-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/21/csgf-conference-hpc-workshop/</guid>
      <description>I found the breakout sessions in the afternoon particularly fascinating for their paradigm-breaking look into the future of high performance computing. While FLOPS become free, huge scale and ultra-low-power devices (little voltage difference to identify bits) make error handling a topic of major concern, and the idea of &amp;ldquo;wasting&amp;rdquo; processors to perform redundant calculations to avoid errors becomes quite serious. Other ideas, like moving computation around the memory instead of the reverse, the rise of large data and questioning the role of GPU and other novel architecture was also an important theme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wainwright Lab Meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/06/16/wainwright-lab-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/16/wainwright-lab-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Presented a revised version of my talk for Evolution 2010, focusing on the inadequacy of information-criteria heuristics for model choice in phylogenetic comparative methods and presenting the likelihood-ratio based approach I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on. Much better received this time. (The last two weeks have been pretty dedicated to preparing for the upcoming conferences, mostly for this presentation, so not much in the way of new research. Will be able to return to new stuff in July, following iEvoBio).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graham &amp; Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/06/09/graham-and-peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/09/graham-and-peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Fantastic meeting with Graham and Peter today, covered a lot of ground.
MNV I briefly sketched the multivariate normal solution for joint probability across the tree under the regimes model. The original regimes approach did not take advantage of the fact that the solution to the joint probability across the tree is multivariate normal given the painting. This allows the calculation to be partitioned as outlined in Saturday&amp;rsquo;s entry:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making slides for Evolution meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/06/08/making-slides-for-evolution-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/08/making-slides-for-evolution-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Anoles LP model vs BM
Anoles LP fits vs OU1
Anoles Neyman-Pearson model selection
Visualization of transition matrix</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing the new approach</title>
      <link>/2010/06/06/implementing-the-new-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/06/implementing-the-new-approach/</guid>
      <description>Spent just about the entire day off and on implementing the approach described in yesterday&amp;rsquo;s entry. Code includes the more direct implementation of the likelihood by generating trees from the process and averaging, as well as by weighting trees by their probability. Methods appear to agree reasonably well. The second approach should generate a wider variety of trees instead of using those produced by the first method. This could be done by varying the parameters of the transition rates to populate the collection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihood Calculation</title>
      <link>/2010/06/05/likelihood-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/05/likelihood-calculation/</guid>
      <description>Direct Calculation of the Joint Probability Fig 1 Sample tree
 This is the approach implemented in the wrightscape project matrix_method.c. Consider an example phylogenetic tree (Fig 1) over which a stochastic process describes the evolution of trait x, defined by the transition probability rate w. Then the joint probability for a set of observed traits under this process can be written:   The transition density from any state to any state can be represented as a matrix over the domain of the integral.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Phylogenetics Talk</title>
      <link>/2010/06/04/comparative-phylogenetics-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/04/comparative-phylogenetics-talk/</guid>
      <description>Practice talk in Wainwright lab meeting next Weds. 12 minutes.
 Introduce question: Inferring the number of regimes Context relative to existing methods Statistical challenges &amp;ndash; model-dependent phylogenetic signal problem Labrid example  Frameworks for approaching regimes question  wrightscape phylogenetically corrected clustering
 speed/feasibility concerns, rate limiting steps.
 model realism / representation concerns
 statistical concerns
  Returning to Wrightscape approach Haven&amp;rsquo;t worked on the full problem of inferring multiple peaks directly from comparative data using the joint probability calculation since the beginning of this notebook, so about time to return to the direct problem and compare with the more heuristic approach of &amp;ldquo;phylogenetically corrected clustering&amp;rdquo; and also synthesize the work on uncertainty which has been a dominate theme thus far (add category label for this group!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Survey</title>
      <link>/2010/05/31/csgf-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/31/csgf-survey/</guid>
      <description>Wrote survey. Getting feedback and will send out this week.  previous comments
Wiki Tricks Exploring use of mvs to download and upload entries from openwetware. The mediawiki client is easy to install as described in the link. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have a tool to grab everything in my Notebook namespace, but with a little bash script I can grab all the entries in a particular notebook:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/05/13/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/13/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Public code hosting  Project code now available through Github. Advantages to public hosting: Replication of adaptive dynamics simulations can be difficult, particularly in matching various nuisance parameters. While there is certainly much pedagogical value in individual researchers implementing their own simulations, verification and reproducibility of scientific results would be greatly facilitated by adapting an accepted open source code base and adding branches, etc. Researchers could much more immediately benefit from the work of their colleagues and spend more time implementing novel research and less reproducing it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roi and Sam Comparative Phylogenetics R Workshop</title>
      <link>/2010/05/12/roi-and-sam-comparative-phylogenetics-r-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/12/roi-and-sam-comparative-phylogenetics-r-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Day 2: 4p - 6:30p  Attending the R workshop by Roi Holzmann and Sam Price from the Wainwright lab. Missed the introductory session on Monday. Course data currently available here. Resources: Springer R books pdfs available through UC Davis. In particular: R book w/ ape.  Speciation &amp;amp; Diversification 3rd session (4:10 - 5:10 pm): Packages: Laser, Geiger, Ape, apTreeshape &amp;amp; Diversitree
 Lineage through time plots ape and laser:   ltt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/05/11/peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/11/peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussed potential solution to the model choice scenario:
 Consider an ordered list of models, A, B, C, D Then the Neyman-Pearson Lemma (see earlier entry on this) lets us walk through the list in the following fashion: We generate the simulated data sets under model A and compare likelihood ratios in each case. If the likelihood ratio of the observed data falls outside the 95% confidence interval, than it with this confidence that we are saying the data justify the alternate model (model B).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primates</title>
      <link>/2010/05/05/primates/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/05/primates/</guid>
      <description>Primates project now has a Github repository. Updates are embedded from here.
 Experimenting with distributing code and data effectively. Pluses and minuses of three options:
   zipped file with R code and data. Requires setting working directory, harder to update. Subsequent uploads must include all the data, rather than incremental. Directly grab repository over github. Simple to update and access, stores only incremental changes. Requires knowledge of git R package: Nicely integrates data, code, and documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/05/04/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/04/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Wide gap, flat landscape  Waiting times on a flatter landscape: sigma_c ~ sigma_k. Waiting times are dominated by the number of times phase 3 collapses: the established invader in a dimorphic population (right panels). Collapse of phase 2: collapse of the dimorphism before third population can establish is much rarer (about an order of magnitude).   from the run3 dataset, with parameters.  Narrower gap, steeper landscape  with sigma_c &amp;lt;&amp;lt; sigma_k, branching is easy, neither phase is particularly limiting, though single collapses from both phases are very common.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/05/03/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/03/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Working on simulation based approach to summarize distribution of waiting times across different phases. What to do about zeros in phase two (when first dimorphism survives long enough to be invaded&amp;hellip;) Quantify number/distribution of failed attempts at each phase? How to represent these distributions across a parameter space in sigma_c, sigma_k, sigma_mu, and mu?  library(BranchingTime) sim &amp;lt;- branching_time(rep=1000, cpu=8) save(file = &amp;quot;run1.Rdat&amp;quot;) pdf(&amp;quot;distribution.pdf&amp;quot;) m &amp;lt;- max(sim$data) plot(density(sim$data[1,]), xlim = c(0,m), col=&amp;quot;black&amp;quot; ) lines(density(sim$data[2,] ), col = &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;) lines(density(sim$data[3,] ), col = &amp;quot;green&amp;quot;) lines(density(sim$data[4,] ), col = &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;) legend(&#39;topright&#39;, c(&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;2&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;3&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;4&amp;quot;), col=c(&amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;blue&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;green&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;), pch = 15) dev.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/05/01/coexistence-of-the-early-dimorphism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/01/coexistence-of-the-early-dimorphism/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/05/01/phase1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/05/01/phase1/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/04/30/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/30/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Modified code phase definitions: phasetime[0] is the first time dimorphism is established. Dimorphism may be lost and restablished, last (most recent) time it establishes is phasetime1. Other times are still the most recent time at which the phase was accomplished.
 Fiddling with analytic approximations. These shouldn&amp;rsquo;t integrate to evaluate at each value, but should be done in a fully discretized system. Prototyping in R, the discrete version is probably fast enough to handle in scripted code alone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/04/29/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/29/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Manuscript writing.  Phylogenetics Submitted Lightning talk to iEvoBio
PDG group will be discussing
 Rabosky DL and Lovette IJ. .&amp;rdquo;) pmid:18611849. PubMed HubMed [1]  tomorrow, along with critique and response.
 Waiting to hear back from Peter on manuscript. Should follow up with Ralph on likelihood ratio discussion with Ethan. Transcluding exploratory work on primate phylogeny data:  Embedded:

Primate Phylogeny Carl Boettiger 00:37, 30 April 2010 (EDT):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meetings</title>
      <link>/2010/04/28/meetings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/28/meetings/</guid>
      <description>Theory Coffee 10-11a: Varied discussion, including NEON project and future of large data.
 Hastings Lab Meeting 2-3p: David Kling presents bioeconomic model on assisted migration. Model focuses on dynamic and spatial aspects, reflects pattern of dispersal common in ideal free distribution with dynamic carrying capacity, adds linear and quadratic costs.
 (Fire alarms in Wickson Hall don&amp;rsquo;t make for a productive day).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio lightning talk</title>
      <link>/2010/04/27/ievobio-lightning-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/27/ievobio-lightning-talk/</guid>
      <description>Submitting a five minute lighting talk on open science. Submitted version here, final text below. See the page revision history for earlier drafts and the original call below. Special thanks to Sam, Alistair, Betta, Shaun, and Alex for feedback.
My experiment with open science: Why the benefits of sharing go beyond source code The practice and philosophy of open source run deep within the iEvoBio community. Sharing source code has made software development faster and more reliable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/04/26/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/26/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Matching theoretical approximations to simulation:
 Implemented the first analytic approximation, calculating the waiting time to complete phase 1. Established dimophisms are often still lost, hence the first successful completion of phase 1 (dimorphic population in coexistence region with each above threshold size) doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the time of the last completion of phase 1. Phase 2, an established third population seems to happen soon after the last successful phase 1, giving the illusion this step is easy rather than the reality that this process requires fast traversal to persist past the coexistence time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/04/23/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/23/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Computing Challenges  10 - 1p Adding solutions to yesterday&amp;rsquo;s puzzles, see Yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Entry The random number generator solution is imperfect, as it limits the total number of seeds to 1e9 since coercing to an integer will create NAs with larger numbers.  
 seeds &amp;lt;- 1e9*runif(reps) out &amp;lt;- sfSapply(1:reps, function(i){ branch_simulation(seed=seeds[i]) })  Analytic Solutions Git Log  Created commit da58a6e: random number seeds now set to avoid parallel cores running with same seed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/04/22/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/22/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>compiling with R and C and parallel computing  Problem: cannot get the R code to take advantage of parallelization via openMP.
 Solution:
  C++ file mangles names in .so, changing the .C call. to get the object name:
objdump -x file.so  Carl Boettiger 03:01, 25 May 2010 (EDT): More standard solution: enclose cpp code in
 extern C {  
 Problem: Trouble getting R to export the C library to all nodes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/04/21/adaptive-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/21/adaptive-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Wrapping up paper on waiting time to branching in adaptive dynamics. Cleaning up code from summer. Now in a local git repository in adaptiveDynamics/code Moved ensemble parallelization to higher level, so parallelization can be performed in R or C. Adding documentation  Current status  Calculates the waiting time to complete phase 1, phase 2, and phase 3 successfully from individual-based simulation.  Phase 1 ~ Completed when 2 branches exist over threshold Phase 2 ~ Completed when a third population has established over threshold exterior to a stable pair Phase 3 ~ Completed when two populations over threshold are separated in traitspace by more than finishline units</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/04/20/waiting-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/20/waiting-time/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R-sig-phylo</title>
      <link>/2010/04/20/r-sig-phylo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/20/r-sig-phylo/</guid>
      <description>A couple interesting discussions on R-sig-phylo   estimating alpha and sigma reliably, knowing when you hit a likelihood ridge. See discussion. strange behavior in ace. Tried new ace function, same problem.  
Research  Working on logs paper Waiting on Primate data Waiting on feedback on Labrids paper  
DoE Conference Registration  Submitted Poster title and abstract corresponding to my iEvoBio proposal.  Reading  podcast on the Science Careers story.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/04/19/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/19/research/</guid>
      <description>Sent Peter updated draft of Labrids manuscript Writing up logarithms manuscript finally&amp;hellip; Contacting Helen re. primates data Created Labrid Functional Morphology literature collection:  Research collected using Mendeley
 Started stochastic methods and model inference collection:  Research collected using Mendeley
Various To Do  Add Peter&amp;rsquo;s bootstrap references and books to stochastic methods and model inference library. Add Science of Science papers to Future of Science collection. Adding tags, abstracts, etc to Mendeley public Library Personal/extended task view (and opinion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MATICCE</title>
      <link>/2010/04/18/maticce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/18/maticce/</guid>
      <description>Testing out Andrew Hipp&amp;rsquo;s maticce package, doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp625. Goal of package is to model-average over trees and regimes. Takes a brownie approach to regimes, identifying nodes at which a transition may have occurred.  
The Approach Takes a brute force approach to avoid user-defined paintings in the ouch framework. Users identify nodes of interest, software tries combinations of possible shifts.
runBatchHansen()  User identifies a set of nodes of interest, and optionally a maximum number of transitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio Submission</title>
      <link>/2010/04/16/ievobio-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/16/ievobio-submission/</guid>
      <description>Quantifying Information in a Phylogenetic Tree: The Robustness of Phylogenetic Signal Since Felsenstein (1985)&amp;rsquo;s influential paper on phylogenetic contrasts, phylogenetically-based inferences of evolutionary patterns have gotten increasingly more complex (Hansen, 1997; Butler and King, 2004; Freckleton and Harvey, 2006; O&amp;rsquo;Meara et al., 2006; Pagel and Meade, 2006). More and more sophisticated models are applied to datasets of species mean traits on a phylogenetic tree in an attempt to answer such questions as reconstructing ancestral states, identify changes in rates of character evolution across time and across clades, identify the number and location of evolutionary optima or the strength of stabilizing selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/04/15/branching-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/15/branching-paper/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2010/04/14/wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/14/wednesday/</guid>
      <description>10-2p Finish preparing for EDG talk.
 2-3p. Talk went pretty well. Could still polish slides up for them to be useful, likewise for outline.
 3-4 OA meeting
 4-9p awesome talk in ESLP with Katie Maynard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2010/04/13/tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/13/tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Preparing for EDG talk</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primate chronogram</title>
      <link>/2010/04/12/primate-chronogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/12/primate-chronogram/</guid>
      <description>From User:Daniel Mietchen/Notebook/Evolutionary MRI/2010/04/12:
 Jinchuan Xing recommended New perspectives on anthropoid origins whose Fig. 2 goes into our direction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/04/09/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/09/research/</guid>
      <description>Working on bootstrapping theta parameters bootstrapping multiple parameters doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem effective in the context of the boot package, despite claiming it can use a vector of stats. Certainly part of challenge is that different models have different numbers of parameters, so this isn&amp;rsquo;t a fixed size vector. Approaching manually for the moment, inhibits use of bootstrap confidence intervals function from the boot package. Some irregular behavior in bootstrapping parameters &amp;ndash; have to load package and then reload likelihood_bootstrap library source file or else bootstraps are NAs, needs further investigation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/04/08/comparative-phylogenetics-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/08/comparative-phylogenetics-notebook/</guid>
      <description>Research  Wrote summary function using bootstrap confidence intervals for the bootstraps of the likelihoods directly. On interpreting the bootstraps of likelihoods directly:   The extent to which the distributions themselves are distinct provides an indication of the ability to distinguish between models on the given phylogenetic tree and the actual data. For instance, if the tree was a star tree and the data produced by either BM or OU1, then all distributions would fall on top of one another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/04/06/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/06/research/</guid>
      <description>Seem to have successfully fixed the behavior when getting over parameterized models. See diffs against the git log for details.
 Will work on acceleration of code (avoiding refitting), meanwhile a little more trouble shooting and queuing some long runs.
 ace function fails on certain data sets for unknown reasons. Think rewriting this from scratch will be an important step.
  Mixture Models in Bayesian context  Josh sent me this paper regarding our discussion on model choice in Bayesian context last Friday.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/04/05/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/05/research/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapping procedures should have the option to refit the painting. Currently use the fixed painting but refit parameters. wrote the function peaks_update() which update the painting as well as the OU peak parameters.  20 replicates, bootstraps the painting step as well
Computing / Package  LR_bootstrap and model_bootstrap should be the same function call with an optional second model for the LR bootstrapping. Similarly the LR_bootstrap_all and model_bootstrap_all() should be the same function call.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/04/04/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/04/research/</guid>
      <description>Trouble-shooting on parameter refitting version of LR bootstraps.  
NESCent  Considering a visit to NESCent, meet researchers and learn about programs, post-docs, etc.  People  Todd Vision, UNC &amp;ndash; Ass. Director Informatics. Contact Re: Dryad project. Consider a white paper on interdisciplinary evolutionary synthesis. Brian Weigmann NCSU Diptera Systematics. Ass. Director Outreach NESCent Allen Rodrigo Director NESCent. (Computational evolutionary biology). Discuss possible catalysis meeting, working group, visiting scholar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/04/02/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/02/research/</guid>
      <description>Graham &amp;amp; Peter Meeting Fig 1
Fig 2
 Decided that bootstrapping against fixed model parameters would be more difficult to interpret, Fig 1. Simulated data results with refitting seem strange (Fig. 2), perhaps related to fitting of the tree. Observed LR for data should at least remain symmetric, so something has gone wrong. Expected pattern should be deducible simply by upper left triangle of graphs, should accept the first model where the data becomes typical.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/03/31/comparative-phylogenetics-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/31/comparative-phylogenetics-notebook/</guid>
      <description>Research Labrid Paper Outline Biology Letters format, 2500 words, 2 figures.
Fig 1?
Fig 2?
 Title: Phylogenetic Evidence for Multiple Morphological Niches in Coral Reef Fish Summary (&amp;lt; 200 words)
 We present phylogenetic evidence for two distinct evolutionary optima in the fin morphology of Labrid Fish.  Keywords: Evolution, Phylogenetics, Comparative Methods, Labrids, Multiple Niches
 Introduction
 Labrid Fin Morphology Is clustering in Trait space evidence of Selection or Phylogenetic Inertia?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/03/30/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/30/research/</guid>
      <description>Current Situation &amp;amp; Challenges 2000 bootstraps of models fitted to simulated ou2 data
 A single data set is produced by simulation under a specified ou2 model on the Labrid tree (actually one that was fitted to the original Labrid data). Each model (Brownian motion and 1 to 5 separate OU peaks (assigned by my partition function) is fitted to this dataset. Each fitted model is used to generate 2000 replicate datasets For each replicate dataset, the model used to generate it is compared to each other model in likelihood ratio test 2(log(L~1~) − log(L~2~)), where L~1~ is the likelihood of the model that generated the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Still puzzling on LR</title>
      <link>/2010/03/26/still-puzzling-on-lr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/26/still-puzzling-on-lr/</guid>
      <description> The likelihood ratios when parameters are not held fixed, using data originally generated from a two peak model. Has 1000 bootstrap replicates per plot.   The likelihood ratios when parameters are held fixed, after being generated from a two-peak model. (2000 replicates each)   parameters held fixed, three peak model (200 replicates each)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/03/25/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/25/research/</guid>
      <description>New Simulations  Now have code to run partitioned models on the Anoles dataset, compare partitioned models to the paintings chosen by Butler and King. Preliminary figures below. Models with _s are partitioned by my algorithm, others are the the original ones from earlier.   Also have examples with simulated data with a known number of partitions, to check the method. Tested with data produced at two peaks on the Labrid tree, the pattern seems similar to that of the Labrids &amp;ndash; comparisons involving any model with more than 2 peaks produce LR ratios that become very unlikely in either pairwise comparison.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel R</title>
      <link>/2010/03/24/parallel-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/24/parallel-r/</guid>
      <description>Parallelized LR_bootstrap_all() and model_bootstrap_all() bootstrapping functions. Lets the bootstrapping of different models (or LRs between models) to be performed on different machines. Using the snowfall package in R for easy parallel computing. The parallel loop is done through the sfLapply() function. Had to get libraries and functions exported to all loops using sfLibrary() and sfExportAll(). R-sig-hpc mailing list was very helpful at getting this up and running at 4am.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrapping Likelihood ratios</title>
      <link>/2010/03/23/bootstrapping-likelihood-ratios/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/23/bootstrapping-likelihood-ratios/</guid>
      <description>Bootstraps of the likelihood ratio, holding the parameters fixed, finally completed.  Anoles: Summary Anoles table:
&amp;gt; summary(anoles_boots) [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4] [,5] [1,] 0.500000000 0.981399498 0.26514573 0.06668672 0.018154938 [2,] 0.009580545 0.500000000 0.15610274 0.04819938 0.011616566 [3,] 0.039233893 0.075349644 0.50000000 0.05699877 0.005443493 [4,] 0.004211230 0.004592917 0.01389950 0.50000000 0.006648916 [5,] 0.173457542 0.198303402 0.38893099 0.33891430 0.500000000 &amp;gt;  Labrids: &amp;gt; summary(labrid_boots) [,1] [,2] [,3] [,4] [1,] 0.5000000 6.036842e-05 0.0000000 0.0 [2,] 0.5424613 5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetic Tree formats</title>
      <link>/2010/03/22/phylogenetic-tree-formats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/22/phylogenetic-tree-formats/</guid>
      <description>Consider a tree with N nodes. has tips and internal nodes.  ape Format: class &amp;ldquo;phylo&amp;rdquo;  Elements of the data structure: phy$edge &amp;ndash; Topology. 2 by N-1 matrix. First column has internal nodes only, each node appearing twice. Internal nodes range from 1+(N+1)/2 to N-1, while the tip numbers go from 1 to (N+1)/2. Each node appears once in the second column, and is a child of the node identified in the first column.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/03/20/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/20/research/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrap the fitted models (rather than allow the parameters to be refit, simply evaluate the likelihood of the model under each simulated dataset) Directly evaluate Neyman-Pearson lemma for each pairwise model comparison. Also analyze the bootstrapped likelihoods directly (and without refitting) for each model.  To Do  Add a summary function for the likelihood_ratio_bootstrap.R library final wrapper function for infer_niches.R partitioning library More error handling and documentation Example of partitioning Anoles then bootstrapping Bootstrapping likelihoods directly  References on thinking about bootstrapping model comparisons  The original Neyman-Pearson paper Testing Statistical Hypotheses Text by Lehmann &amp;amp; Romano Permutation, Parametric and Bootstrap Tests of Hypotheses by Good Thanks to Peter on these; Bibsonomy collection  ouch2ape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/03/19/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/19/research/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapped against 2000 replicate simulations overnight on both the Anoles dataset and the Labrids dataset. Distributions that overlap zero represent replicates that choose the wrong model. The Anoles data below; the first column corresponds to the likelihood ratios shown in Butler &amp;amp; King (2004), comparing each model against BM.   The Labrid dataset:   Find matching figures for the case of parameters held fixed on more recent entry</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/03/18/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/18/research/</guid>
      <description>A some point I&amp;rsquo;ll want to think more seriously about incorporating geographic information into comparative analyses. At some level this data is more available than appropriate continuous traits, as illustrated in the example phylogenetics wiki from Prof. Roderic Page that I just came across.  Today&amp;rsquo;s Goals  Repeating last night&amp;rsquo;s bootstraps on the likelihood ratio. Need to clean up and incorporate my bootstrap codes first. Should also explore the bootstrapping of the partitioning functions from yesterday.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/2010/03/17/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/17/research/</guid>
      <description>Maximum likelihood assignment based on arbitrary number of partitions now completed. Working on stochastic assignment. Now have functions for:   partitioning data into k groups, inferring an ancestral state painting based on this partition inferring a continuous model with k OU regimes based on this painting   need to add my function for the proper model-comparison bootstrap of likelihood ratio values rather than the likelihoods themselves. See my original entry on this approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graham &amp; Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/03/16/graham-and-peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/16/graham-and-peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussed inverse problem approach. Discussed bootstrapping likelihoods directly vs bootstrapping likelihood ratio Integrating over uncertainty in the likelihood assignment  
Research Progress  Completed writing the bootstrapping function for the partition scheme, ouch2ape function completed for converting ouch tree formats back to ape. modifies code from r-forge More details and log on the repository  Goals for Wainwright meeting tomorrow  Repeat Labrid Fin analysis with tripartition Bootstrap likelihood ratio functions</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computing</title>
      <link>/2010/03/15/computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/15/computing/</guid>
      <description>Exploring parallel computing options. OpenMP for distributed memory applications. learning git &amp;ndash; need to get used to the branch and merge, install on one.  Research The failure of the Anoles data set to robustly select the more common model can easily be explained by the likelihood distribution: Not surprising since this dataset consists of only 23 taxa. The Labrid tree of 114 taxa clearly resolves the difference between the different models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-Workshop</title>
      <link>/2010/03/14/post-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/14/post-workshop/</guid>
      <description>Working on a couple new ideas:
 Multiple partitions Community phylogenetics nulls Diversification rates w/ stationary distributions  Tools exploration  Finding my forum a very useful tool for recording and organizing around idea. Nice complement to this notebook which helps me organize temporally instead. Becoming convinced I should transition from svn to git. Created a git-hub account and have started learning the basic git commands. The Git community book and the website video tutorials have been very helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Workshop Presentations</title>
      <link>/2010/03/12/bodega-workshop-presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/12/bodega-workshop-presentations/</guid>
      <description>Final day of Bodega Phylogenetics workshop: a full day of student presentations. (High resolution images for the trees available by clicking on them)
Principle figures from my investigation of the Labrid data. While morphospace doesn&amp;rsquo;t present an obvious clustering, it can be effectively divided by my maximum likelihood partitioning scheme on fin angle. A smoothed density plot of fin angle alone reveals two identifiable modes in the traitspace.
Based on the discretized partition, ancestral states are reconstructed under both the equal rates and independent rates model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetics Workshop Day 5</title>
      <link>/2010/03/11/phylogenetics-workshop-day-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/11/phylogenetics-workshop-day-5/</guid>
      <description>Last day of lectures: Lineage Diversification
Brian Moore: Rates of Lineage Diversification Bodega Wiki slides &amp;amp; tutorial
 Detecting significant diversification rate variation across tree locate shifts along branches and through time (niche-filling, density dep models?) correlates of differential rates parameter estimation speciation/extinction  correlates of differential rates  Apply Felsenstein pruning algorithm to calc likelihood and hence fit model this is just the definition of a joint probability! Use this to estimate the model, then do rejection sampling to create the tree painting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Workshop Day 4</title>
      <link>/2010/03/10/bodega-workshop-day-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/10/bodega-workshop-day-4/</guid>
      <description>Morphological Evolution Day:
 Peter Wainwright Sam Price Johnathan Eisen  We have the afternoon session off for field trips and research.

Peter Wainwright, Comparative Analysis of Morphological Diversity  Fantastic diversity in morphology, corresponds to niche! But morphological diversity isn&amp;rsquo;t evenly distributed across tree of life. (See slides, parallels Peter&amp;rsquo;s section on core and gives the best biological coverage we&amp;rsquo;ve had this week).  What changes morphological diversification rate</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Phylogenetics Workshop Day 3</title>
      <link>/2010/03/09/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/09/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-3/</guid>
      <description>Rich Glor, Character Evolution Official slides and tutorial
 Weakness of ancestral state reconstruction
 Cunningham 1999 Losos 1999  Testing hypotheses with ancestral reconstruction
 Parsimony Farris method. Downward/upward pass. Gives a maximum parsimony reconstruction. May miss other ones. Apparently this Parsimony analysis can be done for continuous traits as well, needs a measure of distance Likelihood Pagel 1994 Schluter 1997   R tutorial (see anolis_cheat.R)
 Discrete trait ancestral state reconstruction</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Phylogenetics Workshop Day 2</title>
      <link>/2010/03/08/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/08/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Marine lab researchers are back, and network speeds have just about given up (down to bytes/s). This post is composed offline and will be uploaded to the notebook. Details are well logged on the Bodgea Phylogenetics Wiki so these are reasonably sketchy with my comments.
My Updates to Bodega Phylogenetics Wiki Made several contributions to the Bodega Phylogenetics Wiki today:
 User page Phylogenetics on Linux Becoming a Programmer Edits on Advice for Aspiring Phylogeneticists  Today&amp;rsquo;s agenda  BEAST continued.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bodega Phylogenetics Workshop Day 1</title>
      <link>/2010/03/07/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/07/bodega-phylogenetics-workshop-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Lecture notes for the phyolgenetics workshop. These are taken in real time, so may contain errors. I&amp;rsquo;ll see if I keep this up throughout the course. See course website.
Huelsenbeck 9a-11a
 Parameters θ Observation X p(X | θ) is known as the likelihood. Adjust parameter to maximize likelihood. Coin toss example  θ = prob of heads on a single toss of a coin, X is # of heads observed on n tosses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2010/03/05/friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/05/friday/</guid>
      <description>11a Sebastian Meeting (see Stochastic Population Dynamics Notebook)
12p - 1p
 Lunch talk in joint lab group (Schreiber Coop Moore Rannala Eisen) on coalescents for wARG. Remember to check out kcachegrind as interface to valgrind and profiler, and also mauve as a dynamic sequence alignment display tool.  Comparative Phylogenetics Discussion group 4-5p. Discussing:
 Van Bocxlaer I, Loader SP, Roelants K, Biju SD, Menegon M, and Bossuyt F.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Picture Comparative Phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/2010/03/04/big-picture-comparative-phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/04/big-picture-comparative-phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>A Task View on Phylogenetic Comparative Methods (in R on CRAN) has been released today, maintained by Brian O&amp;rsquo;Meara. Quite thorough and concise.
 Follow-up discussion on:
 List is useful, but would be nice to be able to expand / collapse the list to see more / less details about the functions available. More detail makes it harder to maintain, perhaps get the developers involved? List is also quite provocative source to realize what&amp;rsquo;s missing (there&amp;rsquo;s no way to estimate ancestral states under OU using existing software?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Solution to the strange behavior in ouch</title>
      <link>/2010/03/03/solution-to-the-strange-behavior-in-ouch/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/03/solution-to-the-strange-behavior-in-ouch/</guid>
      <description>Looks like my troubles actually stem from a bug in the code. I summarize the problem here, just as I posted in my query to R sig phylo. Essentially the program erroneously squares alpha at the moment, explaining the pattern I found yesterday. Giving it root alpha preemptively should be a good work around.

data(bimac) tree &amp;lt;- with(bimac,ouchtree(node,ancestor,time/max(time),species)) print(h2 &amp;lt;- hansen(log(bimac[&#39;size&#39;]),tree,bimac[&#39;OU.1&#39;],alpha=1,sigma=1))  The print command says alpha = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in trees</title>
      <link>/2010/03/02/power-in-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/03/02/power-in-trees/</guid>
      <description>Back to Phylogenetics after a week with only population dynamics.  Exploration  data created by brown simulation on the star tree in ouch matches the expected variance, σ^2^t. This variance is slightly reduced when simulated on the Felsenstein tree, as might be intuitively expected due to the increased correlations. The degree of decrease should be analytically attainable, but isn&amp;rsquo;t obvious to me at the moment. Example using functions in felsenstein_tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2010/02/25/thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/25/thursday/</guid>
      <description>Some exploration with felsenstein_tree.R, see svn log.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing an example of low and high power trees</title>
      <link>/2010/02/20/implementing-an-example-of-low-and-high-power-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/20/implementing-an-example-of-low-and-high-power-trees/</guid>
      <description>Code implementation in felsenstein_tree.R
 I consider a star tree and a Felsenstein tree each of N nodes; M = (N+1)/2 tips. I consider an uncorrelated data set of M normal random variables, such as would be generated by either BM or OU models on the star tree. I produce a correlated data set such as would be generated by Brownian motion on the felsenstein tree. I generate 8 model fits &amp;ndash; fitting BM and OU to each tree under each data set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in trees continues</title>
      <link>/2010/02/19/power-in-trees-continues/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/19/power-in-trees-continues/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of power in trees need a counterpoint to the example of the star tree as being devoid of information content. The best example here is probably the example tree used in the introduction of Felsenstein 1985: two star trees sharing a common ancestor. Implemented the basic creation of a balanced tree of arbitrary depth having this structure. The balanced tree has 2^h^ − 1 nodes, all internal nodes occuring at time = 1&amp;frasl;2 and all tips at time = 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Power in Trees</title>
      <link>/2010/02/18/power-in-trees/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/18/power-in-trees/</guid>
      <description>Following up after yesterday&amp;rsquo;s meeting, I am working on implementing the confidence interval analysis and quantifying information in trees. This second point I will develop by comparing the Felsenstein example tree (information-rich) to the star tree (uninformative), and develop this discussion in the context of assessing the importance of phylogenetic corrections and phylogenetic intertia (my original theme again: noise or data??).
Primate Brain Morphometry Daniel Mietchen contacted me through openwetware 11 days ago with interest in applying phylogenetic comparative methods to Primate Brain Morphometry data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting Goals</title>
      <link>/2010/02/17/meeting-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/17/meeting-goals/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of information in phyologenetic trees analysis  Review manuscript outline. More examples of comparisons? Sequence of presentation? Parametric bootstrapping approach; see this entry. Quantifying information in a tree a priori to any trait data Stationary distribution fits vs full model fits as measure of phylogenetic signal  Discussion of Regimes model  Review project status of implementing the more complicated regimes model, discussed here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updating manuscript</title>
      <link>/2010/02/16/updating-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/16/updating-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>The progress of the past few days has lead to substantial revision proposals in my manuscript draft. Rewriting for discussion with Brian tomorrow. Currently revised outline:
 Intro
 Biological Motivation Comparative Methods and Comparing Models Model choice paradigm: the right direction, but incomplete  Simple Example
 The Star Tree Two hypotheses: stabilizing vs disruptive selection Information Criteria approach is insufficient Likelihood surfaces Likelihood ratio distribution  Anoles Example</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parametric bootstrapping</title>
      <link>/2010/02/15/parametric-bootstrapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/15/parametric-bootstrapping/</guid>
      <description>There are several ways we can frame the bootstrapping question. What is the probability that we see a given likelihood ratio statistic (that the log likelihoods differ by a certain spread) just by chance? We have two versions of chance &amp;ndash; the chance we see this ratio when model a is correct and the chance we see this ratio when model b is correct. We simulate 2000 data sets under each model, generating a distribution of likelihood ratio scores for each data set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/02/14/speciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/14/speciation/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Follow-up on Parametric Bootstrapping</title>
      <link>/2010/02/10/follow-up-on-parametric-bootstrapping/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/10/follow-up-on-parametric-bootstrapping/</guid>
      <description>Continuing on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s discussion of parametric boostrapping implementation. Peter sent some very helpful comments and agreed to having them here for reference; I&amp;rsquo;ve added some links.  &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve read up a bit on the bootstrap just now. First off, although parametric and nonparametric bootstrapping has always seemed very different to me, they fit in the same natural framework. The general idea is that in reality, there&amp;rsquo;s some real parameters x and some probability distribution P that&amp;rsquo;s given us some data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting with Graham and Peter</title>
      <link>/2010/02/09/meeting-with-graham-and-peter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/09/meeting-with-graham-and-peter/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of Model Comparisons Primary focus of today&amp;rsquo;s discussion was rooted in Sunday&amp;rsquo;s entry
 On plotting quirks, haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out lattice but here&amp;rsquo;s yet another newer plotting engine for R I need to revisit how OUCH computes likelihood ratios and P values. Since some parameters are bounded to the positive real line (and may be small) the standard chi square isn&amp;rsquo;t correct. I should repeat the AIC-style analysis for likelihood ratios, though this is just a shift of where I put the zero line.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Difficulties with Existing Methods continued</title>
      <link>/2010/02/08/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/08/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods-continued/</guid>
      <description>Working on manuscript for this today, hope to have a draft soon.
 Just added a basic example using a star-burst tree to illustrate the challenges associated with this kind of model choice inference.
 Sent draft to Brian and Peter, and Wainwright lab.
 Still needs a figure explaining the BM, OU(1) and OU(LP) models for those not familiar with Butler and King 2004 paper, general polishing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Difficulties with Existing Methods</title>
      <link>/2010/02/07/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/07/exploring-difficulties-with-existing-methods/</guid>
      <description>Model choice plays an increasingly dominant role in comparative phylogenetics. The software OUCH of Butler and King (2004) is built around the model comparison framework and returns a variety of information criteria for choosing between different models fitted to the tree.
 I&amp;rsquo;ve written a short R script to explore how robust these inferences are, and the results are rather surprising. None of the inferences holds up to the classical P value standard of 95% probability of being right, and the inference can be wrong more often than it is right &amp;ndash; a coin flip out-performs the model choice method based on these information criteria in certain cases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lunch with Wainwright Lab</title>
      <link>/2010/02/05/lunch-with-wainwright-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/02/05/lunch-with-wainwright-lab/</guid>
      <description>Friday lunch with Wainwright lab continues to be a very useful chance to bounce ideas off of lab members with an excellent grasp of both the models involved and the real biology, morphology and evolution in question. Today&amp;rsquo;s discussion hit several topics.
 Should regime transitions be restricted to nodes? The general consensus was No. On one hand, the position of nodes may contain information about the timing of an actual environmental change responsible for a regime shift.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/01/18/progresschallenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/01/18/progresschallenges/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CPB thesis proposal</title>
      <link>/2010/01/10/cpb-thesis-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2010 14:07:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/01/10/cpb-thesis-proposal/</guid>
      <description>In the spirit of archiving work in the lab notebook, this was my PhD dissertation proposal, a requirement to advance to candidacy submitted before our oral defense in the second or third year. Following some excellent advice, this is focused more narrowly than my actual dissertation. As a historical note, I started keeping an open lab notebook the month following this, on OpenWetWare (so work leading up to this isn&amp;rsquo;t archived, though admittedly first two years were largely coursework).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2009/08/25/diffusion-solution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2009/08/25/diffusion-solution/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2009/08/25/drift-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2009/08/25/drift-effects/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2009/08/25/stochastic-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2009/08/25/stochastic-methods/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2009/07/28/branching-times/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2009/07/28/branching-times/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2008/06/09/popbio-core-review-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2008/06/09/popbio-core-review-notes/</guid>
      <description> Embedded versions of my summary sheets for the Population Biology graduate group core course, organized by faculty member&amp;rsquo;s section.
Schreiber: Single species population dynamics Schoener: multispecies population dynamics Stachowicz: Community ecology Sih: Animal behavior Turelli: Population genetics and speciation Wainwright: macroevolution and comparative phylogenetics </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>