<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Science on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/categories/open-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Science on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 17:54:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/open-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Notebook Science Abstract</title>
      <link>/2010/12/30/open-notebook-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2010 17:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/30/open-notebook-science/</guid>
      <description>In addition to my primary research categories, I make some entries in my lab notebook to document and reflect on my experiment in open notebook science. This includes my notes on tools I try out for open and collaborative science, including uses of social media, cloud computing, and scientific databases and repositories.
This serves as a cover-page for the open science entries in my notebook, displaying the most recent entries, articles, figures and code through rss feeds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing, Cloud Computing, and #scio11</title>
      <link>/2010/12/23/writing-cloud-hpc-and-scio11/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2010 19:08:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/23/writing-cloud-hpc-and-scio11/</guid>
      <description>Working on a few things in today&amp;rsquo;s lab notebook entry. Some more notes on exploring cloud computing tools, sketching out some ideas for my #scio11 science online panel discussion on open notebook science, and otherwise working on my phylogenetics mansucript.
Cloud Computing An interesting package was announced over the r-sig-hpc list today, creating an arbitrarily large Hadoop cluster out of Amazon EC2 instances directly from the R command line. JD Long has been very responsive to my naive questions on setting it up, so I was able to quickly activate an Elastic Map Reduce account via Amazon Web Services and run the example code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sun: Visualizing my coding over the past year</title>
      <link>/2010/12/20/sun-visualizing-my-coding-over-the-past-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2010 00:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/20/sun-visualizing-my-coding-over-the-past-year/</guid>
      <description>Not really working today, as holidays approach, but came across the Gource toolkit for creating video visualization from git development (inspired by the Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s example). So in the spirit of year-in-review reflections, here&amp;rsquo;s my development from the past year (just for the phylogenetic statistics work).
Quality is a little too poor to read file names, more entertaining than practical. Other user icons appear in December corresponding with my move to running the code from Amazon cloud.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citations</title>
      <link>/2010/12/11/citations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 07:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/11/citations/</guid>
      <description>This evening I&amp;rsquo;m testing extensions to find a better way to include citations in my entries. Thus far I&amp;rsquo;ve use Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s convenient copy-paste citation tool to paste the whole citation in, which I suppose could work reasonably smoothly with the nice footnotes plugin I recently adopted. However, this still requires a couple more steps than I need to cite in my LaTeX text editor or in OpenOffice.
Using the papercite plugin, I can add citations to posts in much the same way that I add them to my latex documents, using the citation key created Mendeley when it makes my bibtex file.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>socialR: Reproducible Research &amp; Notebook integration with R</title>
      <link>/2010/12/11/socialr-an-r-package-to-track-the-status-of-computations-with-social-network-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 03:44:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/11/socialr-an-r-package-to-track-the-status-of-computations-with-social-network-tools/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve created an R package that uses social media tools for reproducible research. The goal of the package is this: whenever I run a code, output figures are automatically added to my figure repository (Flickr), linked to the timestamped version of the code that produced them in the code repository. Figures should be tagged by project and be embedded selectively or automatically into this lab notebook. The basic workflow of the notebook looks like this:[ref]Diagram of my notebook as presented at Science Online, 2011, see other slides in my entry on this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on the New Policies for Data Archiving at NSF and in Common Journals</title>
      <link>/2010/12/03/nsf-and-journal-data-archiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2010 19:08:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/03/nsf-and-journal-data-archiving/</guid>
      <description>This post is a work in progress, a scratch pad for me to start assembling what I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning about and resources pertaining to the new policies emerging from NSF and journals relevant to ecology and evolution. Hoping to highlight not only the policies, but the issues, opportunities, and concerns around them.
I am hoping to help organize a workshop to discuss these issues in my department this Winter. The Davis Open Science group, is planning a series of these workshops, hoping to work with departments, the libraries and the UC Davis Office of Research and its Responsible Conduct of Research  program (in compliance with NIH/NSF ethics requirements), as well as resident faculty and editors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making R twitter?</title>
      <link>/2010/11/21/following-my-computer-simulations-on-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 21:28:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/21/following-my-computer-simulations-on-twitter/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m running quite a few of my analyses on my remote server, a 16 core, 32 GB ram, Ubuntu server with Tesla GPU, named &amp;ldquo;zero&amp;rdquo; (we&amp;rsquo;re creative folks). It&amp;rsquo;s easy to start lots of simulations (from ssh), harder to track when they are finished and verify results. No longer &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;zero&amp;rdquo; now uses social media to share what she&amp;rsquo;s up to. Find her on twitter: @tweeting_cpu
Social Computation  Provides automated updating of simulation status and error messages</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>evolution today:  Discussion groups, writing, etc</title>
      <link>/2010/11/15/phylogenetics-today-discussion-groups-writing-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2010 22:37:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/15/phylogenetics-today-discussion-groups-writing-etc/</guid>
      <description>Interesting discussion of a Lenski paper in Wainwright&amp;rsquo;s 270.
Barrick, J.E. et al. Genome evolution and adaptation in a long-term experiment with Escherichia coli. Nature 461, 1243-7(2009).
Seems to focus on surprise of continuing linear rate of increase in beneficial mutations, though statistics don&amp;rsquo;t seem to confirm. Curious about uncertainty in assay of fitness estimates (seem to go down at times, but surely not fixing deleterious mutations). General difficulties in setup of exponential growth with applications of classic constant population size, but maybe we&amp;rsquo;re all missing something.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my Lab Notebook</title>
      <link>/2010/11/08/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 02:50:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/08/welcome-to-my-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: Not a Blog Welcome to my open lab notebook. This is the active, permanent record of all my scientific research, standing in place of the traditional bound lab notebook. It is a record of ideas, and intuitions; results and mistakes. Please bear in mind that the notebook is primarily a tool for me to do science, not communicate it. I write my entries with the hope that they are intelligible to my future self; and maybe intelligible to my collaborators and experts in my field.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: Evolution reading, writing</title>
      <link>/2010/11/05/friday-evolution-reading-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 18:21:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/05/friday-evolution-reading-writing/</guid>
      <description>Read through the article for Monday&amp;rsquo;s PBG270, a 2009 Nature paper from the Plotkin lab on mutational robustness and the rate of evolution. They consider an interesting little setup. Start with a Moran model (individual born, may mutate, choses who to replace at random), but allow the following mutational structure (landscape). Of P possible genotypes, each can only move to one of K neighbors by a single mutation. Call the genotype(s) of optimal fitness C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2010/11/05/thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 18:08:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/05/thursday/</guid>
      <description>Wrote yesterday&amp;rsquo;s entry on power spectral analysis difficulties from yesterday. Why don&amp;rsquo;t I remember my physics training better? Bialek&amp;rsquo;s Phy562 notes still very helpful. No one else seems to write about this stuff clearly enough for me. Including me. 8a-11a
Catching up on reading. Good news and discussion items in Nature on publishing code and review materials, excellent piece on climate change scientists engaging media, climate high performance computing in Brazil; etc see headlines and links in my twitter feed archive for today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviews, organization, rewrites</title>
      <link>/2010/11/03/reviews-organization-rewrites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 05:20:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/03/reviews-organization-rewrites/</guid>
      <description>Today&amp;rsquo;s a mixed bag of activities. Finished a journal review, comments confidential, recorded in my reviewed papers archive. I then organized documents library (more below) and then back to paper revisions.
The reference manager software Mendeley recently upgraded the way it handles groups and sharing, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been waiting to revise how it impacts my workflow around articles. Articles can be organized into folders (collections) or kept unsorted within the library, and can be part of as multiple collections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrong picture, wrong model: why warning signals don&#39;t look like rare events</title>
      <link>/2010/10/25/wrong-picture-wrong-model-why-warning-signals-dont-look-like-rare-events/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2010 23:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/25/wrong-picture-wrong-model-why-warning-signals-dont-look-like-rare-events/</guid>
      <description>Detecting a warning signal of collapse isn&amp;rsquo;t about detecting that a system is non-stationary, but more specifically, that the system is about to do something sudden. The classic saddle-node bifurcation example results in a picture like this:
A visible steady decrease interrupted by a sudden jump. The goal is to distinguish this from the case of a steady decrease that involves no loss of stability &amp;ndash; such as would be created by continually lowering the carrying capacity of logistic-model system at a linear rate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab Notebooks</title>
      <link>/2010/09/07/lab-notebooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2010 08:23:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/09/07/lab-notebooks/</guid>
      <description>I strive for a transparent and reproducible research process. My lab notebooks are kept on an open wiki (via OpenWetWare). I curate the literature I read into several public lists (Mendeley), maintain my research source code and simulations on a collective database for open source development (Github), and am active on academic forums and mailing lists. These web-based tools make a largely automated, interlinked archive of my work I can search, update and share easily.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>