<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Semantics on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/semantics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Semantics on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 18:39:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/semantics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a semantic notebook</title>
      <link>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 18:39:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</guid>
      <description>What would a semantic lab notebook look like? What would be possible with such a structure, ideally? What is already possible now? There&amp;rsquo;s a lot that can be done with an electronic notebook that adds value over a paper notebook: browsing by categories and tags, embedding links, time-stamping entries, searching the full text, and having automated trackbacks or pingbacks when a post is mentioned in another post or appears elsewhere on the web.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citation tools &amp; Future of Publishing</title>
      <link>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 23:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of rapid development in scientific tools based on a Wordpress platform recently, perhaps spurred in part by the recent Beyond-the-PDF and sessions in Science Online conferences. A new discussion group has emerged around these tools, as described by Martin Fenner.
I have been exploring better tools for citation management within my lab notebook. Recently I have been using the papercite plugin to add citations from my BibTeX files, which are generated from Mendeley, as I described earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Semantic Notebook notes Reading
 Nice collection of posts on scholarly html, but too little mention of the serious linked data stuff coming out of biscol, ievobio/nescent, etc. In particular, Martin&amp;rsquo;s history gives some nice perspective.
 The war for schema. Which ontologies should we choose? (e.g. schema.org&amp;rsquo;s take  Puzzles
 How do we mix ontologies How do we meet Google Rich Snippets requirements using FOAF? How do we avoid redundant vocabulary terms?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>All notebook entries are formatted with XHTML compliant (polyglot) HTML5 semantic structure. This means that any entry can be parsed with a generic XML parser to extract the entry content in &amp;lt;article&amp;gt;, the &amp;lt;header&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;footer&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;aside&amp;gt;, etc. The &amp;lt;head&amp;gt; section provides &amp;lt;title&amp;gt; and essential &amp;lt;meta&amp;gt; tags declaring the character encoding (which also sets the MIME type for HTML5).
Head In _includes/header.html we introduce some basic academic archive metadata using the Dublin Core ontology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>C. Titus Brown has an excellent post discussing his exploration into the merits and technicalities cross-posting his blog posts to figshare. The rfigshare package written by Ted Hart and myself can do just this, once we puzzled out some of the same challenges (Notes to Titus: though the documentation doesn&amp;rsquo;t mention it, you can get a programmatic list of available categories from http://api.figshare.com/v1/categories. Figshare can also take code as a fileset or dataset, and may soon add a type for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Lab Notebook</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/semantic-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/semantic-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>As the lab notebook grows, to make the maximum use of content it would be particularly useful to maximize the ability for a computer to understand the content, allowing us to identify, manipulate, and connect data using scripts and software. This is the concept of linked data, or a semantic notebook. I have explored this this idea before in the context of a wordpress-based platform, but now that Jekyll has let me strip away some of the abstraction of Wordpress it seems a good time to revisit this idea.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>