<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Semantics on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/semantics.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Semantics on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/semantics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/07/25/formal-semantics-with-reml/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/25/formal-semantics-with-reml/</guid>
      <description>A lot has been happening in the reml development over on our package Github page, particularly through discussion on the issues tracker we have been working through several of the major conceptual challenges in designing the package.
Semantics Writing Semantics. Lots of elements of the EML schema have semantic meaning, but we can&amp;rsquo;t start leveraging ontological tools while these terms are defined only as part of the Schema vocabulary. In their current state, they are just &amp;ldquo;meaningless bits of syntax&amp;rdquo;, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/06/23/notes-on-leveraging-the-ecological-markup-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/23/notes-on-leveraging-the-ecological-markup-language/</guid>
      <description>This post creates new tag eml for posts discussing the Ecological Markup Langauge or the implementation of an R parser thereof (reml).
Why EML? Jones et al.(2005) give an excellent explanation describing the relative advantage of the descriptive metadata approach over vertically integrated repositories (such as Genbank, TreeBase, or many other repostories that have been the focus of rOpenSci development to date).
In short, the EML approach allows archiving of very heterogeneous data without having to standardize everything into a narrow and pre-defined syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notebook Features: parsing linked data in the semantic notebook</title>
      <link>/2013/04/04/notebook-parsing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/04/notebook-parsing/</guid>
      <description>In a post a while back I originally put forward the idea of a semantic lab notebook. Semantics, or linked data, are among the most powerful concepts to emerge in online science for scholarly data organization and communication. I have slowly been adding and exploring new ways to introduce semantic concepts into the notebook, which I have documented along the way under my #semantics tag. In this post, rather than discuss how to generate the semantic data, I try to focus on some of the things we can do with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/28/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/28/notes/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with Marc Selection of problem: consider simpler models only. Sep through complexity hierarchy at the beginning:
 classical approaches are to fix relationship of stock recruitment.
 parameter uncertainty Gaussian processes for model uncertainty  The Discussion section can deal with model uncertainty model choice approaches.
 A method where we don&amp;rsquo;t have to assume the stock recuritment relationship How well we can do with that.
 How much data we need.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/22/semantic-citations-for-the-notebook-and-knitr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/22/semantic-citations-for-the-notebook-and-knitr/</guid>
      <description>I have on ocassion been exploring the use of semantic markup in the notebook. In this post I illustrate how I am handling semantic citations. One of the more intriguing ideas is the ability to add semantic meaning to citations through the CITO ontology of Shotton (2010). Citation counts form a central part of academic discourse, but contain very little information regarding the reason for the citation. Most notably, &amp;lsquo;negative&amp;rsquo; citations refuting a claim carry just the same weight as those confirming or relying upon a claim.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/11/23/citing-lab-notebook-entries/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/23/citing-lab-notebook-entries/</guid>
      <description>C. Titus Brown has an excellent post discussing his exploration into the merits and technicalities cross-posting his blog posts to figshare. The rfigshare package written by Ted Hart and myself can do just this, once we puzzled out some of the same challenges (Notes to Titus: though the documentation doesn&amp;rsquo;t mention it, you can get a programmatic list of available categories from http://api.figshare.com/v1/categories. Figshare can also take code as a fileset or dataset, and may soon add a type for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/10/23/semantic-markup-examples-for-the-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/23/semantic-markup-examples-for-the-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>All notebook entries are formatted with XHTML compliant (polyglot) HTML5 semantic structure. This means that any entry can be parsed with a generic XML parser to extract the entry content in &amp;lt;article&amp;gt;, the &amp;lt;header&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;footer&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;aside&amp;gt;, etc. The &amp;lt;head&amp;gt; section provides &amp;lt;title&amp;gt; and essential &amp;lt;meta&amp;gt; tags declaring the character encoding (which also sets the MIME type for HTML5).
Head In _includes/header.html we introduce some basic academic archive metadata using the Dublin Core ontology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/10/19/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/19/notes/</guid>
      <description>Semantic Notebook notes Reading
 Nice collection of posts on scholarly html, but too little mention of the serious linked data stuff coming out of biscol, ievobio/nescent, etc. In particular, Martin&amp;rsquo;s history gives some nice perspective.
 The war for schema. Which ontologies should we choose? (e.g. schema.org&amp;rsquo;s take  Puzzles
 How do we mix ontologies How do we meet Google Rich Snippets requirements using FOAF? How do we avoid redundant vocabulary terms?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Semantic Lab Notebook</title>
      <link>/2012/10/14/semantic-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/14/semantic-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>As the lab notebook grows, to make the maximum use of content it would be particularly useful to maximize the ability for a computer to understand the content, allowing us to identify, manipulate, and connect data using scripts and software. This is the concept of linked data, or a semantic notebook. I have explored this this idea before in the context of a wordpress-based platform, but now that Jekyll has let me strip away some of the abstraction of Wordpress it seems a good time to revisit this idea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a semantic notebook</title>
      <link>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 18:39:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/08/building-a-semantic-notebook/</guid>
      <description>What would a semantic lab notebook look like? What would be possible with such a structure, ideally? What is already possible now? There&amp;rsquo;s a lot that can be done with an electronic notebook that adds value over a paper notebook: browsing by categories and tags, embedding links, time-stamping entries, searching the full text, and having automated trackbacks or pingbacks when a post is mentioned in another post or appears elsewhere on the web.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citation tools &amp; Future of Publishing</title>
      <link>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 23:04:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/16/citation-tools-future-of-publishing/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of rapid development in scientific tools based on a Wordpress platform recently, perhaps spurred in part by the recent Beyond-the-PDF and sessions in Science Online conferences. A new discussion group has emerged around these tools, as described by Martin Fenner.
I have been exploring better tools for citation management within my lab notebook. Recently I have been using the papercite plugin to add citations from my BibTeX files, which are generated from Mendeley, as I described earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>