<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Progress Summary on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/progress-summary.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Progress Summary on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2011 23:46:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/progress-summary/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic Year 2011 Summary</title>
      <link>/2011/08/21/academic-year-2011-summary.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2011 23:46:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/21/academic-year-2011-summary.html</guid>
      <description>Brief summary of events for this past academic year, as submitted to my dissertation committee.
TALKS  Model Choice for Phylogenetic Comparative Methods, Evolution 2010 Computational Methods for comparative inference (poster), DoE CSGF Meeting, 2010. My experiment with open notebook science, iEvoBio 2010 Power in Phylogenetic Comparative Methods, SICB 2011 Open Notebook Science - Connections to databases. Science Online, 2011 General model of evolution for continuous traits on phylogenies, Evolution 2011 Automated meta-analyses via an R - TreeBASE package, iEvoBio 2011 Early Warning Signals, ESA 2011.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DoE renewal and a year in review</title>
      <link>/2010/12/24/doe-renewal-and-a-year-in-review.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Dec 2010 03:24:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/24/doe-renewal-and-a-year-in-review.html</guid>
      <description>This time of year I have to file my renewal for my DOE Fellowship, including a statement of accomplishments and a summary of the computational aspects of my work. Seemed like a good idea to jot these down in my notebook as well:
synopsis of accomplishments over the year: In January I passed my qualifying exam, advancing to candidacy where my dissertation remains my only requirement. In March I attended the phylogenetics workshop in Bodega Bay, an internationally known week-long training program.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>