<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Multiple_uncertainty on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/categories/multiple_uncertainty/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Multiple_uncertainty on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/multiple_uncertainty/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/05/02/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/02/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</guid>
      <description>Logistic recruitment, uniform noise (Sethi Fig 3 configuration)
Logistic recruitment, lognormal noise Beverton-Holt recruitement, uniform noise Beverton-Holt recruitement, lognormal noise Logistic recruitment, uniform noise, small r Logistic recruitment, lognormal noise, small r Metadata From scenarios_meta.txt
Columns: y_grid: The observed stock size escapement: The optimal escapement policy. (y_grid value minus the escapement is the quota). sigma_g: The growth noise scaling factor sigma_m: The measurement error scaling factor (between observed stock x and measured stock y) sigma_i: The implementation noise scaling factor (between quota q set and harvest h realized).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/04/23/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/04/23/multiple-uncertainty-notes/</guid>
      <description>Multiple uncertainty Handling variation in different grids. Cleaned up a bunch of transpose expressions in the code and make sure that dimensions are always properly aligned. Now problem can be solved on arbitrarily different grid discritizations for stock $x$, observed stock $y$, harvest $h$ and quota $q$. See multiple_uncertainty.m and example calls in testing.m
Taking a look a how we handle normalization when some of the probability density falls outside the discritized space.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>