<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conference on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conference on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/11/17/wssspe-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/11/17/wssspe-feedback/</guid>
      <description>WSSSPE working groups: Reproducibility, Reuse, and Sharing (Neil Che Hong) Our group focused on journal policies regarding software papers. Our objectives were:
 A Survey of journals that publish software papers. The Software Sustainability Institute already maintains a list
 A summary of policies each of these journals has in place regarding software papers. (e.g. licensing requirements, repository requirements, required sections in the manuscripts regarding installation or tests, etc).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DIMACS Workshop on Global Change</title>
      <link>/2014/05/21/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/21/notes/</guid>
      <description>Program Website My slides   Venue: 2063 Valley Life Science Building. 8:00 - 8:30 Registration and Breakfast 8:30 - 9:00 Welcome and Background 9:00 - 9:40 Revolutionizing Science &amp; Mathematics Education: the global change challenge Mark McCaffrey, National Center of Science Education 9:40 - 10:20 Mathematics and Climate: A New Partnership Hans Kaper, Georgetown University 10:20 - 10:50 Break 10:50 - 11:30 The Application of Information Theory to Ecology John Harte, University of California - Berkeley 11:30 - 12:10 A GIS Global Change Case Study Kevin Koy, University of California - Berkeley 12:10 - 1:30 Lunch 1:30 - 3:00 Panel 1: Communicating Global Change: Minda Berbeco, National Center of Science Education, Barbara Cozzens, Holly Gaff, Old Dominion University 3:00 - 3:30 Break 3:30 - 5:30 Contributed Talks: Sea-ice Albedo Feedback and the Tipping Points in Algae Dynamics Ivan Sudakov, University of Utah Predicting Future Extinction Debt from Present-Day Community Patterns Justin Kitzes, University of California-Berkeley Optimal Control of Restoration - the Role of Economic Threshold Adam Lampert, University of California-Davis Both Climate Change and Land Use Change Influenceinvasive Species&#39; Future Ranges Jennifer Weaver, University of California-Berkeley Towards a National Early Warning System for Human West Nile Virus Incidence Carrie Manore, Tulane University Wastes to Fuel - Waste a Valuable Resource Viral Sagar, Rutgers University 6:00 - 9:00 Banquet Dinner and Talk Finding the Sweet Spot Richard Salter, Oberlin College Location: The Faculty Club Howard Room University of California, Berkeley Tuesday, May 20, 2014 8:00 - 8:30 Breakfast 8:30 - 9:10 Massive Data Set Management and Analysis in the Context of Global Change Carl Boettiger, University of California - Santa Cruz 9:10 - 9:50 Understanding Socio-Ecosystems as Complex Networks in Changing Environments Neo Martinez, University of Arizona 9:50 - 10:30 Applications of GIS in Emerging Zoonotic Processes Jason Blackburn, University of Florida 10:30 - 11:00 Break 11:00 - 12:20 Panel 2: Data Deluge or Drought (Quality and Quantity): David Ackerly, University of California - Berkeley, Fred Roberts, Rutgers University, Philip Stark, University of California - Berkeley 12:20 - 1:30 Lunch 1:30 - 3:00 Workshops 1 and 2 (in parallel) 1: Student driven: Using Mathematics to Interface Global and Ecosystem Processes 2: Student driven: Using Mathematics to Link Individual and Population Level Processes 3:00 - 3:30 Break 3:30 - 4:30 Workshops 1 and 2 (continue) 1: Student driven: Using Mathematics to Interface Global and Ecosystem Processes 2: Student driven: Using Mathematics to Link Individual and Population Level Processes 4:30 - 5:00 Workshop report back Wednesday, May 21, 2014 8:00 - 8:30 Breakfast 8:30 - 9:10 When All Models are Wrong Andrea Saltelli, European Commission JRC 9:10 - 10:30 Panel 3: Are Our Models Adequate for Policy Formation: Solomon Hsiang, University of California - Berkeley, Donald Lucas, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratories, A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/02/07/nceas-workflows-day3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/07/nceas-workflows-day3/</guid>
      <description>(Day 2 work) Hack-a-thon; no notebook entry but all progress appears in group Github repo: github.com/NCEAS/commdyn/. 78 Commits in 2 days, nice work team.
Discussion of challenges and opportunities in open data and ecological workflows
Synthesis and Reporting back
Group 1.5 Plan Product 1: Paper: Visualizing global change in long term community ecology studies: the strawmen?
 Lead: Sydney Jones  Long-term ecological research (LTER) sites have been collecting and publishing raw community ecology data for over 30 years from across the US and across a wide array of taxa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/02/05/workflows-working-group-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/05/workflows-working-group-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Goals  Develop ideas for larger synthesis across systems Introduce scientists to the concept of workflow systems Introduce scientists to open data and methods sharing Gather requirements for collaboration tools that would allow scientists to use them and share data and workflows.  Participants  Ilkay Altintas, UC San Diego, Carl Boettiger, UC Davis, Erica Christensen, Utah State, Elsa Cleland, UCSD, Scott Collins, U New Mexico, Sam Fey, Dartmouth, Corinna Gries, U Wisconsin, Lauren Hallett, Berkeley, Stan Harpole, Iowa State, Dave Harris, UC Davis, Matt Jones, UC Santa Barbara, Sydney Jones, U New Mexico, Julie Ripplinger, Arizona State University, Andrew Rypel, WDNR, David Seekell, UVa, Elizabeth Siddon, U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/01/15/asn-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/15/asn-conference/</guid>
      <description>Note: posting this considerably after the fact as I did not have a chance to make a proper entry during the conference.
 Full program, abstracts, etc.
 President&amp;rsquo;s debate: are ecological communities saturated in species diversity? Watch the whole debate on youtube tweet log, maybe?. Or from the editor&amp;rsquo;s desk  Some highlights (such as on the top of my head 2 months later anyway, certainly others I&amp;rsquo;ve forgotten to mention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/08/mbi-day-five-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/08/mbi-day-five-notes/</guid>
      <description>Panel discussion
 Hugh&amp;rsquo;s question on the usefulness of dynamic vs static models: do we have dynamical systems envy? Chris: are temporal dynamics historical artefact, and space the new frontier? Hugh: though decision theory is fundamentally temporal. really question of sequential decision vs single decision Hugh, on what would be his priority if he had time for new question: Solve the 2 player, 2 step SDP competition closed form.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/07/mbi-day-four-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/07/mbi-day-four-notes/</guid>
      <description>Morning session Iadine Chades  Chadès, I., Carwardine, J., Martin, T.G., Nicol, S., Sabbadin, R. &amp;amp; Buffet, O. (2012) MOMDPs: a solution for modelling adaptive management problems. The Twenty-Sixth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-12), pp. 267-273. Toronto, Canada.
 10.1098/rspb.2013.0325 Migratory connectivity magnifies the consequences of habitat loss from sea-level rise for shorebird populations
  Jake LaRiviera presents the challenges of the uncertainty table. Additional challenges in making an apples-to-apples comparison of the benefit of decreasing noise of different systems (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/06/mbi-day-three/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/06/mbi-day-three/</guid>
      <description>MBI Workshop Becky Epanchin-Niell  Motivating example of Rabies spatial control in Switzerland
 2012 Eco Let: should New Zealand survey for bark beetle? Cost of survellience, control, and damage. Epanchin-Niell et al. (2012)
 2012 JEEM spatial spread of star thistle: control spread and eradication as an integer programming problem in deterministic context. (with Wilen) Epanchin-Niell &amp;amp; Wilen (2012)
 Breaking landscape into individual landowners makes it less valuable to control early.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/05/mbi-day-two/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/05/mbi-day-two/</guid>
      <description>MBI Workshop Paul Armsworth Very nice example of control in creating a market for ecosystem services for landowners. Key feature is that multiple land-owners respond by adjusting their prices, and so payments can be divided into fraction going into subsidy and fraction going into conservation. When one land-owner controls land that is particularly good cost per conservation accomplished, they also stand to gain largest value.
Also looked at auction mechanism and impact of cooperation among landowners to create hold outs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/11/04/mbi-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/04/mbi-notes/</guid>
      <description>SUSTAINABLE MANAGEMENT OF LIVING NATURAL RESOURCES  Description Full Schedule Participants  Introductions Hastings Lou Gross  Big picture: big data, computational challenges.
 NEON, DataONE, ADW, iDigBio &amp;ldquo;Convergence&amp;rdquo; as the new interdisciplinary (National Academies) Rise of synthesis centers &amp;ldquo;Enabling architecture for next gen life science research&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; National Academies report Lou Gross (2013) Comp Science for Natural Resource Management &amp;ndash; Fuller, Wang, Gross (2007)
 language barriers: What&amp;rsquo;s a model?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/11/isees-workforce-development-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/11/isees-workforce-development-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Near the end of another excellent day of discussions we were asked to put pen to paper to outline our own views in writing. My own contribution was the following notebook scribble.
My own vision of what ISEES should be doing for workforce development:
ISEES would employ a multi-scale approach to improve basic computational expertise across the entire workforce necessary to fully participate in the modern software-immersed world of research through the development of training standards, while using a working-group model focused on emerging researcher-developer communities which would simultaneously improve the quality and synthesis of existing software tools while also delivering essential skills to the most transformative members of the research software communities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/10/isees-training-workshop-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/10/isees-training-workshop-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Education / Workforce Development Group Cannot do grand synthesis opaquely and be science. must be able to scale and evolve.
How did data succeed? What features really made the difference and what were just sideshows?
 Sticks (Funder and journal mandates?) Working groups (NCEAS) Training external forces: there is more data.
  Why one center? Why not 15 centers? Divided by discipline rather than region&amp;hellip;. synthesize the synthesis centers</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/08/14/isees-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/14/isees-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Other services: Tangible infrastructure support services  Discovery registration system. Includes:  Software review and certification Use and quality metrics Ticket tracking Seed funding to join the ecosystem   Community Building  user defined registry  // Hackathon?
Consulting services  Support software lifecycle
 Function: Assist in full lifecycle software development: e.g. (and order notwithstanding) initiation, licensing, maintenance, hardening, extensible, release, decommissioning
 Mechanisms:
 Call for Proposals - to solicit consulting help (or to nominate a project to receive help) (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ISEES software lifecycle and components workshop, Day 1</title>
      <link>/2013/08/13/isees-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/13/isees-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Range of large project to the long tail.
 statistical analyses One-off models community model Services (Blast)  Science Challenges Outcomes of previous community workshops
18 Grand Challenge areas. Highlights: Supermodels. human/biophysical systems shape and be shaped by water availability. (A vision similar to Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Model all Earth&amp;rdquo; Purves et al)
Functions and services areas: (priority ordering)
 Computational training (early career - all career) Assimilation and QA/QC tools Collaborative environment decisions and workflows software discovery consultants / collaborator community hub to converge on standards merging disparate tools user-friendly interfaces multiscale coupled modeling framework Software vetting (how about paper vetting?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/08/08/esa-2013-notes-for-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/08/esa-2013-notes-for-week/</guid>
      <description>Sun Co-Leading the Workshop on R, DataONE and open science.
All material on github
Mon  Ives Plenary  Talking to Dave, Vasilis, Tye,
 Lunch Vasilis, Ryan Batt
 2:30 Chesson L100H / Ryan Batt L100J
 3:20 O&amp;rsquo;Regan L100H
 3:40 Adler L100H
 4 Yaekel M100HC
 ropensci meetup, funded by Github. Great turnout, great success. (And rare shot of dev team together in person).
 Theoretical ecology mixer</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/07/11/visit-to-whoi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/11/visit-to-whoi/</guid>
      <description>Presented my work from the nonparametric-bayes project, Avoiding tipping points in the management of ecological systems: a non-parametric Bayesian approach at the Woods Hole Oceangraphic Institution as part of their weekly Biology Department Seminar Series.
 9 - 9:30 Julie Kellner 9:30-10:15 Ben Jones, (Kellner group) 10:15 - 11:00 Math ecology group 11:00 - 11:30 Ian Carroll 11:30-12 Seminar prep 12-1 my seminar 1-2 Lunch with the Marine Policy Center (Mike Fogarty, Hauke Kite-Powell, Di Jin), Julie Kellner  Enjoyable visit, with some particularly great questions after talk: including challenges/opportunities in multi-dimensional examples, concerns about temporal heterogeneity, partially observed systems / working with catch data in place of stock assessment data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/11/03/altmetrics-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/11/03/altmetrics-conference/</guid>
      <description>From Thursday Nov 1 through Saturday Nov 3 I attended the PLoS Altmetrics workshop as a member of the ROpensci project. An exciting meeting driven mostly by the opportunity to interact with a small and incredibly creative and innovative group of science publishers, funders, start-ups, and other researchers. Details of the event are largely recorded on the altmetrics 2012 workshop website. We also have a few slides addressing the ropensci slant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/08/10/esa-2012-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/08/10/esa-2012-conference/</guid>
      <description>My Schedule Meetings/discussion with Don Strong, Tony Ives, Marten Scheffer, Justin Yeakel, Karen Abbott, Jarrett Byrnes, Christopher Lortie.
 Check in with Paul Armsworth on working group rOpenSci tutorial session (below) tweetup My contributed talk (below)  rOpenSci tutorial, Thursday A year out from our launch at ESA last year, we presented an introduction and tutorial on rOpenSci. Slides and links to more information are all available at esa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/07/27/csgf-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/27/csgf-conference/</guid>
      <description>Conference Agenda Alumni-organized Plus-One Day Agenda Great chance to talk with US Secretary of the Department of Energy Stephen Chu Interesting leadership training session lead by improv acting professional Raquel Holmes of ImprovScience
  Video recording of my talk  Slides:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution and iEvobio conference notes</title>
      <link>/2012/07/09/evolution-conf-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/09/evolution-conf-summary/</guid>
      <description>Saturday  Jeremy Brown Graham Slater (Education Data Symposium) Cecile Ane Joe Felsenstein Lars Schmitz Carl Boettiger Liam Revell Brian O&amp;rsquo;Meara (Leithan McGonigle)  Sunday  Marie-Josee Fortin Emma Goldberg 10:45 rm 209 Networks Symposium Jeremy Fox 1.30p Rm 201 (Adaptation B) Schluter 2:15p Canada 2-3 Rosie Redfield public lecture  Monday  9:00 Michael Landis, 203 9:30 Dick Gumolkiowicz 214 10:30 Dean Adams 11 (Cavender-Bares, 214) (Bolnick, 213) 11:30 Mark McPeek 214  Tuesday  Luke Harmon 9am rm 214 Luke Mahler 9am rm 210 Rafael Maia 9:15a rm 210 Sam Price 11:15a rm 210 Liam Revell 11:30 Canada 2-3 Dan Rabosky 2:30pm Canada 2-3 Tanja Stadler 3pm Canada 2-3 Chris Martin 3pm rm 213  Also: ievobio Day 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution 2012 Conference, Day 1</title>
      <link>/2012/07/08/evolution-day1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/08/evolution-day1/</guid>
      <description>Fantastic first day at Evolution. Spent the morning in the SSB Sympossium organized by Jeremy Brown, &amp;ldquo;Predictive approaches for assessing the fit of evolutionary models&amp;rdquo;. Really covered both methods assessing model fit (posterior predictive simulations) and approximate likelihood approaches, which are also simulation-based. Then the afternoon in the second SSB Symposium on emerging methods for comparative phylogenetics, organized by Liam Revell and Cecile Ane, which included my talk. Lots of great talks, but Cecile&amp;rsquo;s was perhaps the most striking results I saw presented all day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/06/24/ievobio-lightning-talk-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/06/24/ievobio-lightning-talk-proposal/</guid>
      <description>The rOpenSci Project Carl Boettiger, Scott Chamberlain, Karthik Ram Sharing scientific data is a win for individual scientists as well as for the larger enterprise of other researchers, publishers, funders, educators, and the general public. Despite the rapid increase of public data, most researchers continue to work on their own data just as before. We lack the both the tools and training to quickly and easily leverage such data. To address some of these challenges, we have created the rOpenSci project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data to Knowledge Day II and other notes</title>
      <link>/2012/05/08/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/05/08/notes/</guid>
      <description>Great second day at the Data to Knowledge conference (a few notes below).
Also I have been trying to move a few projects forward during the commute and break. I&amp;rsquo;ve sent Alan my revisions on the prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s fallacy manuscript, getting pretty close. Following up on a query from John, ran a simulation showing the impact of having a delay in the timeseries before the slow change towards the bifurcation begins.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data to Knowledge Day 1</title>
      <link>/2012/05/07/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/05/07/notes/</guid>
      <description>Scaling Time Series Data Mining to trillions of series Eamonn Keogh
 Similarity search is the fundamental problem for any task This problem is now solved. As effective as possible, as efficient as possible.  What is similarity search? All about required invariances: Looking at ancient manuscripts of fish &amp;ndash; identify multiple drawings of the same species. Invariant to color, scale, and orientation.
(Note that rotation becomes phase, easy to handle).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data to Knowledge Conference, UC Berkeley: application </title>
      <link>/2012/03/29/data-to-knowledge-conference-uc-berkeley-application-abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2012 12:08:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/29/data-to-knowledge-conference-uc-berkeley-application-abstract/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve just been accepted to the Data to Knowledge Conference in Berkeley this May. I think this conference will address some of the key issues facing us in Big Data today across many different fields, and I hope to learn much that could be useful to ecology and evolution. Given the audience I look forward to being a source of questions rather than answers as I put on my biologist&amp;rsquo;s cap.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DataCite Day 2</title>
      <link>/2011/08/25/datacite-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2011 08:14:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/25/datacite-day-2/</guid>
      <description>9:00am-10:30am Session 4: Data and the Scholarly Output  MacKenzie Smith, Research Director, MIT Libraries. Orcid: the Open Researcher and Contributor ID Registry. (slides)
 Greg Janee, Digital Library Research Specialist, Earth Research Institute, University of California, Santa Barbara. Earth Science Data:Second-Class Citizen in the Scholarly Record.
  see great example of the ACRID database
 Dr. Micah Altman, Archival Director, Henry A. Murray Research Archive, Senior Research Scientist, Harvard University.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DataCite Day 1</title>
      <link>/2011/08/24/datacite-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2011 08:10:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/24/datacite-day-1/</guid>
      <description>12:00pm-1:00pm Lunch
 1:15pm-2:00pm Keynote Address: John Wilbanks, Vice President for Science, Creative Commons. Citation in the Commons. (Slides)    Find -&amp;gt; access -&amp;gt; understand -&amp;gt; be influenced -&amp;gt; cite.
Lesson of the Library of Babel, Early Web (Greenspun, 1995) Simple and weak is best &amp;ndash; scalable. (Rule of least power).
 2:00pm-3:30pm Session 1: Exposing Dataset DOIs and Citations
 Heather Piwowar, DataONE Postdoctoral Researcher, NESCent and Dryad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA personal notes: people, goals</title>
      <link>/2011/08/13/esa-personal-notes-people-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2011 19:22:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/13/esa-personal-notes-people-goals/</guid>
      <description>Meetings  John Drake Suzanne O&amp;rsquo;Regan (Post-doc with John, strong dynamical systems) Justin Kinze &amp;ndash; great post-doc at Berkeley with John Harte, should visit. Paul Armsworth &amp;ndash; with Alan, have asked me to join NIMBioS working group on Pretty Darn Good Control (Tuesday evening). Hal Caswell &amp;ndash; interested in some of the data management / provenance for theoretical work. (Mon) Jeremy Fox &amp;ndash; Interesting lunch discussion, clonal interference as ecological insight?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/12/esa-friday/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 18:34:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/12/esa-friday/</guid>
      <description>Great last day of the conference, despite noticeably decreased attendance. Once again just pulling in my tweets, since I haven&amp;rsquo;t had a chance to transcribe proper notes. Meanwhile, some of the bloggers have done a rather nice day-to-day coverage; no idea how they all manage to keep up. Links below, with a nice mix of those targeting more theory oriented, more application oriented and more outreach oriented sessions.
Twitter-log    cboettig ESA should have science cafes!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/11/esa-thursday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2011 18:43:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/11/esa-thursday/</guid>
      <description>Just automatically generating a log form twitter since I cannot find the time to write proper notes. Perhaps those will amended eventually&amp;hellip;
Twitter-log    cboettig Predicting rare; predicting ubiquitous/noxious weed species by machine learning vs GLMs #esa11
   cboettig Beautiful thing when you know just how talk methods will proceed after 2 min of intro to problem.. but stay tuned for surprises #esa11
   cboettig Deitterich: how to reconstruct life history patterns from abundance fluctuations #esa11 inferring what we want from what we have w models</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/10/esa-wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2011 18:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/10/esa-wednesday/</guid>
      <description>My talk today, as well as several others from our Theory group at Davis. Journal review requirements mean posting my slides is gonna be delayed somewhat, but appreciated some excellent questions and those who laughed at my jokes in between slides. Meanwhile, automatically generating a log form twitter since I cannot find the time to write proper notes. Perhaps those will amended eventually&amp;hellip;
Twitter-log    cboettig @carlystrasser Here&amp;rsquo;s the paper I mentioned for introducing ontologies/linked data into spreadsheetshttp://t.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/09/esa-tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2011 18:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/09/esa-tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Just automatically generating a log form twitter since I cannot find the time to write proper notes. Perhaps those will amended eventually&amp;hellip;
twitter-log    cboettig Great Eco Let mixer. Kudos to Marcel &amp;amp; crew for increasing citation rates w/o decreasing acceptance. Now how bout data sharing reqs? #esa11
   cboettig RT @IceAgeEcologist: #ESA11 Marten Scheffer gets Honorary Member Award (max 20 living awardees); Don Strong ge… (cont) http://deck.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: ESA Conference</title>
      <link>/2011/08/08/monday-esa-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 13:09:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/08/monday-esa-conference/</guid>
      <description>Hope to process the day&amp;rsquo;s happenings later, meanwhile just a snapshot of my twitter-stream notes. My own highlights certainly include Steve Pacala&amp;rsquo;s fantastic plenary session in receiving the MacArthur award, and Mark Urban&amp;rsquo;s crystal clear presentation on &amp;ldquo;climate collisions.&amp;rdquo; I thought I was less tolerant of data-free models with arbitrary assumptions these days, but somehow Mark just swept those concerns away. In pointing out really fundamental concepts, such details just aren&amp;rsquo;t so important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF Conference Notes</title>
      <link>/2011/07/24/csgf-conference-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 14:30:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/24/csgf-conference-notes/</guid>
      <description>Just returned from 5 days in Washington, DC for the annual computational science graduate fellowship conference. No live notes/tweets, so just attempting to synthesize some of the major ideas before I get back to paper writing. Most of the conference material, including workshop slides, are archived online.
The high performance computing workshop made two things clear to me &amp;ndash; a lot of parallel computing can be done without lots of communication between nodes (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CSGF 2010 Computing Practices Survey Summary</title>
      <link>/2011/07/24/csgf-2010-computing-practices-survey-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 14:11:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/24/csgf-2010-computing-practices-survey-summary/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to everyone who participated in the CSGF 2010 Survey.With too many things going on this year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t conduct a survey at the 2011 Conference. But as people were asking about the survey, I thought I could at least make last year&amp;rsquo;s summary a bit more accessible. The following comes from the pdf report I submitted to Krell and a few example figures from data.This year&amp;rsquo;s survey was longer and broader, recieving over 90 responses from fellows and alumni.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#ievobio Day 2</title>
      <link>/2011/06/22/ievobio-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 23:44:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/22/ievobio-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Day 2 is every bit as packed as day 1, and then some do to the higher concentration of lightning talks. Other coverage of #ievobio is starting to find it&amp;rsquo;s way to the web:
 Nico Cellinese
 Scott Chamberlain
 Rob Guralnick
  Meanwhile, my scratchpad of notes from day 2, tweet-style.
My Lightning Talk Gave my lightning talk in this session, slides:
R interface to TreeBASE</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Day 4 / #ievobio Day 1</title>
      <link>/2011/06/21/evolution-day-4-ievobio-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2011 23:44:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/21/evolution-day-4-ievobio-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Start of the ievobio conference, simultaneously the forth day of evolution. ievobio conference was very busy, luckily given the nature of the conference it is also largely well documented online. My notes are again archived primarily in tweet form below. My personal highlights of the day included the Keynote by Cladio Silva on Provenance &amp;ndash; essentially supporting reproducible research workflows &amp;ndash; and examples through his vistrails software, and Mark Yoder&amp;rsquo;s demonstration of mx at the software bazaar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Day 3</title>
      <link>/2011/06/20/evolution-day-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2011 23:44:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/20/evolution-day-3/</guid>
      <description>Talks  David Babst: Patterns of diversification on large species level supertree of extinct graptolites &amp;ndash; Actually, more on methods for making such a supertree for extinct taxa than on diversification analysis, but excellent talk.
 Gene Hunt: _Using fossils to test the link between speciation and phenotypic evolution &amp;ndash; _another highlight of the talks, really looking at cladeogeneic vs anaogenic models of evolutionary change, modifying the approach of Folmer Bokma</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides from my talk at Evolution 2011</title>
      <link>/2011/06/20/slides-from-my-talk-at-evolution-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2011 20:59:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/20/slides-from-my-talk-at-evolution-2011/</guid>
      <description>A general model of continuous character evolution [iframe http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/8371419 425 355]
View more presentations from Carl Boettiger
As highlighted in the last slide (following acknowledgments), clicking on the results graphs will take you to the image repository, which records when the result was generated in my workstream, and provides a link to the script, software package and data to replicate. Code is parallel, examples shown took between 2 and 12 hours on a 16-core cpu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Day 2</title>
      <link>/2011/06/19/evolution-day-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2011 23:44:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/19/evolution-day-2/</guid>
      <description>Second day of the conference. Many of the talks I most want to see are coming up Monday and Tuesday, and I have a bit more to do to prepare my own talk, so I take it a bit light on sessions. Highlight of the day was definitely the discussion with Mark McPeek and the other journal editors during and following the &amp;ldquo;Happy hour with the editors&amp;rdquo; session, which was perhaps the best event of the conference, despite a rather unimpressive attendance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution Conference Day 1</title>
      <link>/2011/06/18/evolution-conference-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2011 21:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/18/evolution-conference-day-1/</guid>
      <description>Morning Sessions SSB Symposium 8:30 - noon: Unified Approaches for Understanding Patterns of Character Evolution and Diversification  Stacey Smith (U. of Nebraska-Lincoln) and Boris Igic (U.of Illinois-Chicago) - &amp;ldquo;Introduction to models of character state-dependent diversification&amp;rdquo;  Introduces the BiSSE model.
 Richard Fitzjohn (U. of British Columbia) - &amp;ldquo;Stochastic mapping incorporating differential diversification&amp;rdquo;  BiSSE comparison to traditional discrete-trait transition rate which ignores the correlation.
 Folmer Bokma (Umeå University) - &amp;ldquo;Estimating speciation and extinction with incomplete phylogenies&amp;rdquo;   Emma Goldberg (University of Illinois-Chicago) - &amp;ldquo;Modes of speciation and character change from phylogenetic trees&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finishing up my #SICB Presentation</title>
      <link>/2011/01/02/finishing-up-my-sicb-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2011 21:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/02/finishing-up-my-sicb-presentation/</guid>
      <description>Finished up my SICB presentation tweaks, slides now up on slideshare, flying off to the conference tomorrow. Created this in OpenOffice, started adding animations and then decided it would be more reliable to just duplicate slides to have parts appear (really just for the explanation of the likelihood ratio distributions under each model). Next time think I&amp;rsquo;ll stick with my usual inkscape slides tied together with latex beamer, the lack of vector images in this one is not ideal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit</title>
      <link>/2010/07/29/open-science-summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/07/29/open-science-summit/</guid>
      <description>First day of the Open Science Summit, began with excellent panel discussion including Cameron Neylon, Victoria Stodden, Peter Murray-Rust and Jason Hoyt. Followed by great lineup of short talks, but behind schedule and no breaks.
 Conference Schedule Backchannel twitter archive A neat backchannel question proposing site used for the conference.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graham &amp; Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/2010/06/09/graham-and-peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/06/09/graham-and-peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Fantastic meeting with Graham and Peter today, covered a lot of ground.
MNV I briefly sketched the multivariate normal solution for joint probability across the tree under the regimes model. The original regimes approach did not take advantage of the fact that the solution to the joint probability across the tree is multivariate normal given the painting. This allows the calculation to be partitioned as outlined in Saturday&amp;rsquo;s entry:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio lightning talk</title>
      <link>/2010/04/27/ievobio-lightning-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/27/ievobio-lightning-talk/</guid>
      <description>Submitting a five minute lighting talk on open science. Submitted version here, final text below. See the page revision history for earlier drafts and the original call below. Special thanks to Sam, Alistair, Betta, Shaun, and Alex for feedback.
My experiment with open science: Why the benefits of sharing go beyond source code The practice and philosophy of open source run deep within the iEvoBio community. Sharing source code has made software development faster and more reliable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio Submission</title>
      <link>/2010/04/16/ievobio-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/16/ievobio-submission/</guid>
      <description>Quantifying Information in a Phylogenetic Tree: The Robustness of Phylogenetic Signal Since Felsenstein (1985)&amp;rsquo;s influential paper on phylogenetic contrasts, phylogenetically-based inferences of evolutionary patterns have gotten increasingly more complex (Hansen, 1997; Butler and King, 2004; Freckleton and Harvey, 2006; O&amp;rsquo;Meara et al., 2006; Pagel and Meade, 2006). More and more sophisticated models are applied to datasets of species mean traits on a phylogenetic tree in an attempt to answer such questions as reconstructing ancestral states, identify changes in rates of character evolution across time and across clades, identify the number and location of evolutionary optima or the strength of stabilizing selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/04/12/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/04/12/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Notes potentially for my EDG talk.
&amp;ldquo;Keeping Up&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a talk to EDG? Science is growing. Fast. Number of papers published. Genomes on Genbank. Software on CRAN. Everyone&amp;rsquo;s felt the pressure. So what do we do? Keeping with tradition, I&amp;rsquo;ll present my own work in developing comparative phylogenetic methods to identify niche differentiation in Labrid fish. I will try and use this context to pose the question &amp;ndash; what do we do about this information explosion?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>