<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conference on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conference on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Notes potentially for my EDG talk.
&amp;ldquo;Keeping Up&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a talk to EDG? Science is growing. Fast. Number of papers published. Genomes on Genbank. Software on CRAN. Everyone&amp;rsquo;s felt the pressure. So what do we do? Keeping with tradition, I&amp;rsquo;ll present my own work in developing comparative phylogenetic methods to identify niche differentiation in Labrid fish. I will try and use this context to pose the question &amp;ndash; what do we do about this information explosion?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graham &amp; Peter Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/graham--peter-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/graham--peter-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Fantastic meeting with Graham and Peter today, covered a lot of ground.
MNV I briefly sketched the multivariate normal solution for joint probability across the tree under the regimes model. The original regimes approach did not take advantage of the fact that the solution to the joint probability across the tree is multivariate normal given the painting. This allows the calculation to be partitioned as outlined in Saturday&amp;rsquo;s entry:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Science Summit</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/open-science-summit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/open-science-summit/</guid>
      <description>First day of the Open Science Summit, began with excellent panel discussion including Cameron Neylon, Victoria Stodden, Peter Murray-Rust and Jason Hoyt. Followed by great lineup of short talks, but behind schedule and no breaks.
 Conference Schedule Backchannel twitter archive A neat backchannel question proposing site used for the conference.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio Submission</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ievobio-submission/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ievobio-submission/</guid>
      <description>Quantifying Information in a Phylogenetic Tree: The Robustness of Phylogenetic Signal Since Felsenstein (1985)&amp;rsquo;s influential paper on phylogenetic contrasts, phylogenetically-based inferences of evolutionary patterns have gotten increasingly more complex (Hansen, 1997; Butler and King, 2004; Freckleton and Harvey, 2006; O&amp;rsquo;Meara et al., 2006; Pagel and Meade, 2006). More and more sophisticated models are applied to datasets of species mean traits on a phylogenetic tree in an attempt to answer such questions as reconstructing ancestral states, identify changes in rates of character evolution across time and across clades, identify the number and location of evolutionary optima or the strength of stabilizing selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iEvoBio lightning talk</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/ievobio-lightning-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/ievobio-lightning-talk/</guid>
      <description>Submitting a five minute lighting talk on open science. Submitted version here, final text below. See the page revision history for earlier drafts and the original call below. Special thanks to Sam, Alistair, Betta, Shaun, and Alex for feedback.
My experiment with open science: Why the benefits of sharing go beyond source code The practice and philosophy of open source run deep within the iEvoBio community. Sharing source code has made software development faster and more reliable.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>