<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Workflow on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/workflow/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Workflow on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/workflow/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/07/10/notes-on-tricks-in-manuscript-submission-and-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/07/10/notes-on-tricks-in-manuscript-submission-and-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>Some thoughts on collaborating with markdown / dynamic document workflow Collaborating on manuscripts with other researchers when not writing in MS Word has been a perpetual nuisance for those of us not using Word (no doubt the others might say the same). When I first began writing papers I worked in LaTeX, and at that time I collaborated largely with others who already knew TeX (e.g. my mentors), so this wasn&amp;rsquo;t much of a problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep challenges to dynamic documentation in daily workflows</title>
      <link>/2014/05/05/knitr-workflow-challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/05/knitr-workflow-challenges/</guid>
      <description>We often discuss dynamic documents such as Sweave and knitr in reference to final products such as publications or software package vignettes. In this case, all the elements involved are already fixed: external functions, code, text, and so forth. The dynamic documentation engine is really just a tool to combine them (knit them together). Using dynamic documentation on a day-to-day basis on ongoing research presents a compelling opportunity but a rather more complex challenge as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday / Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 23:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday/</guid>
      <description>rfishbase updated to Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback writing intro section on Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy. wrightscape update project repository. Scripts mostly in demos, results in notebook. Notebook makes is easy to get the most recent writeup on the topic, from where I can start to track back the history, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide a good at-a-glance view of the analyses I&amp;rsquo;ve run side-by-side. Moving the R script demos/ into markdown knitted files in inst/examples/ and rerunning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday/Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/03/mondaytuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 15:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/03/mondaytuesday/</guid>
      <description>knitr + markdown + pandoc + latex Troubleshooting this workflow still&amp;hellip;
 Fonts xtable for html &amp;amp; latex/pdf xtable comments display tikz device trouble Pandoc table trouble pandoc footnotes Getting a satisfactory LaTeX template.
 Makefile   writing writing writing: Mostly writing this week, so my notebook has been lacking in entries. Trying to move several manuscripts forward: two are papers accompanying software packages for extracting, manipulating and visualizing data from online repositories (TreeBase and FishBase); part of the rOpenSci project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: pandoc citations notes, various</title>
      <link>/2012/03/27/tuesday-pandoc-citations-notes-various/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 22:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/27/tuesday-pandoc-citations-notes-various/</guid>
      <description>Markdown over latex? knitr may have solved the fundamental challenge of all Sweave/latex users with Markdown. Too many of us must be able to work with collaborators who don&amp;rsquo;t know LaTeX and journals that won&amp;rsquo;t accept LaTeX. It&amp;rsquo;s a sad state of the affairs, and has improved slowly for journals (at least many will take pdfs for initial submissions) if not for collaborators. Consequently getting away from LaTeX would be nice, but Word or Google docs just won&amp;rsquo;t cut it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>