<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research Blogging on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/research-blogging/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research Blogging on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 14:10:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/research-blogging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Is your phylogeny informative?</title>
      <link>/2012/01/19/is-your-phylogeny-informative/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 14:10:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/19/is-your-phylogeny-informative/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday my paper (Boettiger et. al. 2012) appeared in early view in Evolution (author&amp;rsquo;s preprint),As the open access copy doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear on pubmed for a while, you can access my author&amp;rsquo;s copy here. so I&amp;rsquo;d like to take this chance to share the back-story and highlight my own view on some of our findings, and the associated package on CRAN.Just submitted, meanwhile, the code is always on github.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t set out to write this paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Showcasing the latest phylogenetic methods: AUTEUR</title>
      <link>/2011/07/20/showcasing-the-latest-phylogenetic-methods-auteur/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2011 15:07:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/20/showcasing-the-latest-phylogenetic-methods-auteur/</guid>
      <description>While high-speed fish feeding videos may be the signature of the lab, dig a bit deeper and you&amp;rsquo;ll find a wealth of comparative phylogenetic methods sneaking in. It&amp;rsquo;s a natural union &amp;ndash; expert functional morphology is the key to good comparative methods, just as phylogenies hold the key to untangling the evolutionary origins of that morphology. The lab&amp;rsquo;s own former graduate, Brian O&amp;rsquo;Meara, made a revolutionary step forward in the land of phylogenetic methods when he unveiled Brownie in 2006, allowing researchers to identify major shifts in trait diversification rates across the tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>141 scientists can&#39;t be wrong?</title>
      <link>/2011/07/08/141-scientists-cant-be-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2011 13:18:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/08/141-scientists-cant-be-wrong/</guid>
      <description>Turning the author-list into a petition is becoming an almost familiar ruse in the table of contents of journals such as Nature (Simberloff, 2011), (Abbot et. al. 2011). This as prompted some rather provocative commentary on whether we have begun conducting scientific debates as popularity contests rather than arguments of evidence and logic (see David Sloan Wilson on inclusive fitness theory 137 scientists can&amp;rsquo;t be wrong, or Chris on invasive species on ecolog.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>