<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pdg Control on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/pdg-control.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pdg Control on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 22:22:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/pdg-control/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: pandoc citations notes, various</title>
      <link>/2012/03/27/tuesday-pandoc-citations-notes-various.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 22:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/27/tuesday-pandoc-citations-notes-various.html</guid>
      <description>Markdown over latex? knitr may have solved the fundamental challenge of all Sweave/latex users with Markdown. Too many of us must be able to work with collaborators who don&amp;rsquo;t know LaTeX and journals that won&amp;rsquo;t accept LaTeX. It&amp;rsquo;s a sad state of the affairs, and has improved slowly for journals (at least many will take pdfs for initial submissions) if not for collaborators. Consequently getting away from LaTeX would be nice, but Word or Google docs just won&amp;rsquo;t cut it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Active adaptive management solutions: Belief SDP</title>
      <link>/2012/03/26/active-adaptive-management-solutions-belief-sdp.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2012 14:46:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/26/active-adaptive-management-solutions-belief-sdp.html</guid>
      <description>Have finally gotten my active adaptive management solutions working.
The active adaptive management solution learns very quickly and rather monotonically which model is correct, even when models differ by small amounts and the initial belief is heavily skewed to the wrong model. I&amp;rsquo;ve implemented examples with Myers model, but in this parameter space the allee effect is well below the Reed escapement level of the alternative Beverton Holt model, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t exert itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policy costs to changing mangement, TP 1b: Apples to Apples</title>
      <link>/2012/03/21/policy-costs-to-changing-mangement-tp-1b-apples-to-apples.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 14:42:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/21/policy-costs-to-changing-mangement-tp-1b-apples-to-apples.html</guid>
      <description>A central question of training problem 1b addressed at the working group was how to compare the different penalties. Following up on those discussions, here are a few notes on how far I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten in the analysis regarding the best way to make these comparisons.
 simulate_npv_curves Nice job of showing the performance of the variance ratio, clear example for L2. Correlation test should probably be applied to differences, pattern is much less clear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: active adaptive management, a first solution</title>
      <link>/2012/03/20/tuesday-active-adaptive-management-a-first-solution.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2012 22:31:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/20/tuesday-active-adaptive-management-a-first-solution.html</guid>
      <description>Spent way more of today than I wanted to hammering out the active adaptive management implementation for a trivial model-choice problem using the discretized belief-SDP approach.
We have alternate models $f_1$ and $f2$ of the state equations (population growth dynamics) $$ x{t+1} = z_t f(x_t) $$ and introduce a continuously valued belief probability $p$ that model 1 is correct. This lends itself to a Bayesian updating rule for our belief based on observing a transition from $x$ to $y$,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control Day 1 goals by training problem</title>
      <link>/2012/03/13/pdg-control-day-1-goals-by-training-problem.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 21:23:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/13/pdg-control-day-1-goals-by-training-problem.html</guid>
      <description>Training Problem I / Theme 1 Policy costs  Functional forms of cost &amp;amp; Structure of the paper Comparability (view over all costs? view expected economic benefit?)
 Visualizations Dan&amp;rsquo;s L1 norm story (vs stochastic, discrete time?)  Transaction Fee details in cts time, deterministic Advanced problem 1 How many spatially differentiated policies are optimal 1. formulate bioeconomic model 2. modularity methods 3. comparison of GBR &amp;amp; Caribbean examples</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control, Training Problem 2 update to group</title>
      <link>/2012/03/13/pdg-control-training-problem-2-update-to-group.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2012 20:17:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/13/pdg-control-training-problem-2-update-to-group.html</guid>
      <description>Intrinsic Stochasticity $$ x_{t+1} = z_t f(x_t, ht) $$ $$ max{h_t} \textrm{E} \left( \sum_t \Pi(h_t, x_t) \delta^t \right) $$ Measurement error $ m_t = z_m x_t $ Implementation error $ i_t = z_i h_t $
Next: Uncertainty = we can learn and hence decrease the uncertainty. But state-space grows exponentially.
Parametric Uncertainty Biological state equation $$ x_{t+1} = z_t f(x_t, h_t, a_t) P(a_t, \hat a_t, \sigmat) $$ Bayesian Learning state equations $$ \hat a{t+1} = \textrm{Posterior}(a | x) = \frac{ L(x|a) \textrm{Prior}(a)}{\int L(x|a) \textrm{Prior}(a) da } $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameter uncertainty in stochastic control problems</title>
      <link>/2012/03/11/parameter-uncertainty-in-stochastic-control-problems-2.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2012 23:52:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/11/parameter-uncertainty-in-stochastic-control-problems-2.html</guid>
      <description>Day 3 of my short-term visitor stay before the working group starts.
 Wednesday: Travel
 Thursday: 8:45 Group Meeting: Paul, Michael, Lance, Dan, Jake, Carl.
  Training problem II discussion &amp;ndash; problem taxonomy: stochastic , model uncertainty, parameter uncertainty, state uncertainty. Learning on uncertainty (passive/adaptive active management) in the uncertainty cases, all of which increase the parameter space. Evening with Paul&amp;rsquo;s students.
 Friday Writing up Training problem II with Jake, Michael.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/03/06/tuesday-14.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2012 19:58:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/06/tuesday-14.html</guid>
      <description>Confirm travel plans for tomorrow  pdg-control  Stability analysis speeding up policycosts (extra loop) will probably require some C coding. Meanwhile could hard-code in the profit function to accelerate things.
 model averaging (mimic the fisheries science work &amp;amp; climate models that present distribution of outcomes over different models as the range of possibilities, lacking probabilities assigned to those models&amp;hellip;). work on model estimation externalization: Note that we can tangle a file to create a .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/03/05/monday-17.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2012 16:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/05/monday-17.html</guid>
      <description>Trivial example of a non-optimal but more robust policy by editing the optimal strategy directly. Note in particular that this outperforms the optimal strategy economically as well as ecologically (fewer crashed populations).
 Running the policy-costs model with Beverton Holt instead of the Myers function seems to give a clearer picture of a system responding to policy costs. The single-replicate picture probably captures this better than the policy/replicate visualizations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday, Friday, Saturday</title>
      <link>/2012/03/03/thursday-friday-saturday.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2012 22:21:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/03/thursday-friday-saturday.html</guid>
      <description>forage fish seminar - Patrick and Jay with interesting stuff. Sounds like compensating benefits due to quality-response (larger fish) and stock effect (easier to find) will be more minor in this fishery, but demand response be compensating.  knit hooks externalization example working (based on Reed.R). Still unsure how I feel about externalization vs fully literate code. Redundant typing is bad but isn&amp;rsquo;t that why common tasks are functionalized?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic optimization </title>
      <link>/2012/02/22/stochastic-optimization.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 21:44:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/22/stochastic-optimization.html</guid>
      <description>Surprising heterogeneity of profit distribution under a simple Beverton-Holt model Usually I expect the alternate stable state dynamics to be the ones producing bimodal distribution of profit:
The pattern is driven by a costs to harvesting making harvest unprofitable most of the time, while chance fluctuations push some populations across this threshold again and again. The ensemble variation in harvest is suggestive of this:
but we really see what is going on when we color-code the population dynamics of the most profitable and least profitable realizations of the stochastic dynamics:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/01/30/monday-15.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2012 19:38:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/30/monday-15.html</guid>
      <description>pdg-control, aside exercise Lab group commented that optimum in Reed model looks unrealistic due to frequency with which it shuts down all fishing. This is an artifact of not having extraction costs increase sufficiently for small catch, and can be easily fixed by increasing that cost (c in the profit eq, profits-costs = p*x-c/x)
view sourcecode, Reed.R
NIMBioS short visitor application Have been thinking that it would be really useful to have some extra time at Nimbios to meet with folks at the time of our next working group meeting (March 12-15).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control Training Problem II update</title>
      <link>/2012/01/24/pdg-control-training-problem-ii-update.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2012 16:55:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/24/pdg-control-training-problem-ii-update.html</guid>
      <description>Basically we&amp;rsquo;ve done some simple stuff and now would be a good time to think about tools for some heavy-lifting computational challenges standing in the way. Michael &amp;amp; Jim have been a great help on this, and Jake has also helped with theoretical underpinnings.
Statement of problem
We consider the impact of uncertainty in the harvesting of fisheries which involve alternative stable state dynamics.
Current Findings
 Adding uncertainty in current state means optimal escapement isn&amp;rsquo;t the optimal solution (contrary to Reed model) (Sethi et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal policy with assymetric costs to changing harvest quotas</title>
      <link>/2012/01/06/optimal-policy-with-assymetric-costs-to-changing-harvest-quotas.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 13:52:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/06/optimal-policy-with-assymetric-costs-to-changing-harvest-quotas.html</guid>
      <description>The optimal policy with symmetric L1 costs to changing the quotas results in the solutions that stop changing, sometimes at no harvest (if there&amp;rsquo;s scrap value), or at some fixed high harvest if no scrap value. (See earlier notes). Asymmetric costs of comparable magnitude result in more crashes.
When we apply an L1 norm cost of the same magnitude as before for decreasing quotas, but allow increasing quotas to be free (no cost to environmental lobby), the solution follows the Reed optimum is in purple (harvest_alt) (cost-free adjustment), while the blue is the harvest level being implemented with a cost:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/12/09/friday-9.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2011 13:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/09/friday-9.html</guid>
      <description>Wrightscape/pmc  Writing up derivation from Thursday properly / for manuscript. Writing up test cases for method2, direct evaluation of covariance matrix for comparisons Minor revisions submitted to Evolution  pdg-control To Do  Implement the NCO. Implement HS SDP Closer read of (Sethi et. al. 2005), (Su &amp;amp; Peterman, 2012) and Woodward &amp;amp; Tomberlin  Warning signals  Allee effects in linear programming with different classes. Timescales of noise using van Kampen expansion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - wrightscape runs and various other things</title>
      <link>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 18:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11.html</guid>
      <description>pdg-control  plots for changing costs Report out to Training Problem II group.  ggplot note defining functions that return a ggplot object can be tricky. If you compute some objects in the plot function (stats etc), those stats are not stored by the object (due to lazy evaluation, usually a very nice time-saving feature), so the plot cannot be produced unless the function returns those things to the global environment (or from wherever the plot will be printed/evaluated).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal control -- costs to policy shifts</title>
      <link>/2011/12/07/optimal-control-costs-to-policy-shifts.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 09:11:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/07/optimal-control-costs-to-policy-shifts.html</guid>
      <description>Considering the case where there is a cost to changing the harvest quota (representing the cost of efforts to change policy). We can imagine several scenarios that could introduce this:
 Fixed cost to change
 Cost proportional to the size of the change (L1 norm)
 Cost proportional to the square of the size (L2 norm, i.e. small changes aren&amp;rsquo;t expensive, large ones are very expensive)
 asymmetric costs &amp;ndash; lowering quotas may be harder than raising them</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday - wrightscape meetings, PDG meeting</title>
      <link>/2011/12/05/monday-wrightscape-meetings-pdg-meeting.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 18:45:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/05/monday-wrightscape-meetings-pdg-meeting.html</guid>
      <description>Wrightscape &amp;ndash; added a user utility to to specify custom model types, such that some subset of the total number of regimes can share certain parameters.
Peter Meeting  Derivation &amp;ndash; provide clear examples of the differences and by how much it matters. Expected result from the biology: the jaw lever traits should show greater changes than the other traits after a release of constraint. Based on previous studies, expect most of the action to be around the intramandibular joint innovation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - various logistics, then checking likelihood calculation</title>
      <link>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2011 20:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation.html</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci  rOpenSci wins runner up prize in PLoS + Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s Binary Battle! Write replies to interview questions with Mendeley. roxygenizing documentation for RMendeley &amp;ndash; about half done  pdg-control  Call with Jake scheduled for tomorrow Emails with Michael. I&amp;rsquo;ll implement delay intervals, he&amp;rsquo;ll add costs to adjustment. Need to fix/finish delay interval optimization calculation (exponent of matrix &amp;amp; beta)  Warning Signals Meeting with Alan
 Regime shifts Emphasize the RO curve in uncertainty analysis See (Dulvy et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handling other sources of noise</title>
      <link>/2011/11/28/handling-other-sources-of-noise.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2011 09:16:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/28/handling-other-sources-of-noise.html</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m now computing the optimal solution under three sources of noise (compare with my earlier examples of calculating the optimal solution assuming only growth noise, but simulating dynamics with other noise sources). See the statement of problem details, essentially:
$$ \max_{ { q_t } \leq 0 } \mathbb{E} \left{ \sum_0^{\infty} \alpha^t h_t \right} $$ s.t. Fish population follows: $ x_t = zt^g f( x{t-1} - h_{t-1} ) $ and measured stock is given by: $ m_t = z_t^m x_t $ while harvest is: $ h_t = \min (x_t, z_t^i q_t) $ Where $ z^g $ denotes uncertainty in population growth, $ z^m $ denotes uncertainty in measurement for the stock assessment, and $ z^i $ denotes uncertainty in harvest implementation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting the right distributions</title>
      <link>/2011/11/23/getting-the-right-distributions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2011 15:43:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/23/getting-the-right-distributions.html</guid>
      <description>Determining the stochastic transition matrix is the essential computational step of SDP solution. If stochasticity enters only in the growth process:
$$x_{t+1} = z_t f(x_t) $$
where $zt$ is a draw from a log-normal density distribution function $ \log \mathcal{N} (x; \mu, \sigma) $, then the probability that $x{t+1}$ falls within a bin $ [x_i-\Delta,x_i+\Delta] $ given that at it is currently at $x_t = y$ is
$$ P([x_i-\Delta,xi+\Delta] |y) = \int{x-\Delta}^{x+\Delta} \log \mathcal{N}(x; \log(f(y)) + \mu, \sigma) dx$$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Sources of stochastic variation in optimal control</title>
      <link>/2011/11/15/tuesday-10.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 23:28:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/15/tuesday-10.html</guid>
      <description>Adding stochasticity seems to have a small history.
Reed 1979 Reed, 1979 Uncertainty in next year&amp;rsquo;s stock, &amp;ldquo;growth uncertainty&amp;rdquo; at the time of determining harvest. Constant escapement policy, no chance of extinction.
Clark &amp;amp; Kirkwood 1986 Clark &amp;amp; Kirkwood, 1986 Uncertainty in this year&amp;rsquo;s stock, &amp;ldquo;measurement uncertainty&amp;rdquo; when determining harvest.
Roughgarden &amp;amp; Smith (1996) consider both, and add uncertainty in harvest. Sethi et al. 2005 (Sethi et. al. 2005) consider the economist&amp;rsquo;s optimization of this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>non-optimal outcomes of optimal solutions</title>
      <link>/2011/11/13/non-optimal-outcomes-of-optimal-solutions.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2011 00:54:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/13/non-optimal-outcomes-of-optimal-solutions.html</guid>
      <description>I consider the optimal stochastic-dynamic programming solution for the model specified with known stochasticity in population dynamics, but now vary the actual simulated dynamics to include further uncertainty or error not included in the optimal solution in different ways. In some way this is an &amp;ldquo;unfair&amp;rdquo; analysis, as I really should be solving for the optimal solution in light of the fully uncertain space, but in practice this at least serves as a sensitivity analysis to the assumptions that certain quantities are perfectly known.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SDP solution for allee model</title>
      <link>/2011/11/08/sdp-solution-for-allee-model.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2011 12:40:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/08/sdp-solution-for-allee-model.html</guid>
      <description>Summarizing efforts from last few days setting up and running some stochastic dynamic programming optimization problems. As we are focusing on discrete time at the moment, these problems are solved by Bellman&amp;rsquo;s equation (don&amp;rsquo;t need Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman formulation).
Problem Statement Choose the harvest level to optimize the profit $$ \maxh \sum{t=0}^T \beta^t \pi(x,h,t) $$
Subject to the boundary conditions $X(0) = X_0, X(T) = X_T$ and the state equation: $$ X(t+1) = Z(t) f(X(t)) $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Optimal Control</title>
      <link>/2011/11/02/stochastic-optimal-control.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 22:57:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/02/stochastic-optimal-control.html</guid>
      <description>Starting with Reed 1979 Reed, 1979. Consider the stochastic population growth model
$$ X_{t+1} = Z_n f(X_n) $$
$ f(x) $ is concave and non-decreasing (compensating, not over-compensating). A natural choice is the Beverton-Holt model,
$$ f(x) = \frac{A x}{1+B x} $$
Cost of harvest is Schaefer production function $ c(x) = k/q x $, (i.e. doubling fish density halves the cost, assume $q $ constant), or Cobbs-Douglas form $ c(x) = k/x^{\theta} $ where $ \theta = 1+\beta \leq 1$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control Conference Call</title>
      <link>/2011/11/01/pdg-control-conference-call.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 16:53:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/01/pdg-control-conference-call.html</guid>
      <description>Call includes everyone except Frank &amp;amp; Claire.
Logistics  Meeting 2: 13-15 March
 Review code/files on wiggio.
 Want a group review of material / webX tutorial? Email Paul after the call.
  Training Problem 1b: penalty to policy-change rate. Group is: Paul, Jake, Dan, Carl T, Jim, Frank, &amp;hellip;
 Dan: L2 done. Code coming (in Python, matlab coming). L1 is hard.
 Control variable becomes $ dh/dt $, and $ h $ becomes a control variable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Training Problem 2 update</title>
      <link>/2011/11/01/training-problem-2-update.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 14:20:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/01/training-problem-2-update.html</guid>
      <description>Problem Statement We consider the stochastic optimal control problem of fisheries harvests under the scenarios involving alternate stable states, with uncertainty about the parameters of harvest. We consider a series of introductory problems to prepare us for the full problem. We begin with classical optimal control approaches (Pontraygin&amp;rsquo;s principle to transform into an ordinary differential equation boundary-value problem) for continuous time state equations (fish population dynamics) as a reference point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control examples continued: Bellman,  Dynamic Programming</title>
      <link>/2011/10/28/optimal-control-examples-continued-bellman-dynamic-programming.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2011 23:23:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/28/optimal-control-examples-continued-bellman-dynamic-programming.html</guid>
      <description>Discrete-time state equation Discrete-time solution appears to be all about dynamic programming
and a chance for me to remember that I&amp;rsquo;m out of practice writing recursive functions. It&amp;rsquo;s just that in thinking about the problem, you start from the end, with the trivial subcase, and keep adding the layers. But the recursive function kinda starts at the beginning, and that trivial case is the exit condition. R doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem very efficient with these recursive functions, so this might become a C sub-routine eventually.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal control sample problems (Mostly continuous time by Pontryagin principle)</title>
      <link>/2011/10/27/optimal-control-next-steps.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2011 13:53:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/27/optimal-control-next-steps.html</guid>
      <description>Optimal Control by Pontryagin principle Problem statement  State equation: $\dot x = x \exp \left( \alpha \left(1-\frac{x}{K}\right) \left( \frac{x-C}{K} \right) \right) - x h$
 Utility function $\pi(h, x, t) = \frac{h^{1+\gamma}}{1+\gamma}$
 Boundary constraints: $x(0) = X_0 \qquad x(T) = X_T$
  See problem statement and analytic BVP formulation details in this post. Additionally we scale the variables appropriately. Then we can begin with some basic parameter exploration in the original model formulation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday, misc notes</title>
      <link>/2011/10/26/monday-misc-notes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2011 09:47:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/26/monday-misc-notes.html</guid>
      <description>R packages relevant to the optimal control problems
 BB: solving system of nonlinear equations bvpSolve: boundary value problems  lunch with Alan &amp;amp; visiting professor from Ottowa, Frithjof Lutscher.
ADG (algorithm discussion group)  Reviewed github, basic git commands. Added roxygen function documentation Created basic package, toyHMM Some git notes: The quick git-undo for a destroyed file:  git checkout filename  This will checkout the file from HEAD, overwriting your change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Training problem 2: the economist&#39;s problem statement</title>
      <link>/2011/10/24/optimal-control-training-problem-2-problem-statement.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 17:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/24/optimal-control-training-problem-2-problem-statement.html</guid>
      <description>pdg-control Problem statement: Maximize profits subject to $$\max_{h(t)} \int_0^T e^{-\rho t} \pi(x, h, t) dt $$ Subject to the state equations (biology):
$$ \dot x = x \exp \left( \alpha \left(1-\frac{x}{K}\right) \left( \frac{x-C}{K} \right) \right) - x h $$
Note that we consider the control variable to be effort, $h$ instead of harvest, $\mathcal{H}$, where $\mathcal{H} = h x$.
and the constraints: $$ x(0) = X_0 \qquad x(T) = X_T $$ We have fixed boundary conditions (equalities) and equalities in the state equations, so we have a nice straight-forward problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control Exploration</title>
      <link>/2011/10/19/optimal-control-exploration.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 23:01:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/19/optimal-control-exploration.html</guid>
      <description>Translating Jim&amp;rsquo;s Matlab code.
Adapted for Octave.
R version.
Document review:
 Chapter 04_Sanchirico_Final.pdf
 SanchiricoOptimalSpace_JEEM.pdf (Sanchirico &amp;amp; Wilen, 2005)
 Optimal_Rebuilding_AJAE2010.pdf, Optimal_Rebuilding_Supp_Material.pdf (Sanchirico et. al. 2010)
 Sanchirico_editsembedded.pdf: Book Chapter 1: Economically Optimal Management of a Metapopulation
  Reviewing Bett&amp;rsquo;s Practical Methods for Optimal Control using Nonlinear Programming. (( Practical Methods for Optimal Control and Estimation Using Nonlinear Programming, Second Edition (Advances in Design and Control) John T.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/24/saturday-2.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2011 18:03:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/24/saturday-2.html</guid>
      <description>NIMBioS Working group follow-up:  Install pdf plugin (pdf24, Kalin&amp;rsquo;s pdf, epub all don&amp;rsquo;t display equations) &amp;hellip; Posted issue to wordpress-for-scientists list. Solution: simply print to file (pdf) from google-chrome. (Doesn&amp;rsquo;t work when printing from firefox 6.0) Reply to Paul, add pdf of notes on wiggio.  Fellowship stuff  Email Alan, David, George, John, Perry  Reviews  Answer request to review for Ecology Answer request to review for Evolution _**Working on reviews (see private notes) **_3-6pm  Misc  Testing Droideley.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control pdg-control: Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-control-thursday.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 14:54:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-control-thursday.html</guid>
      <description>Thursday, August 15 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Training Problem Groups TASK: Prepare progress report/action strategy for full group 9:30 Regroup: Reports from each Training Problem Group 10:30 Planning for Meeting 2 12:00 Lunch at NIMBioS &amp;amp; Departure</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control pdg-control: Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-control-thursday.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 14:54:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-control-thursday.html</guid>
      <description>Thursday, August 15 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Training Problem Groups TASK: Prepare progress report/action strategy for full group 9:30 Regroup: Reports from each Training Problem Group 10:30 Planning for Meeting 2 12:00 Lunch at NIMBioS &amp;amp; Departure</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control PDG group, Tasks</title>
      <link>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-group-tasks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 08:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-group-tasks.html</guid>
      <description>Tools  Sharing: Dropbox (Team account? 350 gigs/12 users $1670/yr)
 Common language for training development: Matlab
 Remote collaboration: GoToMeeting? Evo?
 Code collaboration GitHub?
  Training problem I 1a) State vars &amp;gt; Control vars: Can give solutions with chattering (periodic, possibly jumping between boundaries.)
Short-term priorities:
1) shared numerics. Jim looks at collocation problem: how do they perform on periodic controls on the infinite time? (If they can&amp;rsquo;t work, we go to finite time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control PDG group, Tasks</title>
      <link>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-group-tasks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 08:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/15/nimbios-pdg-group-tasks.html</guid>
      <description>Tools  Sharing: Dropbox (Team account? 350 gigs/12 users $1670/yr)
 Common language for training development: Matlab
 Remote collaboration: GoToMeeting? Evo?
 Code collaboration GitHub?
  Training problem I 1a) State vars &amp;gt; Control vars: Can give solutions with chattering (periodic, possibly jumping between boundaries.)
Short-term priorities:
1) shared numerics. Jim looks at collocation problem: how do they perform on periodic controls on the infinite time? (If they can&amp;rsquo;t work, we go to finite time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Training Problem II</title>
      <link>/2011/09/14/training-problem-ii.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2011 22:47:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/14/training-problem-ii.html</guid>
      <description>Consider a harvested fish population with discrete-time population dynamics under an allee effect:
$$ N_{t+1} = N_t \exp \left( \gamma \left[ 1-\frac{N_t}{K} \right] \left[ \frac{N_t - C}{K} \right] \right) - \beta E_h N_t$$
Note that C is the unfished allee threshold, K the carrying capacity, $E_h$ the fish harvesting effort.
Consider that the initial population is unknown, but described by a density function whose variance can be decreased by sampling. Just to get started, let&amp;rsquo;s assume log-normal (avoiding the chance of negative population sizes), with log-standard deviation inversely proportional to the sampling effort $E_s $.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control pdg-control: Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/14/nimbios-pdg-control-wednesday.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2011 14:54:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/14/nimbios-pdg-control-wednesday.html</guid>
      <description>Wednesday, August 14 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Introduction to Day 3 (Donahue/Armsworth) 9:00 Training Problem Groups
Marie-Jose reflects on the sampling problem:  Optimization between effort and data.
 Spatial autocorrelation challenges
 periodic sampling challenges.
 Fortin et al 1989
 Carl asked: Nyquist frequency?
 Spatial sampling the correct scale by maximum variance in wavelet scaling.
  Frank reflects on our activities from a control engineer&amp;rsquo;s perspective  MPC for fishery management - few long-sampling engineering examples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control pdg-control: Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/14/nimbios-pdg-control-wednesday.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2011 14:54:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/14/nimbios-pdg-control-wednesday.html</guid>
      <description>Wednesday, August 14 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Introduction to Day 3 (Donahue/Armsworth) 9:00 Training Problem Groups
Marie-Jose reflects on the sampling problem:  Optimization between effort and data.
 Spatial autocorrelation challenges
 periodic sampling challenges.
 Fortin et al 1989
 Carl asked: Nyquist frequency?
 Spatial sampling the correct scale by maximum variance in wavelet scaling.
  Frank reflects on our activities from a control engineer&amp;rsquo;s perspective  MPC for fishery management - few long-sampling engineering examples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control pdg-control, Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/13/2588.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 09:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/13/2588.html</guid>
      <description>Tuesday, August 13 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Outline for Day 2 (Donahue/Armsworth)
Adaptive Control, Jake Introduced by he two-armed bandit problem, Rothchild i = 1,2. $ T_i $ is the number of trials, $ N_i $ are numbers of successes.
Define $$ \rho_i = \frac{1}{1+T_i}, \mu_i = \frac{N_i}{1+T_i} $$
If i is played $ p_i $ becomes
$$ \frac{p_i}{1+p_i} = \frac{1}{T+2} $$
If i is played and successful $ \mu_i $ becomes</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control pdg-control, Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/13/2588.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 09:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/13/2588.html</guid>
      <description>Tuesday, August 13 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Outline for Day 2 (Donahue/Armsworth)
Adaptive Control, Jake Introduced by he two-armed bandit problem, Rothchild i = 1,2. $ T_i $ is the number of trials, $ N_i $ are numbers of successes.
Define $$ \rho_i = \frac{1}{1+T_i}, \mu_i = \frac{N_i}{1+T_i} $$
If i is played $ p_i $ becomes
$$ \frac{p_i}{1+p_i} = \frac{1}{T+2} $$
If i is played and successful $ \mu_i $ becomes</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pretty Darn Good Control Working Group</title>
      <link>/2011/09/12/pretty-darn-good-control-working-group.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 12:49:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/12/pretty-darn-good-control-working-group.html</guid>
      <description>Monday, August 12 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Welcome to NIMBioS (Lou Gross, Director of NIMBioS) 9:00 Intro to the pdg-control Working Group (Paul Armsworth) 9:30 Introductions by each Working Group Participant 5-minute self-introduction to the group, including your background, expertise, and current work 10:30 Break 11:00 Introduction to Training Problem 1 &amp;amp; Discussion (Jim Sanchirico)
Training problem 0: Optimal Control Jim
maximize present discounted value:
$$\max_{h_t} \int_0^T e^{-rt} \Pi(h_t) dt $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pretty Darn Good Control Working Group</title>
      <link>/2011/09/12/pretty-darn-good-control-working-group.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 12:49:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/12/pretty-darn-good-control-working-group.html</guid>
      <description>Monday, August 12 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Welcome to NIMBioS (Lou Gross, Director of NIMBioS) 9:00 Intro to the pdg-control Working Group (Paul Armsworth) 9:30 Introductions by each Working Group Participant 5-minute self-introduction to the group, including your background, expertise, and current work 10:30 Break 11:00 Introduction to Training Problem 1 &amp;amp; Discussion (Jim Sanchirico)
Training problem 0: Optimal Control Jim
maximize present discounted value:
$$\max_{h_t} \int_0^T e^{-rt} \Pi(h_t) dt $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Let
 y be measured stock size, subject to measurement error from true stock x q be harvest quota, subject to implementation error from actual harvest, h  Stock next year is also subject to stochastic growth shock $z_g$, (note that $f$ will also depend on the harvest, h, unless $x_t$ is taken as the escapement population, $x-h$).
$$ x_{t+1} = z_g f(x_t) $$
In discrete space, let X be a vector representing the probability distribution of having stock $x$ at time $t$, restricted to some finite grid of dimension $n$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>EWS review Composing a simple EWS review highlighting where signals are and are not expected and what this means for the system dynamics. With Alan and Noam. See manuscript repository, cboettig/ews-review.
pdg control  Does the matrix formulation fail to account for the treating profits as a function of realized harvest and true stock size rather than quota and measured size?  notebook  fixing some inline equations 04:34 pm 2012/10/09 Updated Readme 02:57 pm 2012/10/09  scicomp discussions on reproducibility  Asked about longevity of code (re: data managment plan) Replied to best practices for linking code to publications  discussions/tweets  @hylopsar @mwpennell thanks - I always find it tricky to explain conditional probabilities clearly, so that&amp;rsquo;s nice to hear Nice paper by +Matt Pennell, Saver &amp;amp;@lukejharmon on biases in inferring early bursts of evolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Multiple Uncertainty algorithm Define each of the transition matrices:
D &amp;lt;- matrix(NA, nrow=length(x_grid), ncol=Tmax) P &amp;lt;- outer(x_grid, h_grid, profit) F &amp;lt;- outer(x_grid, f(x_grid, 0, p), pdfn, sigma_g) M &amp;lt;- outer(x_grid, x_grid, pdfn, sigma_m) I &amp;lt;- outer(h_grid, h_grid, pdfn, sigma_i)  Probably row-normalize each:
rownorm &amp;lt;- function(M) t(apply(M, 1, function(x) x/sum(x))  (Note the transpose is needed since the silly function of a vector turns the column into a row. Not an issue of margin 2)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>multiple-uncertainty Working out the multiple uncertainty computational performance and noise forms. Fixing a few things in the way log-normal noise was calculated. Uniform noise in particular can still give rather non-smooth policy, needs a bit of digging. Uniform noise doesn&amp;rsquo;t show the non-monotonicity of the log-normal noise in measurement uncertainty though.
Uniform lognormal log  A few small tweaks to probability calculations
 Handle the case of mu = grid zero, not just exactly zero, to avoid introducing NAs Calculate dlnorm as (x_grid/mu, 0, sigma), rather than as (x_grid, mu, sigma).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Scripts to estimate apples to apples comparisons for different penalty functions and plot instances of the resulting policy. Example run with fixed linear costs on effort.
 Double the actual variance leads to terminal overfishing 11:16 am 2012/11/28 use fixed seed. 09:45 am 2012/11/28 Compare GP to Reed optimum for BH (successful run this time) 09:37 am 2012/11/28 basic GP example in BH system, compared to Reed Optimum 09:17 am 2012/11/28  Content of current working example, run on server zero.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Straight-forward tasks can sometimes take forever. In advance of our upcoming conference call for the Pretty Darn Good Control (pdg-control) NIMBioS working group, I had a few remaining issues to touch up in Figures 3 and 4.
Figure 3 shows harvest and stock dynamics under the different functional forms fo the cost. The goal is to provide a very intuitive, visual sense of how the policies differ under these different functional forms, such as a fixed &amp;ldquo;transaction fee&amp;rdquo; (fixed) or a cost that is proportional to the size of the change in policy (L1), or the square of that change (L2), etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>pdg-control Call  Send Figure 3 and 4 with stock dynamics to Paul.  Detailed to do items coming out of talk filed as Github Issues for pdg-control (policycosts)
 Comparisons between assumed and true policy costs (Figure 5 style but as a Table) Snappier, more meaningful names for &amp;ldquo;L1&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;L2&amp;rdquo; etc Write real-world context/significance of L1, L2, fixed, etc. Add graph &amp;amp; discussion of stock dynamics for Fig 3 &amp;amp; 4 Figure 5 interpretation Fix boundary issues in Figure 4 Resolve confusion about apples-to-apples / definition of NPV0 Resolve cost structure question On functional forms, drop ALL asymmetric cases for now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Progress mid-October through mid-December 80% Time: nonparametric-bayes The bulk of my time has been spent becoming familiar with the literature on Gaussian Processes and their numerical implementation. I have written my own Gaussian process code from scratch to convince myself of my understanding of the methodology, and explored some of the related numerical issues addressing computational speed and stability.
I then developed an algorithm for applying the Gaussian process inference of the state dynamics to stochastic dynamic programming methods for determining an optimal harvesting policy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>At home after birth of Edward since Jan 19th, leaving little time for research. Assembled notes from a few side projects I&amp;rsquo;ve moved forward in the wee hours. Covers the past several days.
XML and RDFa parsing I have been using the lab notebook to explore technology for scientific communication, including making use of semantic and linked data concepts. To illustrate some of the potential these tools can offer I&amp;rsquo;ve started working on a short post with examples parsing and exploring the XML and RDFa data in the notebook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy comment  Fallacy comment revisions Comment reply letter (draft) ROC curves instead? (examples) Add example of system with an alternative stable state?  Policy costs (pdg-control)  touched up tex document following Paul&amp;rsquo;s edits (mostly reflects comments and decisions from Meeting 3). Reminder of why collaborating on TeX documents can be annoying even when co-authors are tex-literate. Attempted quick conversion to markdown but mapping is troublesome.
  Misc  Some software providing rather impressive/high fidelity pdf to html conversion&amp;hellip; Not just rendering as images &amp;ndash; the text is searchable, though in the html source it just looks like a bunch of binary data URIs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>EWS TE revisions  Finalized manuscript(?) Checking references, reply letter, closing remaining issues.
 Very annoying to submit to a journal system that takes LaTeX but not any external style or class file dependencies. For instance, how does one add two footnotes to the same author without adding any such dependencies (oh, and writing macros that do not involve pairs of $ which pandoc mistakes for its own macros&amp;hellip;) Reasonable author affiliations done otherwise using \and, \thanks, and \footnotemark; see [simple.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>NSF goals:  combine control methods and warning signals do non-parametric or machine learning increase or decrease chance of transition learning  Further areas (from comment piece) baselines (statistical; emperical) context-specific (additional data sources, reflecting context in model)  Warning signals in managed systems Management decreases the signal: compare likelihood statistic in unmanaged_warning managed_warning:
Estimating Stability in managed systems Recovery rate in optimally fished vs unfished system (based on the OU model): stability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>SUSTAINABLE MANAGEMENT OF LIVING NATURAL RESOURCES  Description Full Schedule Participants  Introductions Hastings Lou Gross  Big picture: big data, computational challenges.
 NEON, DataONE, ADW, iDigBio &amp;ldquo;Convergence&amp;rdquo; as the new interdisciplinary (National Academies) Rise of synthesis centers &amp;ldquo;Enabling architecture for next gen life science research&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; National Academies report Lou Gross (2013) Comp Science for Natural Resource Management &amp;ndash; Fuller, Wang, Gross (2007)
 language barriers: What&amp;rsquo;s a model?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>MBI Workshop Paul Armsworth Very nice example of control in creating a market for ecosystem services for landowners. Key feature is that multiple land-owners respond by adjusting their prices, and so payments can be divided into fraction going into subsidy and fraction going into conservation. When one land-owner controls land that is particularly good cost per conservation accomplished, they also stand to gain largest value.
Also looked at auction mechanism and impact of cooperation among landowners to create hold outs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>MBI Workshop Becky Epanchin-Niell  Motivating example of Rabies spatial control in Switzerland
 2012 Eco Let: should New Zealand survey for bark beetle? Cost of survellience, control, and damage. Epanchin-Niell et al. (2012)
 2012 JEEM spatial spread of star thistle: control spread and eradication as an integer programming problem in deterministic context. (with Wilen) Epanchin-Niell &amp;amp; Wilen (2012)
 Breaking landscape into individual landowners makes it less valuable to control early.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>ropensci  Ensuring interoperability in R / ropensci projects. See pre-hackathon discussion: ropensci/hackathon/issues/#20 rfigshare to use new oauth interface of httr, see rfigshare/#72 Ugh. More fun with travis integration on RNeXML RNeXML/#61  pdg-control / policycosts  Started tidying up this repo&amp;rsquo;s manuscript folder a bit.
 Merge Paul&amp;rsquo;s various changes on tex and Word documents into Rmd  Misc  Whoops. Couldn&amp;rsquo;r resist a wee rant on G+, 2014-03-02 on this #PLOSfail discussion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>ropensci Working on proposal. Discussion of section 2: other players in the domain (or rather, the many community interfaces with rOpenSci).
other  Discussion with Hadley re: API testing and test_if functionality, see testthat/141.
 Related with Hadley discussion on handling tests and keys for API packages, httr/93
 Software Carpentry developing R lessons
  rfishbase Add FAO areas (from 04/05), see rfishbase/20
EML  Discussion of unit handling, feedback from Karen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01.html</guid>
      <description>Just wanted to give a quick update on stuff relevant to our adjustment costs paper in events of this week.
I think the talk on Tuesday went all right, (though thanks to a technology snafu going from reveal.js to pdf my most useful figure actually showing the bluefin tuna didn&amp;rsquo;t display &amp;ndash; I tried not to let on). I tried to keep the focus pretty big-picture throughout (we ignore these costs when we model, they matter) and avoid being too bold / prescriptive (e.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>