<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Derivation on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/derivation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Derivation on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2010 22:56:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/derivation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Fitting the limiting OU models to each bifurcation</title>
      <link>/2010/11/30/tues-fitting-the-limiting-ou-models-to-each-bifurcation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2010 22:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/30/tues-fitting-the-limiting-ou-models-to-each-bifurcation/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I derived the linearized SDEs for the saddle node bifurcation :
$$ dX = 2\sqrt{r(t)} (\sqrt{r(t)} + \theta -X) dt + \sigma \sqrt{\sqrt{r(t)}+\theta} dB_t $$
and the transcritical bifurcation
$$ dX = r(t) (K - X) dt + \sqrt{K} dB_t $$
Now to implement them for fitting by likelihood using generic $ r(t) $. I go back to the warning() model implemented in sde_likelihood.R code. We can just solve the odes directly:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further treatment of the limiting models</title>
      <link>/2010/11/29/further-treatment-of-the-limiting-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 19:01:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/29/further-treatment-of-the-limiting-models/</guid>
      <description>Have spent the last three days building and testing the infrastructure to fit the canonical form of a saddle-node (fold) bifurcation by likelihood. Actually I don&amp;rsquo;t use the canonical form straight up: $ dx/dt = x^2 +r$ cannot be fit directly in this manner, since it needs a couple scale transformations on the variables to get the units right (a multiple for the unit scale and an additive factor for the zero point), and more importantly, isn&amp;rsquo;t a stochastic model so cannot assign probabilities to the outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihoods for quadratic models cont</title>
      <link>/2010/11/28/likelihoods-for-quadratic-models-cont/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2010 21:14:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/28/likelihoods-for-quadratic-models-cont/</guid>
      <description>Considering the fits of the quadratic models from yesterday.
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;tag&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;quadraticfitslides&amp;rdquo; tag_mode=&amp;ldquo;all&amp;rdquo;]
Analysis of fits Of course these fits rely entirely on mapping the location of the stable point and the slope through that point, something they still cannot do all that well. In this parameterization the the stable intercept is $$ \hat x = \sqrt{r}+\theta $$ and slope at intercept is $$ \frac{\partial f(\hat x)}{\partial x} = -2\sqrt{r} $$ This creates a numerical optimization problem, since there is high importance on getting the mean right, and less on the variance, the routine tends to fix the combination of r and theta to get the mean right, and then cannot change r to get the slope correct without getting penalized for the loss of likelihood in changing the mean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals: Likelihoods Straight-up</title>
      <link>/2010/11/24/warning-signals-likelihoods-straight-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 21:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/24/warning-signals-likelihoods-straight-up/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with Alan this morning. I haven&amp;rsquo;t solved likelihood of power spectra (previous couple entries in Stoch. Pop / warning signals), though after meeting with Sebastian (11&amp;frasl;9) probably the best method works from the correlation function. Define a new stochastic process Y $$ Y_1 = X_1 X_2 + X_2 X_3 + X_3 X_4 + \ldots $$ $$ Y_2 = X_1 X_3 + X_2 X_4 + \ldots $$ $$ Y_3 = \ldots $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>editorial note: These notes pre-date the formal start of my online laboratory notebook, Feb 2 2010: The Lab Notebook Goes Open and were adapted from a LaTeX document in which I kept notes on this topic during my summer at IIASA. Lacking a proper notebook then, documents like this one were updated periodically and occassionally branched into new ones. The post date represents the last time the LaTeX document was edited in the course of that research.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>