<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Warning Signals on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/warning-signals/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Warning Signals on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/warning-signals/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <link>/2012/10/17/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/17/notes/</guid>
      <description>Talking points for phone interview with Lucy
Finding warning signals in the wild
 Gold standard &amp;ndash; experimental group, control group Real world: We have no control group.
  Would we know a warning signal when we saw it?
From statistics to models: We fit a generalized models of the processes that are and aren&amp;rsquo;t approaching a tipping point, and compare the models. The modeling approach is also more sensitive than the simple statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2012-04-20</title>
      <link>/2012/04/26/2012-04-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2012 13:32:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/26/2012-04-20/</guid>
      <description>Warning Signals Warning signals paper accepted. Making minor edits before submitting final copy.
Added Alan&amp;rsquo;s edits.
 Review model section again Letter: Response to reviewers Create Diff Media Summary Submit  Done!
Database papers  rfishbase edits made, reformatting in word, sent to Peter Ethics form, recommended reviewers, cover letter. Submit  Done!
Misc NERSC web directory: create www in /project/projectdirs/m1366 NSF Arctic SEES grants
 These larger, integrated efforts would promote understanding of Arctic systems and would develop optimized models, multiple stable state scenarios, sustainable pathways, decision matrices, visualization techniques and data infrastructure to aid decision making and communication, and structural, energy and communications technology solutions which would inform community practices, management, and policy for a more sustainable Arctic environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Catching up</title>
      <link>/2012/04/19/catching-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Apr 2012 10:39:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/19/catching-up/</guid>
      <description>Catching up on notebook entries for last week and the beginning of this week in one go here. In the process of wrapping up a variety of older projects, so this is kinda all over the place.
rfishbase  Create function table, finalize functions Add support for references. Done, see getRefs. (And isn&amp;rsquo;t it awesome that you can link to a specific linenumber (i.e. line 280) in github by adding #L280 to the end of the url?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday / Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 23:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/10/monday-tuesday/</guid>
      <description>rfishbase updated to Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback writing intro section on Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy. wrightscape update project repository. Scripts mostly in demos, results in notebook. Notebook makes is easy to get the most recent writeup on the topic, from where I can start to track back the history, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide a good at-a-glance view of the analyses I&amp;rsquo;ve run side-by-side. Moving the R script demos/ into markdown knitted files in inst/examples/ and rerunning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals in Fish Collapse</title>
      <link>/2012/02/28/warning-signals-in-fish-collapse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2012 15:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/28/warning-signals-in-fish-collapse/</guid>
      <description>Description: an example trying to detect early warning signals in data from fisheries collapses
Set up markdown format and image uploads.
render_wordpress() opts_knit$set(upload = TRUE) opts_knit$set(imgur.key = getOption(&amp;amp;amp;quot;imgur&amp;amp;amp;quot;))  Load required libraries
require(warningsignals) require(ggplot2) require(reshape2)  Load the data scotia &amp;amp;amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;amp;amp;quot;../../data/rawdata/sau_scotia.csv&amp;amp;amp;quot;)  Visualize data dat_scotia &amp;amp;amp;lt;- melt(scotia, id = &amp;amp;amp;quot;Year&amp;amp;amp;quot;) p_scotia &amp;amp;amp;lt;- ggplot(dat_scotia, aes(Year, value, fill = variable)) + geom_area() print(p_scotia)  Compute some indicators Define some indicators</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/02/27/monday-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 15:20:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/27/monday-14/</guid>
      <description>Warning Signals  Added resulting indicator distributions on finer sampling results.
 Re-running now excluding the final dive (population below 300).
  Treebase working on manuscript. A few examples using the improved meta-data queries:
Computing configuration vim and R  install vim-r-plugin. Download, then run vim-addons install r-plugin install screen plugin add to .vimrc:   set nocompatible syntax enable filetype plugin on filetype indent on let vimrplugin_underscore = 0   learn some key bindings Really \rf to launch, and \d Also see this post for configuration with vim-latex-suite.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA 2012 Abstract</title>
      <link>/2012/02/23/esa-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 21:44:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/23/esa-2012/</guid>
      <description>Submitted my abstract for ESA 2012, in Portland. Getting a title and abstract pinned down about seven months in advance is itself an exercise in decision making under uncertainty. I&amp;rsquo;ve added some further background below.
Unknown unknowns: management strategies under uncertainty &amp;amp; alternate stable states Background/Question/Methods The effective management of natural resource populations such as fisheries or forests and the ecosystems in which they are embedded is a central goal of much work in both theoretical and applied ecological research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Research, seminar (managing for resilience), talk (future of libraries), etc...</title>
      <link>/2012/02/21/tues-research--managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 19:20:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/21/tues-research--managing-for-resilience-talk-future-of-libraries-etc/</guid>
      <description>research Stuff warningsignals  Exceeded wall time on NERSC, readjusting and running this again.  treebase  Working on treebase manuscript. Treebase Rewrote handling of server errors, added pauses to reduce load, etc.  PMC  A user pointed out my support for &amp;ldquo;white&amp;rdquo; model was incomplete. Fix is now on github (install instructions for development version are also now on github), will push to CRAN soon.
 Another user points out that pmc support for additional functions would be nice, such as rbrownie, fit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>finer sampling in prosecutor&#39;s fallacy</title>
      <link>/2012/02/20/finer-sampling-in-prosecutors-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 19:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/20/finer-sampling-in-prosecutors-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>Create the data. We&amp;rsquo;ll save files as some of these code chunks need to be run on the cluster for large memory use.
require(populationdynamics) pars = c(Xo = 500, e = 0.5, a = 180, K = 1000, h = 200, i = 0, Da = 0, Dt = 0, p = 2) sn &amp;lt;- saddle_node_ibm(pars, times=seq(0,5000, length=50000), reps=1) save(&amp;quot;sn&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;file=prosecutor.rda&amp;quot;)  Subset the chance transitions
d &amp;lt;- dim(sn$x1) crashed &amp;lt;- which(sn$x1[d[1],]==0) dat &amp;lt;- melt( sn$x1[,crashed] ) names(dat) = c(&amp;quot;time&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;reps&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;) save(&amp;quot;dat&amp;quot;, file=&amp;quot;crashed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>prosecutor&#39;s fallacy initial look</title>
      <link>/2012/02/16/prosecutors-fallacy-initial-look/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 20:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/16/prosecutors-fallacy-initial-look/</guid>
      <description>So I&amp;rsquo;ve simulated 1000 replicates of a system that has alternative stable states, but is not approaching the bifurcation. I&amp;rsquo;ve added enough noise (demographic stochasticity in this case, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter what) that 129&amp;frasl;1000 transition stochastically to the bad state, so I have decent sample sizes in each. Here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;m finding: If I condition on having crashed (i.e. take the 129 that transition) and apply our model-based early warning signal, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t detect any early warning sign.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Squiggles</title>
      <link>/2012/02/16/squiggles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 19:34:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/16/squiggles/</guid>
      <description>Variability in the appearance of a trend
nreps &amp;lt;- 64  require(populationdynamics) pars = c(Xo = 730, e = 0.5, a = 100, K = 1000, h = 200, i = 0, Da = 0.09, Dt = 0, p = 2) time = seq(0, 990, length = 100) sn &amp;lt;- saddle_node_ibm(pars, time, reps = nreps)  We reformat the replicates into long form,
X &amp;lt;- data.frame(time = time, value = sn$x1) require(reshape) dat &amp;lt;- melt(X, id = &amp;quot;time&amp;quot;) names(dat)[2] &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;reps&amp;quot;  require(plyr) window &amp;lt;- length(X[[&amp;quot;time&amp;quot;]])/2 tmp &amp;lt;- ddply(dat, &amp;quot;reps&amp;quot;, function(X) window_autocorr(X$value, windowsize = window))  Tidy up the warning signal data</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>getting signal from autocorrelation</title>
      <link>/2012/02/15/getting-signal-from-autocorrelation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 19:40:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/15/getting-signal-from-autocorrelation/</guid>
      <description>This example goes through the steps to demonstrate that in a sufficiently-frequently sampled timeseries, autocorrelation does contain some signal of early warning. ((Post markdown generated automatically from knitr.))
Run the individual based simulation
require(populationdynamics)  [code] Loading required package: populationdynamics
 ```R pars = c(Xo = 730, e = 0.5, a = 100, K = 1000, h = 200, i = 0, Da = 0.09, Dt = 0, p = 2) time = seq(0, 500, length = 500) sn &amp;lt;- saddle_node_ibm(pars, time) X &amp;lt;- data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further examples for appendices</title>
      <link>/2012/02/14/further-examples-for-appendices/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 16:35:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/14/further-examples-for-appendices/</guid>
      <description>Going through additional examples of things I&amp;rsquo;d like to see / demonstrate but do not fit into the narrative of the manuscript. Writing these in knitr/dynamic documentation to confirm code produces the examples listed, and give a bit tighter integration between text and code examples.
Show the parameter distributions: We can also look at the bootstraps of the parameters. Another helper function will reformat this data from reps list. The fit column uses a two-letter code to indicate first what model was used to simulate the data, and then what model was fit to the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2012/02/13/monday-16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2012 23:29:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/13/monday-16/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve created the more extend-able earlywarning package out of my warningsignals package. The individual-based simulations are carried out separately via my new populationdynamics package.
Fallacy plots Appendices Trying a knitr-based platform for tighter integration of code, figures, and text. See today&amp;rsquo;s analysis in markdown generated by knitr, posted as a github wiki page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday </title>
      <link>/2012/02/12/sunday-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 22:14:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/12/sunday-6/</guid>
      <description>phylogenetics  Exploring display of phylogeny. Unlabled, painted fan?   tweaking release-of-constraint plot - vary alpha, less strong? release at T/2? Animated version?  Creating paintings of phylogenies Creating from a specified set of taxa is a somewhat common task for me. Wrightscape supports doing this for both ouch and ape trees.
 ape-based phylogenies ouch-based phylogenies use some legacy maticce functions  intra_ancestor &amp;lt;- mrcaOUCH(c(&amp;quot;Chlorurus_sordidus&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Hipposcarus_longiceps&amp;quot;), labrid$tree) intramandibular &amp;lt;- paintBranches(intra_ancestor, labrid$tree, c(&amp;quot;other&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;intramandibular&amp;quot;)) pharyngeal_ancestor&amp;lt;-mrcaOUCH(c(&amp;quot;Bolbometopon_muricatum&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Sparisoma_radians&amp;quot;), labrid$tree) pharyngeal &amp;lt;- paintBranches(pharyngeal_ancestor, labrid$tree, c(&amp;quot;other&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;pharyngeal&amp;quot;)) two_shifts &amp;lt;- paintBranches(c(pharyngeal_ancestor, intra_ancestor), labrid$tree, c(&amp;quot;wrasses&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;pharyngeal&amp;quot;, intramandibular&amp;quot;) )  The ouch-trees can be converted back to ape trees in a way that can plot them, but for some reason break the fan-plot mode but not the standard phylogram plot mode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday: projects, reading, markdown notebook-technology</title>
      <link>/2012/02/12/saturday-projects-reading-markdown-notebook-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 13:40:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/12/saturday-projects-reading-markdown-notebook-technology/</guid>
      <description>Greatly enjoyed seeing this perspective on power laws (Stumpf &amp;amp; Porter, 2012) Or as Richard McElreath put even more concisely,
 People get amazed by power laws but never by normal distributions. Seems like some max ent outcomes astonish while others don&amp;rsquo;t. When so many mechanisms aggregate to common densities, I&amp;rsquo;d hope we&amp;rsquo;d stop trying to argue that we can go backwards from pattern to process so easily.
 Projects  fishbase example query for Peter Commit edits to warningsignals paper, send to Alan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UC Davis graduate student symposium proposal</title>
      <link>/2012/02/08/uc-davis-graduate-student-symposium-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2012 12:35:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/08/uc-davis-graduate-student-symposium-proposal/</guid>
      <description>Abstract The recog­ni­tion that ecosys­tems can undergo sud­den shifts to alter­nate, less desir­able sta­ble states has led to the desire to iden­tify early warn­ing signs of these impend­ing col­lapses. Motivated by the math­e­mat­ics of bifur­ca­tions, the search for early warn­ing signs seeks to detect subtle patterns that may precede these shift. Faced with limited and imperfect data, such forecasting is fraught with uncertainty. I will present work illustrating how we can quantify the risks of false alarms and missed detection of these early warning signals, and illustrate how this information can be used to inform robust decision-making that may avoid collapse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Different ways of visualizing distribution overlap</title>
      <link>/2012/02/03/different-ways-of-visualizing-distribution-overlap/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2012 10:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/03/different-ways-of-visualizing-distribution-overlap/</guid>
      <description>I spend a lot of time comparing distributions. There&amp;rsquo;s lots of different ways to visualize these comparisons, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what is the most effective &amp;amp; intuitive way to indicate their overlap.
Distributions Boxplot Violinplot Beanplot ROC Curve These images in gallery format with examples from two other data sources as well (click on image to zoom into gallery).
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;warningsignals&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2012-02-03 00:00:00&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2012-02-03 11:00:00&amp;rdquo;]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2012/01/24/tuesday-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2012 15:04:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/24/tuesday-11/</guid>
      <description>Resilience seminar  the unhelpful resilience of invaded systems (ecosystem engineers anyone? Cheatgrass change the fire regime, salt-cedar ) Examples in cheatgrass invading sagebrush, and saltcedar invading cottonwoods. Variables on axes? Problem of dimensionality? resilient to what? Carpenter&amp;rsquo;s rigidity trap (need to eliminate something) vs poverty trap (something is missing) promote a small disturbance to reset the system &amp;ndash; when are small disturbances stabilizing? (escape the rachet?)  pdg-control  Summary for Training Problem II  Warning Signals  Figures for Alan paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday -- meetings</title>
      <link>/2012/01/18/wednesday-meetings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2012 23:22:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/18/wednesday-meetings/</guid>
      <description>Alan meeting write write write
Duncan Meeting Troubleshooting S3 and S4 Try adding methods? Changing order on NAMESPACE?
Leaving ouch off the import list: no errors, but within functions, don&amp;rsquo;t get S4 method. import but don&amp;rsquo;t depend on ouch: error. accurate, since simulate is left as an s3 function at the user level.
What a headache. See stackQ.
manuscript Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback
Meredith Meeting Run a science policy workshop with Davis open science group?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal policy with assymetric costs to changing harvest quotas</title>
      <link>/2012/01/06/optimal-policy-with-assymetric-costs-to-changing-harvest-quotas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 13:52:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/01/06/optimal-policy-with-assymetric-costs-to-changing-harvest-quotas/</guid>
      <description>The optimal policy with symmetric L1 costs to changing the quotas results in the solutions that stop changing, sometimes at no harvest (if there&amp;rsquo;s scrap value), or at some fixed high harvest if no scrap value. (See earlier notes). Asymmetric costs of comparable magnitude result in more crashes.
When we apply an L1 norm cost of the same magnitude as before for decreasing quotas, but allow increasing quotas to be free (no cost to environmental lobby), the solution follows the Reed optimum is in purple (harvest_alt) (cost-free adjustment), while the blue is the harvest level being implemented with a cost:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/12/09/friday-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2011 13:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/09/friday-9/</guid>
      <description>Wrightscape/pmc  Writing up derivation from Thursday properly / for manuscript. Writing up test cases for method2, direct evaluation of covariance matrix for comparisons Minor revisions submitted to Evolution  pdg-control To Do  Implement the NCO. Implement HS SDP Closer read of (Sethi et. al. 2005), (Su &amp;amp; Peterman, 2012) and Woodward &amp;amp; Tomberlin  Warning signals  Allee effects in linear programming with different classes. Timescales of noise using van Kampen expansion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - wrightscape runs and various other things</title>
      <link>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 18:01:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/07/wednesday-11/</guid>
      <description>pdg-control  plots for changing costs Report out to Training Problem II group.  ggplot note defining functions that return a ggplot object can be tricky. If you compute some objects in the plot function (stats etc), those stats are not stored by the object (due to lazy evaluation, usually a very nice time-saving feature), so the plot cannot be produced unless the function returns those things to the global environment (or from wherever the plot will be printed/evaluated).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday -- two insights</title>
      <link>/2011/12/06/tuesday-two-insights/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2011 21:46:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/12/06/tuesday-two-insights/</guid>
      <description>Control &amp;amp; Optimization Dominique Bonvin visit  two-step control (optimize parameters, optimize mean-square error between model and measurement also by parameter adjustment) fails when reality isn&amp;rsquo;t in the model set. Problem is under-determined (N free variables, 4N equations). (converges, but onto the wrong optimum).
 Better solution &amp;ndash; adjust the penalty/regularization terms to to get better agreement between model and data
 Bonvin approach &amp;ndash; adjust the control instead (NCO Control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - various logistics, then checking likelihood calculation</title>
      <link>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2011 20:20:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/30/wednesday-various-logistics-then-checking-likelihood-calculation/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci  rOpenSci wins runner up prize in PLoS + Mendeley&amp;rsquo;s Binary Battle! Write replies to interview questions with Mendeley. roxygenizing documentation for RMendeley &amp;ndash; about half done  pdg-control  Call with Jake scheduled for tomorrow Emails with Michael. I&amp;rsquo;ll implement delay intervals, he&amp;rsquo;ll add costs to adjustment. Need to fix/finish delay interval optimization calculation (exponent of matrix &amp;amp; beta)  Warning Signals Meeting with Alan
 Regime shifts Emphasize the RO curve in uncertainty analysis See (Dulvy et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/11/18/friday-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 17:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/18/friday-7/</guid>
      <description>Connecting weather fluctuations to trends in climate: should really consider replicating (Min et. al. 2011) and (Pall et. al. 2011).
Ooh.. David&amp;rsquo;s Nature Climate paper (McCollum et. al. 2011). (Does UC Davis really not have access to this journal?)
Sebastian mentioned his advisor&amp;rsquo;s work oninverting the sphere without creating a fold, including a proof through a series of physical models made with chickenwire. Math is crazy.
Reviewing Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s manuscript on stochastic sinks at lab meeting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crashing stocks and optimal harvesting effort on Allee effects</title>
      <link>/2011/11/09/crashing-stocks-and-optimal-harvesting-effort-on-allee-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 23:34:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/09/crashing-stocks-and-optimal-harvesting-effort-on-allee-effects/</guid>
      <description>Modeling choices Allee effect model: Myers Beverton-Holt with harvesting-effort mortality:
$$ x_{t+1} = f(x) = \frac{a x_t^{\alpha}}{1+ x_t^{\alpha}/b} - e x $$ For $ \alpha = 2 $, equilibrium points are $ x = 0 $ and
$$ x = \frac{ab}{2(1+e)} \pm \frac{1}{2} \sqrt{ \left(\frac{ab}{1+e}\right)^2-4b } $$
As written this differs from our earlier solutions a couple respects &amp;ndash; the growth function applies to the unharvested population, which then experiences harvesting mortality, and the control variable is fishing effort, not harvest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals - noise response</title>
      <link>/2011/11/03/warning-signals---noise-response/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 11:27:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/03/warning-signals---noise-response/</guid>
      <description>Dakos (Dakos et. al. 2012) considers $ \tfrac{dx}{dt} = f(x,p) $ and perturbs the parameter randomly to introduce variation. Evaluating around an equilibrium where $ f(x^, p^) = 0 $, they expand to first order (citing (Ripa &amp;amp; Heino, 1999)):
$$ \frac{dx}{dt} = \partial_x f(x^,p^)(x-x^) + \partial_p f(x^,p^) (p - p^) $$
and taking $ \xi = x- x^* $, with some slight of hand argue this can be rewritten as an Ito process,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control examples continued: Bellman,  Dynamic Programming</title>
      <link>/2011/10/28/optimal-control-examples-continued-bellman-dynamic-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2011 23:23:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/28/optimal-control-examples-continued-bellman-dynamic-programming/</guid>
      <description>Discrete-time state equation Discrete-time solution appears to be all about dynamic programming
and a chance for me to remember that I&amp;rsquo;m out of practice writing recursive functions. It&amp;rsquo;s just that in thinking about the problem, you start from the end, with the trivial subcase, and keep adding the layers. But the recursive function kinda starts at the beginning, and that trivial case is the exit condition. R doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem very efficient with these recursive functions, so this might become a C sub-routine eventually.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: Optimal Control</title>
      <link>/2011/10/21/friday-optimal-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2011 23:15:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/21/friday-optimal-control/</guid>
      <description>Optimal control Imagine we&amp;rsquo;re trying to minimize $J = \theta( y(t_F), t_F)$
subject to both the state equations: $\dot y = f(y(t), u(t))$, Note these are continuous, applying at all times $t$.
and boundary conditions: $\psi(y(t_F), u(t_F), t_F) = 0$. These are discrete, applying only at fixed time $t_F $. We have to put the continuous constraint in as an integral:
$$ \hat J = \left[\phi + \mathbf{\nu}^T \psi \right]_{tF} - \int{t_I}^{t_F} \mathbf{\lambda}^T \left(\dot{\mathbf{y}} - f(\mathbf{y}(t),\mathbf{u}(t)) \right) dt $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rewrites</title>
      <link>/2011/10/17/rewrites/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 17:37:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/17/rewrites/</guid>
      <description>Add more data set examples Remove skew, Remove the broken CaCO3 analysis Show distributions for increased sampling effort. Does time interval make a difference for convergence of deuterium2 run? Nope. Fails in parallel, running in series.  Code:  get away from explicit parallelization and deeply nested functions. really master optimizers, and avoid errors &amp;amp; failed convergence. store finished data for plotting as data objects. CaCO3 example -&amp;gt; MLE estimate of unstable model doesn&amp;rsquo;t converge, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be used to simulate then!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday, more runs</title>
      <link>/2011/10/17/friday-more-runs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 13:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/17/friday-more-runs/</guid>
      <description>A couple more runs:
G10:
G8: G7: G6: K9: K8: Stable model: IBM critical on first half of data:  Estimate the nonlinear model, show this method does worse than the linear estimation Apply to systems with alternate dynamics. Parameter distributions writing &amp;amp; formatting continue&amp;hellip;  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/10/12/wednesday-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 22:01:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/12/wednesday-10/</guid>
      <description>8:30 gist - flush swap. Catalyst grant review. 9-9:30 SCHA stuff 9:30 - query roc curve thresholds 10 - 10:30 post rfishbase update 10:30 http://openfisheries.org/ 11:15 back to roc curves. noon. curves threshold reading done. lunch.  PNAS writing, examples.
Adding more Drake-data examples: on farm, running G10 and G6.
 1pm-2pm domes 2pm back to writing  Launch additional data runs: deut2, trying in series.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday - forage fish &amp; cascades</title>
      <link>/2011/10/05/wednesday-forage-fish-cascades/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2011 23:38:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/10/05/wednesday-forage-fish-cascades/</guid>
      <description>Forage fish presentation Some simulations exploring top-down &amp;amp; bottom up control concepts in simple models.
$$ \frac{dN}{dt} = r N\left( 1 - \frac{N}{K} \right) - \alpha N P $$ $$ \frac{dP}{dt} = \beta \alpha N P - \mu P $$ Note that at equilibrium, N depends only on predator dynamics, P on K and r. $$\hat N = \frac{\mu}{\alpha\beta} $$ $$ \hat P = \frac{r}{\alpha}\left( 1 - \frac{N}{K} \right) $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Van Kampen Expansion and Stochastic population dynamics</title>
      <link>/2011/09/21/van-kampen-expansion-and-stochastic-population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2011 13:02:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/21/van-kampen-expansion-and-stochastic-population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Embedding a file from some of my earlier work illustrating the use of the linear noise approximation describing demographic noise processes and highlighting some of the more interesting results therein.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/19/monday-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2011 23:55:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/19/monday-9/</guid>
      <description> Catching up on ToCs, reading.
 Working on THEE review.
 Manuscript edits.
 Algorithms group meeting - planning for quarter.
 Interview on KDVS In which I discuss mathematical ecology with my advisor and our local radio station.
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>pdg-control pdg-control, Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/13/2588/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 09:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/13/2588/</guid>
      <description>Tuesday, August 13 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Outline for Day 2 (Donahue/Armsworth)
Adaptive Control, Jake Introduced by he two-armed bandit problem, Rothchild i = 1,2. $ T_i $ is the number of trials, $ N_i $ are numbers of successes.
Define $$ \rho_i = \frac{1}{1+T_i}, \mu_i = \frac{N_i}{1+T_i} $$
If i is played $ p_i $ becomes
$$ \frac{p_i}{1+p_i} = \frac{1}{T+2} $$
If i is played and successful $ \mu_i $ becomes</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pretty Darn Good Control Working Group</title>
      <link>/2011/09/12/pretty-darn-good-control-working-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2011 12:49:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/12/pretty-darn-good-control-working-group/</guid>
      <description>Monday, August 12 8:00 Coffee &amp;amp; Breakfast at NIMBioS 8:45 Welcome to NIMBioS (Lou Gross, Director of NIMBioS) 9:00 Intro to the pdg-control Working Group (Paul Armsworth) 9:30 Introductions by each Working Group Participant 5-minute self-introduction to the group, including your background, expertise, and current work 10:30 Break 11:00 Introduction to Training Problem 1 &amp;amp; Discussion (Jim Sanchirico)
Training problem 0: Optimal Control Jim
maximize present discounted value:
$$\max_{h_t} \int_0^T e^{-rt} \Pi(h_t) dt $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/09/07/wednesday-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2011 12:30:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/07/wednesday-8/</guid>
      <description>Alan Meeting Next steps directions
 economics of uncertainty in early warning
 simulated data approach - insect pest dynamics.
 cod data set. fisheries depensation
  Send Alan: Slides, CV (for post doc apps)
Discussed some relevant literature, mostly for the warning signals in fisheries questions: (Colchero &amp;amp; Clark, 2012), (Hutchings, 2000), HUTCHINGS &amp;amp; REYNOLDS, 2004, (Minckley et. al. 2012), (Myers et. al. 1995), (Schröder et. al. 2012)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday Reading</title>
      <link>/2011/09/01/thursday-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 23:58:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/01/thursday-reading/</guid>
      <description>Very interesting article on tipping points that seems to answer a question I put to Vasilis back in 2009 at IIASA: whether critical transitions due to bifurcations could be distinguished from stochastic transitions due to rare events Ditlevsen &amp;amp; Johnsen, 2010. Argues that some of the well-known climate transitions may have been stochastic transitions instead. Will need a closer read to better assess how they are distinguishing between such transitions in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/31/wednesday-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2011 12:09:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/31/wednesday-7/</guid>
      <description>Reading Wait, the storage effect is often evolutionarily unstable? Yikes. (Snyder &amp;amp; Adler, 2011). Will have to read this more closely.
 Vasseur &amp;amp; Fox nice AD paper in PNAS Am Nat (Vasseur &amp;amp; Fox, 2011), ((One day Am Nat will finish registering the doi for these papers?))   Contrary to previous verbal arguments that suggest that character convergence leads to neutral stability, coadaptation of competing consumers always leads to stable coexistence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/30/tuesday-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2011 22:11:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/30/tuesday-8/</guid>
      <description> Completed review for Methods.
 First read-through of review/resubmission for THEE.
 Working on Evolution manuscript
 Wrightscape: root should have the option of being fixed at phylogenetic mean for all models. Do root estimates occur far from this currently?
 Check graph color schemes, seem inconsistent.
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/09/esa-tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2011 18:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/09/esa-tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Just automatically generating a log form twitter since I cannot find the time to write proper notes. Perhaps those will amended eventually&amp;hellip;
twitter-log    cboettig Great Eco Let mixer. Kudos to Marcel &amp;amp; crew for increasing citation rates w/o decreasing acceptance. Now how bout data sharing reqs? #esa11
   cboettig RT @IceAgeEcologist: #ESA11 Marten Scheffer gets Honorary Member Award (max 20 living awardees); Don Strong ge… (cont) http://deck.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: ESA Conference</title>
      <link>/2011/08/08/monday-esa-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 13:09:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/08/monday-esa-conference/</guid>
      <description>Hope to process the day&amp;rsquo;s happenings later, meanwhile just a snapshot of my twitter-stream notes. My own highlights certainly include Steve Pacala&amp;rsquo;s fantastic plenary session in receiving the MacArthur award, and Mark Urban&amp;rsquo;s crystal clear presentation on &amp;ldquo;climate collisions.&amp;rdquo; I thought I was less tolerant of data-free models with arbitrary assumptions these days, but somehow Mark just swept those concerns away. In pointing out really fundamental concepts, such details just aren&amp;rsquo;t so important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fisheries stock assessments for early warning</title>
      <link>/2011/08/02/fisheries-stock-assessments-for-early-warning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 16:59:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/02/fisheries-stock-assessments-for-early-warning/</guid>
      <description>What you want to look for are stock assessments. For example, for the species closest to home, under the Pacific Fisheries Management Council:
http://www.pcouncil.org/groundfish/stock-assessments/archived-stock-assessments/
Three rockfish species that might be good to look into for your purposes are widow, yelloweye, and bocaccio, but these will have shorter-term data than any of the cod data. Also, NOAA NMFS Technical Reports on individual stocks often have long appendices with lots of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/08/02/monday-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 16:41:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/08/02/monday-8/</guid>
      <description>Peter advice  Figure out your focus. Have all the stuff from your PhD published (at least submitted), make sure your post-doc moves forward. (#1 mistake). Publish with data folks to show you have much to offer the non-theorist community Speak to potential advisers, get them excited about the work. Berkeley over Michigan over NESCent/NIMBioS. Visit Berkeley. Ackerley on sabbatical?  Review for Theoretical Ecology Working on another review. Not a bad paper, but presenting many classical results as novel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday: Fisheries Data Survey, Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2011/07/30/saturday-fisheries-data-survey-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2011 17:26:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/30/saturday-fisheries-data-survey-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Marissa mentioned looking into some of the fisheries data for early warning signals: particularly the Canadian Cod collapse.
Apparently several of the data sets are problematic. All deal with catch instead of abundance and measurement error is highly significant, though it seems that some may suffer from more troublesome systematic errors. Taking a quick look over what is available. Lots of data, but despite what appears to be some rather sophisticated tools available on the sites, I&amp;rsquo;m having a bit of difficulty finding just what I&amp;rsquo;m looking for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday: ESA Practice Talk</title>
      <link>/2011/07/29/2268/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2011 17:26:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/29/2268/</guid>
      <description>Practice talk in Teary today; Jamie, Marissa and myself. Lots of discussion and feedback. Some good general discussion about presentations as well &amp;ndash; Marissa mentioned the Oceanographic Institute&amp;rsquo;s tips for speakers and other resources on her website. Brief notes on changes to make in my talk based on some excellent discussion:
 Julie and others point out I should at least reference Type I &amp;amp; Type II Error &amp;ndash; statement contrasting scientific hypothesis testing vs managing for collapse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Manuscript</title>
      <link>/2011/07/27/weds-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2011 22:38:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/27/weds-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve removed the model choice/model adequacy section of the appendix. This is the section that Reviewer 2 said needed further development, which would be beyond the scope of this paper:
 Here the authors claim that by using particular structural models based on assumptions about underlying dynamics their method makes it easy to identify cases that do not conform to the assumptions. It would be interesting to evaluate this claim but it would require a substantial amount of analysis that may be beyond the scope of a short paper.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: ESA presentation, manuscript/appendix edits </title>
      <link>/2011/07/27/wednesday-esa-presentation-manuscriptappendix-edits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2011 16:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/27/wednesday-esa-presentation-manuscriptappendix-edits/</guid>
      <description>Misc morning  Site trouble, again. requested migrating servers. Done. hope we&amp;rsquo;re more stable now. Checking in with Peter about migrating site domain. Sent request to Matt. Looking over NERSC PI application, see first allocation instructions. Emailed Mary Ann w/ questions on forms. SMB 2012 is at NIMBioS! Nick to join ropensci. Coordinating launch, advisers, etc. Karthik and Scott have done a great job editing my intro post and sprucing up the site.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: ESA presentation</title>
      <link>/2011/07/26/tues-esa-presentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 13:24:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/26/tues-esa-presentation/</guid>
      <description>Working on ESA presentation. See slides and code for details.
 Adding movie a time series which gets longer (and closer to collapse) each frame, with corresponding warning signals for the interval thus far shown below (for CV and autocorrelation). Include sparsely sampled (100) and densely sampled (1000) examples. Compare always using a sliding window-size equal to half the length of the available data (works well on longer time series) to a fixed-width sliding window (doesn&amp;rsquo;t work well ever).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: ESA, appendix, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/07/25/monday-esa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2011 23:22:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/25/monday-esa/</guid>
      <description>Reading Gene expression as a continuous phenotypic trait &amp;ndash; establishing signal for selection over drift. (Bedford &amp;amp; Hartl, 2009) OU vs BM (or just estimation of selection in the OU model relative to tree length) would have been an obvious way to do this, but the paper tries to make the argument that scaling the data and then comparing
$$\frac{\sigma^2}{2\alpha} $$
is some indication.
Model choice section on warning signals Trying to figure out whether or not to remove this section (previously Appendix H: Model Choice and Model Adequacy).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday: Appendix edits</title>
      <link>/2011/07/24/sunday-appendix-edits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2011 16:47:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/24/sunday-appendix-edits/</guid>
      <description>Appendix A. Method Summary &amp;ndash; Basically the &amp;ldquo;methods&amp;rdquo; section as we had it in the Nature version, a bit updated.
 These sections are as before, with minor updates from the reviewers, etc. They&amp;rsquo;re also probably the most important part:
 Appendix B. The data sets Appendix C. Model Derivations Appendix D. Likelihood calculations Appendix E. The likelihood statistic  Appendix F. The distributions for the ROC curves &amp;ndash; these are the former figure 1b/c distributions used to make the ROC curve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday: Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2011/07/17/sunday-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 23:38:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/17/sunday-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Continuing work on warning signals manuscript. Most entries for this work are delayed-release. Some final stages of editing today:
Data sets for appendix  deut1
 caco3
 Other datasets? other drake? other deut?
 launched drakeI9 on farm c0-2 by ssh.
 launched ibm_stable on farm c0-1.
 launched deut2_analysis on farm c0-3, failed. needs better initial conditions to run
  Main paper fix plots: Figure 4 needs axis labels &amp;ndash; done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday - back to Warning Signals MS</title>
      <link>/2011/07/17/saturday---back-to-warning-signals-ms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 10:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/17/saturday---back-to-warning-signals-ms/</guid>
      <description>New outline   &amp;rdquo;An increasing recognition&amp;rdquo;  &amp;ldquo;proof-of-principle&amp;rdquo; - reliability is unknown  &amp;ldquo;Cries wolf&amp;rdquo;  ROC, Fig 1  tau  method  data, Fig 2  analysis, Fig 3  enough data Fig 4  disclaimer  conclusion  Former Outline  Early Warning matter, no-one does statistics We need quantify uncertainty stats ROC curve shows this trade-off ROC also compares different methods &amp;amp; data sizes (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: sending off paper draft, starting applications</title>
      <link>/2011/07/07/thursday-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 19:48:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/07/thursday-8/</guid>
      <description>Add re-sampling blurb to appendix. Done
 Read over manuscript &amp;amp; send to Marissa and Marcel. Done
 Now to spend today working on fellowship applications: research statement and proposal&amp;hellip;
   Appendix edits  Add distributions to the appendix.
 Show where where the data actually fall in the distribution, as would be used in traditional hypothesis testing framework.
 Add extra examples to the appendix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early warning signals presentation notes</title>
      <link>/2011/07/07/early-warning-signals-presentation-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2011 16:40:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/07/early-warning-signals-presentation-notes/</guid>
      <description> motivate story of fisheries management.
 Step advance a time series of fluctuations. Shows a gradual decline and eventually sudden crash. Predict when we crash? Introduce indicators. Advance a different time series, this time displaying summary statistics as we go. Have audience make prediction whether next step will be collapse. Present summary statistics with uncertainty included. (color code confidence?)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exact Simulation by the Gillespie Algorithm</title>
      <link>/2011/07/06/exact-simulation-by-the-gillespie-algorithm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 18:00:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/06/exact-simulation-by-the-gillespie-algorithm/</guid>
      <description>The Gillespie algorithm has two parts: (1) determine what event happens, (2) determine when it happens. Consider the system of equations $$ \dot X_i = f_i(\vec X) $$
where the $f_i$ give the rates of creation and annihilation (negative and postive parts of $f_i(\vec X)$ must be listed seperately) for all species $x_i$. We assume this gives the mean rate at which each event occurs, drawn from on exponential distribution. We could simply draw the associated random exponential time for each reaction, and pick the minimum for which event occurs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: Data wrangling into graphs</title>
      <link>/2011/07/06/wednesday-data-wrangling-into-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2011 14:34:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/06/wednesday-data-wrangling-into-graphs/</guid>
      <description>Really high sampling runs (20000 pts) still don&amp;rsquo;t seem to show any improvement in deut3 dataset summary statistics, perhaps it is the window size. testing by launching deut_replot.R, n5 on zero, 500, 1000, 2000 on a fixed windowsize of 60, see how it compares to the half window. probably because is such a weak signal.
running drake tau sampling with corrected (1&amp;frasl;2 length) windowsizes. &amp;ndash; destroys any improvement in indicators:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: Warning Signals Data Wrangling</title>
      <link>/2011/07/05/tuesday-warning-signals-data-wrangling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2011 17:45:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/05/tuesday-warning-signals-data-wrangling/</guid>
      <description>Revise abstract. 10a-11a. done.  Misc data handling 11-1pm
 wrote a file to fix flickr data file names that are occasionally mangled by parallel loop printing. wrote a file to plot $m T$ values on each dataset to get a sense of which have the most dramatic warning signals. running on one.   locale troubles on install lead to errors in data read  Error in make.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals writing, organization, appendices</title>
      <link>/2011/07/04/warning-signals-writing-organization-appendices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2011 19:03:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/04/warning-signals-writing-organization-appendices/</guid>
      <description>main text Summary Sentence. Abstract
Paragraphs  Early Warning matter, no-one does statistics We need quantify uncertainty stats ROC curve shows this trade-off ROC also compares different methods &amp;amp; data sizes (i.e. Fig 4) Quantifying &amp;ldquo;increasing variance&amp;rdquo; etc &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;ll use tau We&amp;rsquo;ll also do a likelihood-based method Introduce the datasets ROC curves on the data, Fig 3 Quantifying data necessary, Fig 4 Disclaimers: Not completely general Conclusion  Supporting Online Material Original Appendix had:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday, warning signals writing, etc</title>
      <link>/2011/07/01/friday-warning-signals-writing-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2011 17:57:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/07/01/friday-warning-signals-writing-etc/</guid>
      <description>9-10a email, etc 10 am check simulations: Daphnia examples (Drake data) runs done. A few examples, see neighboring plots in image database for the corresponding distributions and further examples. Runtime of this code (click images for script) about 10 hours on 16 cores on zero.
   launched ibm_analysis.R on zero, n10.
 Writing writing&amp;hellip; first full text draft done.
  Trying to get started on the centos cluster, some trouble submitting job to queue, see email discussion with Bill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: Warning Signals writing, figures, segue</title>
      <link>/2011/06/30/thursday-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2011 10:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/30/thursday-7/</guid>
      <description>Alan meeting Figure 1: Introducing the ROC Curve Figure 2: Standard approach Figure 3: ROC curves corresponding to standard approach Do we show the distributions? &amp;ndash; Create for each, but log in appendix
ROC curves corresponding to increased sampling &amp;ndash; our method, other stats? organize how?
Computational Runs Running at constant sample points rather than sample effort.
 On eleven: n5ibm_stable.R 6pm On zero, n10 drake_analysis.R 6pm On zero, n19 deut_analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals: summary statistic performance at varying sampling effort</title>
      <link>/2011/06/29/warning-signals-summary-statistic-performance-at-varying-sampling-effort/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 22:08:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/29/warning-signals-summary-statistic-performance-at-varying-sampling-effort/</guid>
      <description>oikos post launch case of increased sampling on sim data for autocorrelation (is our approach more robust to model differences?)  IBM data Example Using data from the individual-based model simulation of a system approaching a saddle-node.
Variance While the initial example with variance shows almost no signal, increasing the sampling effort substantially improves the performance. This can be seen in the ROC curves and as a tightening and spreading out of the null and test distributions as the sampling effort is increased.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals writing</title>
      <link>/2011/06/29/warning-signals-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2011 18:35:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/29/warning-signals-writing/</guid>
      <description> Alan Meeting: Discussed yesterday&amp;rsquo;s possible representations, post-doc considerations.
Misc &amp;amp; Reading  Catching up on ToCs, now 13 papers to review Installing pilot mx database for comparative methods data accessible semantic web introduction Dean&amp;rsquo;s Lab statement of mutual expectations: nice guide for things that are too rarely spelled out.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: Warning Signals Manuscript</title>
      <link>/2011/06/27/monday-warning-signals-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 12:33:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/27/monday-warning-signals-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Looking at ways to visually explain receiver-operator characteristic (ROC) curves. Should probably be done in a way that maps the curves to the points along the curve. May make a nice graphic but perhaps unnecessary.
Perhaps simpler to present as single panel Integrating the test distribution to the left instead of the right gives the error rate (Type I/Type II errors, False Alarms/Missed Events):
Analyses  Maximization algorithm failing at initial conditions on deut2</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday</title>
      <link>/2011/06/12/sunday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2011 23:03:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/12/sunday-3/</guid>
      <description> SocialR updates: print runtime, handle NULL mentions, and truncate messages to avoid over-length errors.
 Rmendeley repackage in response to user issue. Updated issues list.
 _warningsignals: _Separate demo scripts for each data set, running analysis now
 reversed nboot and cpu values, way to create very annoying error. Back up and running all demo scripts now.
   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/06/10/friday-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jun 2011 17:21:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/10/friday-6/</guid>
      <description>Finish updates to socialR and wrote post.
 reply to Richard on DataONE workflow internship
 really should meet Bertram, re: workflow, dataONE, open science, etc.
 wrote an avereps fn to replace limma dependency. hmmf.
 setup analysis.R to run complete analysis sets. still testing.
   To Do  consider returning myCall information on most standard functions
 Review model implementations
 model convergence error handling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday -- warning signals manuscript (mostly)</title>
      <link>/2011/06/05/sunday-warning-signals-manuscript-mostly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2011 16:20:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/05/sunday-warning-signals-manuscript-mostly/</guid>
      <description>Updates to Scott&amp;rsquo;s rspringer package
 Grabbed remaining datasets from Dakos et al., added to package
 Reading (Biggs et. al. 2009) a bit more closely
 Writing and revisions on warning signals manuscript.
   References  Biggs R, Carpenter S and Brock W (2009). &amp;ldquo;Turning Back From The Brink: Detecting an Impending Regime Shift in Time to Avert it.&amp;rdquo; Proceedings of The National Academy of Sciences, 106.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2011/06/02/thursday-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 21:31:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/02/thursday-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Alan Meeting Reviewing my edits.
 Writing writing writing
 updating graphs and package
  Reading  Yet another volley in the kin-selection group-selection debate (debacle?)(Marshall, 2011)
 This looks excellent, will have to find time for a closer read: (Davies et. al. 2011)
 Jonah&amp;rsquo;s Science paper, the subject of his Merton-Love seminar, (Piovia-Scott et. al. 2011)
  References  Marshall J (2011). &amp;ldquo;Group Selection And Kin Selection: Formally Equivalent Approaches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals Literature: when stats are and aren&#39;t attempted</title>
      <link>/2011/06/01/warning-signals-literature-when-stats-are-and-arent-attempted/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 15:10:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/06/01/warning-signals-literature-when-stats-are-and-arent-attempted/</guid>
      <description>In preparing manuscript on warning signals, reviewing the literature on when statistical validation of the warning signal is included, and if so, what kind are done. There&amp;rsquo;s certainly no consensus in the approach, with the majority of papers not even attempting a method (and those that do not finding significance). Scheffer&amp;rsquo;s key review (Scheffer et. al. 2009) calls for the need to measure statistical significance of warning signals,
 Therefore, it would be useful to build a set of reliable statistical procedures to test whether an increase in autocorrelation, for example, is significant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday Meetings: Duncan; Alan</title>
      <link>/2011/05/26/thursday-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 23:53:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/26/thursday-6/</guid>
      <description>Duncan Meeting  ROAuth/RCurl question. Mendeley is OAuth 1, github is OAuth 2 (simpler). Both are implemented in pure R in another package, may be good. OAuth 1 constructs complicated http urls with secret, and token, and random key, need to escape chars, etc. OAuth 2 is https, just uses token. Authentication options: Jeff&amp;rsquo;s ROAuth/Duncan&amp;rsquo;s mod, other OAuth package. RMendeley&amp;ndash; windows binary, competition? socialR &amp;ndash; discussed strategy to get a figure with matching code and data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/25/wednesday-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 17:25:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/25/wednesday-5/</guid>
      <description>R packages  Trying to build Windows binaries for R packages using win-builder service.
 First have to get R CMD check working. Check runs in &amp;ndash;vanilla mode so have to tell it where libraries are. Created the file ~/.R/check.Renviron containing the line: R_LIBS=&amp;ldquo;/home/cboettig/R/packages&amp;rdquo; seems to do the trick.
 Successfully built windows binaries for RMendeley package (pre-release, still in development). Download the binaries from github.
 Matt successfully installed CUDA on zero (2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/24/tuesday-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2011 23:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/24/tuesday-4/</guid>
      <description>Warning signals package  Reviewing Numerical challenges for faster analysis on warningsignals
 created a quick mcmcTools package so different packages can use my custom routines. Will have to explore some of the standard packages eventually, though most seem somewhat specialized (the Bayesian task-view is epic). bayesm looks promising, and LearnBayes package that accompanies Jim Albert&amp;rsquo;s book (Albert, unknown) might be worth a closer look.
 Wrote mcmc script for warningsignals, much more debugging to handle out-of-bounds conditions then expected.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/05/03/monday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 11:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/05/03/monday-3/</guid>
      <description>Today:
 Application for CPB travel funds. DONE
 Faxed receipts from Felsenstein&amp;rsquo;s visit. DONE
  Seminar on Species trees Coop/Moore Seminar on *BEAST (Heled &amp;amp; Drummond, 2009) and BEST (Liu et. al. 2008).
Essential differences: BEST uses Mr. Bayes to compute probabilities over gene trees (over uniform prior). Then estimates the species tree by importance sampling from this distribution to reflect constraints under a convergence model. Integrates over effective population sizes rather than estimating (highly uncertain anyway), requires rooting, and a rather fast/loose implementation of ultra-metricizing trees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Warning Signals in Coral Dynamics -- Economic analysis of risk</title>
      <link>/2011/04/19/early-warning-signals-in-coral-dynamics----economic-analysis-of-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2011 11:53:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/19/early-warning-signals-in-coral-dynamics----economic-analysis-of-risk/</guid>
      <description>Alan and I have been considering analyzing a particular system for early warning signals where we could highlight risk management from an economics stand-point, probably with the help of Jim Sanchirico. Our current work focuses on quantifying the relative risk of false alarms and missed detections. While statisticians typically accept a 5% &amp;ldquo;false alarm&amp;rdquo; rate, we argue this given limited data this is always a trade-off against the missed detection rate and hence the location of this threshold should properly a decision of management, not of convention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday: submitting warning signals manuscript</title>
      <link>/2011/04/18/thursday-submitting-warning-signals-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 23:47:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/18/thursday-submitting-warning-signals-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Crazy day today submitting the warning signals manuscript.
 Github hosting Precedings hosting?  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds: Final round edits</title>
      <link>/2011/04/13/weds-final-round-edits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2011 16:21:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/13/weds-final-round-edits/</guid>
      <description> Low-power (40 data-point) IBM simulation example   Consider examples of false negative (Deteriorating example), and negative correlations in constant and deteriorating environments (? - nope) Implement LTC updated models! Working over Alex revisions  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: manuscript and appendix edits</title>
      <link>/2011/04/12/tuesday-manuscript-and-appendix-edits/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2011 23:40:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/12/tuesday-manuscript-and-appendix-edits/</guid>
      <description>Today&amp;rsquo;s log  Edited cover letter summary for public.
 Soliciting feedback on examples in manuscript vs appendix, see Monday&amp;rsquo;s entry. (Entry posted, images added to flickr database)
 Jeff fixed the double-post bug in twitteR, tested update.
 Improved initialization estimates for LSN model in fit_models (code), as identified &amp;amp; discussed in Sunday&amp;rsquo;s entry. Needs testing on a unit case, trying on ibm_analysis.R now&amp;hellip; seems to work fine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday: Warning Signals - Updated graphs</title>
      <link>/2011/04/11/monday-warning-signals-updated-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 22:47:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/11/monday-warning-signals-updated-graphs/</guid>
      <description>Trying a different set-up for the graphs. Added two additional datasets, trying layout of making all three figures into a panels in a single figure.
Concerns:
 Better than only one empirical example, but not sure that the three Glaciation data sets add that much since they are all quite similar. Five panels wide might be too much. Don&amp;rsquo;t have an example where a transition is about to occur but the data doesn&amp;rsquo;t have adequate power even for our Likelihood method, third panel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday: Warning signals edits continue</title>
      <link>/2011/04/11/sunday-warning-signals-edits-continue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2011 08:13:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/11/sunday-warning-signals-edits-continue/</guid>
      <description>Marissa edits &amp;ndash; Nearly done
 Single-figure layout &amp;ndash; DONE
 equations in appendix &amp;ndash; DONE
 convergence / likelihood agreement between constOU and constLSN (Done, see below; consider using for a better initial-condition guessing routine for better convergence)
 Reformulate transcritical bifurcation?
 Rewrite cover letter
   load(&amp;quot;5598226674.Rdat&amp;quot;) require(warningsignals) OU &amp;lt;- deterior_mc$null LSN &amp;lt;- deterior_mc$test LSN_OU &amp;lt;- updateGauss(const_LSN, OU$pars, OU$X) c(OU$loglik, LSN$loglik, LSN_OU$loglik) [1] -1038.510 -1142.539 -1162.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals</title>
      <link>/2011/04/08/warning-signals-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 17:08:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/08/warning-signals-3/</guid>
      <description> ibm simulation fit convergence on constOU vs constLSN &amp;ndash; are likelihood scores off from including out-of-bound parameter estimates? Consider transcritical in levins model setup Consider re-arranging figures: one panel, full-width, variance and autocorrelation only, three empirical examples. Trying smaller numbers of replicates in simulated data to get low-power examples.  flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;stochpop&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-04-06 00:00:00&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-04-11 23:59:59&amp;rdquo;
 move ibm simulation code into warningsignals package Working through Marissa&amp;rsquo;s edits.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals - Manuscript touch-ups</title>
      <link>/2011/04/06/warning-signals-manuscript-touch-ups/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 17:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/06/warning-signals-manuscript-touch-ups/</guid>
      <description>[toc]
Refining examples  Updating finished runs to full formats
 Condensing/organizing code examples under the demos to follow the structure of the paper.
 Currently plotting code for manuscript loads a menagerie of different run results from different files. Would be better to consolidate by dataset.
  Proposed figure changes  Consider multiple empirical examples in main text
 Consider removing skew/kurtosis examples to the supplement?
 Consider other empirical examples</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday finishing up appendices(?)</title>
      <link>/2011/04/01/thursday-finishing-up-appendices/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 15:50:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/01/thursday-finishing-up-appendices/</guid>
      <description>Fresh off the cpus: single replicate examples on the Drake data
What&amp;rsquo;s still running:  likelihood for IBM data with 2000 replicates, nice 19 on zero (ibm_likelihood.R) likelihood for Glaciation I-III with 2000 replicates, nice 18 on zero (deut_likelihood.R) likelihood for Glaciation I-III with 2000 replicates, (nice 19 on one)? (deut_likelihood.R) likelihood on sim data, Glaciation III and CaCO3: 80 replicates on one, nice 1 on one (figure3.R) and with 2000 replicates, nice 19 on one (figure3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday: appendices; parameter distributions</title>
      <link>/2011/03/30/wednesday-appendices-parameter-distributions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2011 17:59:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/30/wednesday-appendices-parameter-distributions/</guid>
      <description>Fixed bug causing montecarlotest() calls not to complete: in likelihood_bifurcation_models, LTC error checking uses any() to see if any Vx are negative, returns NA if none are negative but has NAs. rm.na=TRUE fixed this. GetParNames works, probably worth an appendix section to discuss parameter bootstraps as well, particularly in the cases of low power. Updated codes to turn this flag back on and am re-running. Figure3 plot has been using the 160 bootstrap replicates, updated to the 2000 replicates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday, simulations &amp; appendix</title>
      <link>/2011/03/29/tuesday-simulations-appendix/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 22:45:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/29/tuesday-simulations-appendix/</guid>
      <description>Today mostly working over code sets for examples in appendix, and increasing replicates. Somehow more trouble than it should be, see commit history for today.
ibm_sim.R &amp;ndash; simulate from individual-based dynamics containing a saddle-node bifurcation (fully hysteresis model).
ibm_analysis.R &amp;ndash; run figure1, 2, 3 analysis (correlation test, bootstrap of test, likelihood test) on each data.
ibm_likelihood.R &amp;ndash; shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be needed, all code is in deut_examples.R. Running now due to earlier parallel instance errors during montecarlotest.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday, appendices continue...</title>
      <link>/2011/03/29/monday-appendices-continue/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2011 01:09:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/29/monday-appendices-continue/</guid>
      <description>Finished writing up section on correlations (time averages vs ensembles) and the following section on error types. (yay, that writing went much better than yesterday). Appendices nearly done, a few more bits:
 Must figure out what data examples are going into the supplement. Most should be reasonably straight-forward to set up, may take a while to run.
 Have to figure out what to say about likelihood-based statistical method beyond definition of Cox&amp;rsquo;s delta,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday -- edits and appendices</title>
      <link>/2011/03/27/sunday-edits-and-appendices/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2011 21:34:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/27/sunday-edits-and-appendices/</guid>
      <description>Read over Scheffer&amp;rsquo;s rather nice introduction(Scheffer, 2010) to the Drake paper(Drake &amp;amp; Griffen, 2010). Last paragraph is particularly pertinenant:
 Clearly, we have just scratched the surface in exploring the possibilities and limitations of this emerging field. However, the prospect of identifying generic indicators is exciting, as the approach may provide an independent way to assess the risk of critical transitions. Expansion of our toolbox for prediction is especially welcome given the almost insurmountable problem of modelling complex systems in a quantitatively accurate way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturday-- Appendices</title>
      <link>/2011/03/26/saturday---appendices/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 23:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/26/saturday---appendices/</guid>
      <description>Appendices Working on Appendices
Ergodicity Null of Kendall&amp;rsquo;s tau/rank correlations &amp;ndash; independence of X and Y, not satisfied even over replicates. Adjusted codes to use Pearson&amp;rsquo;s (default option, need to pass option up to higher-level functions). Repeated Figure 2 plots with Pearson&amp;rsquo;s, results not much different, funny multimodal though:
Actually verifying independence is rather more challenging, though convenient in this case that a test such as Pearson&amp;rsquo;s is not designed to do this, see http://en.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2011/03/25/friday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 17:25:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/25/friday-3/</guid>
      <description>Reading Some nice theoretical ecology papers out from our group recently, looking over today:
 Paul&amp;rsquo;s paper (Williams &amp;amp; Hastings, 2011) deals with some interesting work on persistence in complex models, (stochastic systems of mixture models), curious how it compares to the conclusions of (Schreiber, 2010).
 Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s paper (Schreiber et. al. 2011) with Dan Bolnick and Burger, another example of the importance of individual heterogeneity, this time in a nice phenotype/genotype specific way by combining quantitative genetics approaches with predator dynamics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2011/03/24/thursday-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 23:19:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/24/thursday-3/</guid>
      <description>Assembled plots for figures 1,2,3 see paper_plots.R. Considerable adjustment of axes/layout. Sent figures out for comments.
 Considered removing skew/kurtosis from Figure 1 &amp;amp;/or Figure 2, currently leaving in (particularly in Figure 2 to make point clear that no indicator works well?) Easy to remove using paper_plots.R script.   To Do list:  Figure 3 layout should mimic Figure 2 as much as possible (font sizes, margins, etc).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/03/23/wednesday-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 18:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/23/wednesday-2/</guid>
      <description>Still to do on figures:
 Plots with and without skew/kurtosis &amp;ndash; DONE, enabled for Figure 1 &amp;amp; 2
 Combine plots into full panels &amp;ndash; DONE for Figure 1 &amp;amp; Figure 2
 separate plotting codes from analysis codes (at least whenever takes any computational effort/time to produce). &amp;ndash; DONE
 bootstrap_indicators should have option of which indicators are included &amp;ndash; DONE
 all_indicators should have option of which indicators are included &amp;ndash; DONE</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday: Figures, figures, figures</title>
      <link>/2011/03/23/tuesday-figures-figures-figures/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 10:37:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/23/tuesday-figures-figures-figures/</guid>
      <description>Today working mostly on selecting examples of data sets to include in the figure patterns. Working with the idea of three figures &amp;ndash; data, bootstraps of Tau, bootstraps of likelihood &amp;ndash; in panels for several examples: some real data sets and some simulated data sets with and without warning. In addition to this, I still have some more work to do with references, and refining the writing of a few of the appendices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday -- Edits and organization</title>
      <link>/2011/03/22/monday-edits-and-organization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2011 09:07:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/22/monday-edits-and-organization/</guid>
      <description>Skype with Alan: 9-9:4
 Figures as panels
 Write Appendix
 Finish References
 Move into Word
   Sims  LSN m = -0.049, N =50, T=100
 LSN m = -0.049, N =100, T=100
 LTC m = -0.049, N =100, T=100
 LTC m = -0.049, N =100, T=50
 LTC m = -0.049, N =100, T=200
  Autocorrelation [flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;stochpop, acor&amp;rdquo; tag_mode=&amp;ldquo;all&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-03-21 10:00:00&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-03-22 10:00:00&amp;rdquo;]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sunday - manuscript and simulations</title>
      <link>/2011/03/21/sunday-manuscript-and-simulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2011 11:19:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/21/sunday-manuscript-and-simulations/</guid>
      <description>Working on manuscript. lot of writing / editing.
Edited package and example to include skew and kurtosis bootstrap estimates of tau. Currently testing.
 m = -0.04, N = 50, nboot = 160, (with all moments)
 m = -0.04, N = 50, nboot = 800, (with all moments)
 m = -0.05, N = 50, nboot = 800, (with all moments)
 m = -0.02, N = 500, nboot = 800 (without skew/kurtosis yet)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing: Warning Signals Mansucript</title>
      <link>/2011/03/20/writing-warning-signals-mansucript/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2011 14:39:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/20/writing-warning-signals-mansucript/</guid>
      <description>Summary Paragraph
 Critical transitions exist (Holling, 1973), (May, 1977),(Scheffer et. al. 2001) Warning signals exist (Scheffer et. al. 2009), (Drake &amp;amp; Griffen, 2010) Warning signals are summary statistics, critical slowing down (Wissel, 1984). Statement of general problem: double-edged sword &amp;ndash; no quantification of the chance detection scheme will fail. We provide a way to do this We find existing methods lack sufficient power and have high false-alarm potential We provide a model-based solution using machinery of modern likelihood statistics  Background  Define CSD, standard detection scheme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals examples and tracking graphs</title>
      <link>/2011/03/19/warning-signals-examples-and-tracking-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 20:52:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/19/warning-signals-examples-and-tracking-graphs/</guid>
      <description>Working on more examples for the notebook. Currently exploring a collection of simulated examples. In particular, would be useful to have simulated examples that look as realistic in data-density as possible (i.e. fewer sample points, also shorter sampling interval relative to timescale, so doesn&amp;rsquo;t look like a fuzzy caterpillar. Second, would be good to include examples on data simulated from non-linearized systems made to represent some richer bifurcation examples. Finally it would be good to include as many real-data examples as reasonable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals in Ecological Systems: Revisions and Drake &amp; Griffen Data</title>
      <link>/2011/03/17/warning-signals-in-ecological-systems-drake-griffen-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 09:59:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/17/warning-signals-in-ecological-systems-drake-griffen-data/</guid>
      <description>Manuscript revisions  Heard back from Alan this morning on manuscript, need to cut wordcount in half, from 3000 to 1500 words. Should emphasize the countless and utterly arbitrary choices made in every one of these analyses. Should emphasize our approach can be applied without replicates. (also without interpolating/having evenly sampled data) Should do coefficient of variation on non-detrended data(?) should discuss?  Chemostat data This morning Alan sent me the data used by Drake &amp;amp; Griffen (Drake &amp;amp; Griffen, 2010).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wednesday</title>
      <link>/2011/03/16/wednesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 23:49:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/16/wednesday/</guid>
      <description>Updated dependencies of warningsignals package. Removed old dependencies, migrated montecarlotest into package, removing the pmc dependency.
 Updated my webpage teaching statement (lunch break)
 montecarlotest wasn&amp;rsquo;t getting sfLibrary(warningsignals) called in yesterday&amp;rsquo;s runs, so redoing this.
 Writing &amp;ndash; conclusion, finalized organization, sent off to Alan.
   To Do:  Panel for models. Appendix for model derivations.
 Panel for approach/algorithm. Appendix for algorithm implementation.
 Figure review</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tuesday</title>
      <link>/2011/03/15/tuesday-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 22:38:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/15/tuesday-2/</guid>
      <description>Variance and warning signals Sebastian has several examples of dynamical systems that decrease in variance as they approach a bifurcation. In some sense this is not surprising, both are through the collapse of periodic attractors. Figure 2d in TPB paperSchreiber, 2003 has an example in a discrete system, and Figure 5a in the Ecology Letters paper (Schreiber &amp;amp; Rudolf, 2008) has a continuous-time example. Consider for instance the supercritical Hopf bifurcation, in which a stable limit cycle vanishes into an unstable node, as in a van der Pol oscillator,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals, Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/03/14/warning-signals-monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 11:18:59 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/14/warning-signals-monday/</guid>
      <description>Set up a few long runs of simulated data to better illustrate the effects of sampling time and density, and better resolve the distributions.
 Longer baseline run, nice 19, indicator_vs_likelihood.R 1600 reps, m=-0.015, N=500, T=100
 Longer sampling, same interval: nice 18, stronger_signal.R 160 reps m=-0.015, N = 2500, T=500
  Fails to compute, looks like poor estimates of model fits.
 Denser sampling, nice 17: indicator_vs_likelihood.R 160 reps, m=-0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals: summary stats vs likelihood on real and simulated data</title>
      <link>/2011/03/11/warning-signals-summary-stats-vs-likelihood-on-real-and-simulated-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2011 14:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/11/warning-signals-summary-stats-vs-likelihood-on-real-and-simulated-data/</guid>
      <description>Added bar of observed tau on real data to the tau distributions. Fixed the tau-distribution method, running new data and real examples now.
Simulated data: can tell tau apart for instance, for autocorrelation (see photostream for variance, code hash for parameters, etc). While can&amp;rsquo;t really tell anything based on the tau on the autocorrelation for the Deuterium data for Glaciation III (which has just about the clearest signal of the deuterium set): Waiting to see how the likelihood statistics compare on these examples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical challenges in likelihood estimation of time-dep OU models</title>
      <link>/2011/03/10/numerical-challenges-in-likelihood-estimation-of-time-dep-ou-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 23:46:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/10/numerical-challenges-in-likelihood-estimation-of-time-dep-ou-models/</guid>
      <description>Worried about accurate maximum likelihood estimates of parameters, as the optimization could still converge on values not far from the starting conditions (not as surprising as the starting parameters are estimated intelligently first from the summary statistics) but could also vary depending on initial conditions.
Second, while it requires some re-parameterization, the stationary model for both linearized transcritical (LTC) bifurcation model and the linearized saddle-node (LSN) model are identically Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals data examples</title>
      <link>/2011/03/09/warning-signals-data-examples/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 16:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/09/warning-signals-data-examples/</guid>
      <description>Working on a little data exploration while writing up manuscript. I have been puzzled why it appears that most estimates of tau on the CaCO3 data infer negative correlation, as in
Despite the fact that there seems to be a loss of stability in the model:
require(warningsignals) load(&amp;quot;CaCO3.Rdat&amp;quot;) timedep$pars Ro m theta sigma 8.36841588 -0.03347119 -2.86194248 282.03234042  So m is negative, so that the system is loosing stability, but only very gradually.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals: Comparing Methods on Climate Data</title>
      <link>/2011/03/01/warning-signals-comparing-methods-on-climate-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 16:51:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/03/01/warning-signals-comparing-methods-on-climate-data/</guid>
      <description>Continuing my exploration in applying these techniques to real climate data. Applying the Kendall&amp;rsquo;s Tau based approach on real data.
Greenhouse Earth, CaCO3 data:
Glaciation I-IV (deuterium data)
These use the unadjusted timeseries, and hence don&amp;rsquo;t reproduce the values of Kendall&amp;rsquo;s tau statistic reported in (Dakos et. al. 2008). In fact they don&amp;rsquo;t even agree on the sign &amp;ndash; visually many of the datasets are certainly decreasing in variance. I ran the Monte-Carlo distributions for tau on models estimated from these data-sets with and without warning, for variance (left) and autocorrelation (right), in the CaCO3 data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals on Real data continued</title>
      <link>/2011/02/28/warning-signals-on-real-data-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 12:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/28/warning-signals-on-real-data-continued/</guid>
      <description>Continuing my tweaks to code to apply warning signals to the climate data used in (Dakos et. al. 2008). After adjusting my code to deal with variably spaced sampling intervals, I reread the supplement &amp;ndash; I had forgotten that they don&amp;rsquo;t actually consider data with variable time-scales, but instead interpolate the curves to have equally spaced sampling intervals.
Obviously this is not ideal. It is true that the autocorrelation would be impacted by non-equally spaced data, while there is no reason to do so for the variance indicator.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals on Real Data?</title>
      <link>/2011/02/27/warning-signals-on-real-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2011 16:24:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/27/warning-signals-on-real-data/</guid>
      <description>Grabbed the data used in (Dakos et. al. 2008), which is includes climate data from the Deuterium levels in the Vostok ice core (Petit et. al. 1999), showing transitions into the last several ice ages, and calcium carbonate from Eocene &amp;ldquo;greenhouse&amp;rdquo; climate (Tripati et. al. 2005), and carbon-14 data from the Younger Dryas (Hughen, 2000). Data is all freely provided through NOAA.
 CaCO3 data file (Tripati et. al. 2005), NOAA entry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ESA 2011 Abstract: Limits to Detection of Early Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2011/02/23/esa-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2011 17:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/23/esa-2011/</guid>
      <description>Just submitted my abstract to for an oral presentation at the Ecological Society of America 2011 meeting in Austin, based on my recent work on early warning signals. Here it is:
Limits to Detection of Early Warning Signals of Population Collapse Background/Question/Methods The recognition that ecosystems can undergo sudden shifts to alternate, less desirable stable states has led to the desire to identify early warning signs of these impending collapses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weds &amp; Framing warning signals manuscript</title>
      <link>/2011/02/16/weds-framing-warning-signals-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2011 23:56:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/16/weds-framing-warning-signals-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Alan Meeting, 10a Good meeting discussing warning signals manuscript details and organization. Particularly on the best way to present some of the major conceptual and semantic elements: there are many ways to describe the same thing, each of which carries a lot of semantic baggage.
Do we choose to present this as:
As Hypothesis Testing Null = isn&amp;rsquo;t a loss of stability (distribution produced by the MLE model of no stability loss), hypothesis = there is (distribution produced by, MLE model with stability loss) determine p value for falsely rejecting the null and the power of the statistical test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday</title>
      <link>/2011/02/14/monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2011 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/14/monday/</guid>
      <description>Excellent CPB visiting weekend with perspective students Thurs evening - Sunday morning. Hosting students, etc doesn&amp;rsquo;t make for much of a research entry Friday. Catching up with many things today.
 ESA registration. Topics, Abstract
 Checking in with Alan
 Data workshop: create &amp;amp; post advertisement, map out subject areas
 Reading: Syst Bio issue
 Updated pubmed author alerts
 Checking in with Peter &amp;amp; Graham on revisions</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals &amp; hpc</title>
      <link>/2011/02/04/warning-signals-hpc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 18:30:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/04/warning-signals-hpc/</guid>
      <description>Morning has been rather difficult trying to get simulations up and running. Parallel library isn&amp;rsquo;t running on zero or one, variety of errors that seemed to be machine dependent and reminiscent of the ~./sfCluster problem, 3 hrs of debugging revealed this was indeed just a bug in my updated code. (In changing to my object-oriented simulate.gauss and update.gauss functions rather than calling the specific functions directly I hadn&amp;rsquo;t updated all the function calls).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Progress on warning signals</title>
      <link>/2011/02/03/progress-on-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2011 18:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/02/03/progress-on-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Going several directions at once in tweaking the warning signals code to make sure I have clear comparisons that are not resulting from any limitations in the numerical algorithms. Performing a variety of error checks, etc:
 Comparing fixed models vs comparing models estimated from the data
 Ensure that const model doesn&amp;rsquo;t attempt to estimate m (doesn&amp;rsquo;t impact likelihood anyway
 Ensure only positive values of sigma are returned (trying use trigger in setLTC and setLSN to return infinite variance if sigma is negative)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals: Indicators vs Likelihood continued</title>
      <link>/2011/01/31/warning-signals-indicators-vs-likelihood-continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 16:49:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/31/warning-signals-indicators-vs-likelihood-continued/</guid>
      <description>Continuing to explore examples
Some difficulty in the &amp;ldquo;snowfall&amp;rdquo; parallel computation engine, removing the ~/.sfCluster directory seems to reset the error &amp;ldquo;unable to unserialize nodes&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo; Also don&amp;rsquo;t have good handling of variable names for tracking the boostrapping of parameters. For the moment have just added a toggle to suppress these to avoid dim mismatch in rownames command. Strange that this happens to the indicator_vs_likelihood code but not to the nearly-identical call to montecarlotest() in lin_bifur_models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals of differing stregths by likelihood and by indicator</title>
      <link>/2011/01/28/warning-signals-of-differing-stregths-by-likelihood-and-by-indicator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2011 17:59:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/28/warning-signals-of-differing-stregths-by-likelihood-and-by-indicator/</guid>
      <description>Strong indicator example: m=-0.049, T=100, Ro=5 And likelihood ratio monte carlo model choice (nonparametric bootstrap) has no trouble: Less strong stability loss, m=-0.02 How statistics perform: </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals vs model choice</title>
      <link>/2011/01/27/warning-signals-vs-pmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 17:11:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/27/warning-signals-vs-pmc/</guid>
      <description>Continuing writing and experimentation for examples in the warning signals manuscript, figuring out how to explain the need for the likelihood-based model comparison approach rather than the standard method of summary statistics.
The traditional approach computes a particular &amp;ldquo;leading indicator&amp;rdquo;, such as variance or autocorrelation, in a sliding window along the time series. If the system is loosing stability approaching a bifurcation, it&amp;rsquo;s leading eigenvalue must go through zero and hence shows critical slowing down, with the associated pattern of increasing autocorrelation an increasing variance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals, Power and Sufficient Statistics</title>
      <link>/2011/01/10/warning-signals-power-and-sufficient-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2011 15:57:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/01/10/warning-signals-power-and-sufficient-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Working on warning signals manuscript. Looking at overall powercurves as a function of sample size and rate of stability loss in both models. Planning to repeat that analysis with summary statistics approach to illustrate the relative loss in power of the &amp;ldquo;leading indicator&amp;rdquo; approach. (simulations just set up to run now, figures should appear below as they complete. Click on figures for links to code).
 Power curve based on transcritical bifurcation as a function of rate of stability loss:  [flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;search&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;warningsignals, LTC, stability&amp;rdquo; tag_mode=&amp;ldquo;all&amp;rdquo; min_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-01-10 00:00:00&amp;rdquo; max_upload_date=&amp;ldquo;2011-01-12 23:59:59&amp;rdquo;]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals manuscript</title>
      <link>/2010/12/10/warning-signals-manuscript/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 21:10:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/10/warning-signals-manuscript/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with Alan today to discuss outline. Came up with basic break-down of paragraphs:
 Intro/Abstract
 Scope: Previous work, scope simple example existence of warning signal/CSD is clear. Identifiability/Power not clear. Mention the issue of Replicates
 Nonlinearity not observed with infinite data
 reasons detection fails: Identifiability issue &amp;amp; Power issue. Example signal that exists but inadequate power to detect?
 Eigenvalue story
 Probability of data vs Probability of a statistic</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Power in Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2010/12/09/exploring-power-in-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2010 23:03:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/09/exploring-power-in-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Started trying to get the power curves for sample-size and rate of change. Currently focusing on the transcritical bifurcation model. This first pass uses just 100 replicates, which appears to be not nearly enough. Need some troubleshooting on handling to get power curves out. Scroll through, the set has 65 different images:
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;tag&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;stochpowercurvesslides&amp;rdquo;]
(code ids in image discription, compare to structured-popultions git log. )
Includes plots of the timeseries, giving a visual clue of how dramatic the warning signal is under each case.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/2010/12/04/identifying-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 22:41:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/12/04/identifying-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Updated methods for the Monte Carlo estimate of the distributions of likelihood ratios completed on Wednesday this week, modulo some troubleshooting of code. Now exploring the parameter range in which warning signals can be identified with accurate power. Individual power tests provide a good start, but remains to generate power curves for each bifurcation type by magnitude of the loss of stability, length/duration of the timeseries and the sampling frequency.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tues: Fitting the limiting OU models to each bifurcation</title>
      <link>/2010/11/30/tues-fitting-the-limiting-ou-models-to-each-bifurcation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2010 22:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/30/tues-fitting-the-limiting-ou-models-to-each-bifurcation/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I derived the linearized SDEs for the saddle node bifurcation :
$$ dX = 2\sqrt{r(t)} (\sqrt{r(t)} + \theta -X) dt + \sigma \sqrt{\sqrt{r(t)}+\theta} dB_t $$
and the transcritical bifurcation
$$ dX = r(t) (K - X) dt + \sqrt{K} dB_t $$
Now to implement them for fitting by likelihood using generic $ r(t) $. I go back to the warning() model implemented in sde_likelihood.R code. We can just solve the odes directly:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Further treatment of the limiting models</title>
      <link>/2010/11/29/further-treatment-of-the-limiting-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2010 19:01:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/29/further-treatment-of-the-limiting-models/</guid>
      <description>Have spent the last three days building and testing the infrastructure to fit the canonical form of a saddle-node (fold) bifurcation by likelihood. Actually I don&amp;rsquo;t use the canonical form straight up: $ dx/dt = x^2 +r$ cannot be fit directly in this manner, since it needs a couple scale transformations on the variables to get the units right (a multiple for the unit scale and an additive factor for the zero point), and more importantly, isn&amp;rsquo;t a stochastic model so cannot assign probabilities to the outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Likelihoods for quadratic models cont</title>
      <link>/2010/11/28/likelihoods-for-quadratic-models-cont/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2010 21:14:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/28/likelihoods-for-quadratic-models-cont/</guid>
      <description>Considering the fits of the quadratic models from yesterday.
[flickr-gallery mode=&amp;ldquo;tag&amp;rdquo; tags=&amp;ldquo;quadraticfitslides&amp;rdquo; tag_mode=&amp;ldquo;all&amp;rdquo;]
Analysis of fits Of course these fits rely entirely on mapping the location of the stable point and the slope through that point, something they still cannot do all that well. In this parameterization the the stable intercept is $$ \hat x = \sqrt{r}+\theta $$ and slope at intercept is $$ \frac{\partial f(\hat x)}{\partial x} = -2\sqrt{r} $$ This creates a numerical optimization problem, since there is high importance on getting the mean right, and less on the variance, the routine tends to fix the combination of r and theta to get the mean right, and then cannot change r to get the slope correct without getting penalized for the loss of likelihood in changing the mean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing Likelihoods for quadratic models</title>
      <link>/2010/11/27/implementing-likelihoods-for-quadratic-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Nov 2010 11:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/27/implementing-likelihoods-for-quadratic-models/</guid>
      <description>Working from the quadratic model for the saddle node bifurcation rather than the linear (OU) model. Recall that the dynamics are:
$$dX = \left( r - (x-\theta)^2\right)dt + \beta \sqrt{X} dB_t $$
and the linear noise approximation gives a linear Fokker Planck equation such that the probability distribution is Gaussian with moments ((corrected from yesterday to scale noise, basically as pure-birth Poisson process))
$$\frac{d \hat{x}}{dt} &amp;amp;= r - (\hat{x}-\theta)^2 $$ $$ \frac{d \sigma^2}{dt} &amp;amp;= -2 (\hat x - \theta )\sigma^2 + \beta \left(r - (\hat{x}-\theta)^2 \right) $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning signals: Likelihoods Straight-up</title>
      <link>/2010/11/24/warning-signals-likelihoods-straight-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Nov 2010 21:44:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/24/warning-signals-likelihoods-straight-up/</guid>
      <description>Meeting with Alan this morning. I haven&amp;rsquo;t solved likelihood of power spectra (previous couple entries in Stoch. Pop / warning signals), though after meeting with Sebastian (11&amp;frasl;9) probably the best method works from the correlation function. Define a new stochastic process Y $$ Y_1 = X_1 X_2 + X_2 X_3 + X_3 X_4 + \ldots $$ $$ Y_2 = X_1 X_3 + X_2 X_4 + \ldots $$ $$ Y_3 = \ldots $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting the details right on the Fourier Transform approach to likelihood</title>
      <link>/2010/11/03/getting-the-details-right-on-the-fourier-transform-approach-to-likelihood/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2010 16:28:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/11/03/getting-the-details-right-on-the-fourier-transform-approach-to-likelihood/</guid>
      <description>Recall that we consider the power spectrum of some measurable fluctuating quantity x(t), defined as
$$ y(\omega) = \int0^T dt e^{i\omega t} x(t) $$ $$ S(\omega) = \lim{T \to \infty} \frac{1}{2\pi T} \left| y(\omega)\right|^2 $$
A little work can show is equal to the Fourier transform of the autocorrelation function, $ \langle x(t) x(t&amp;rsquo;) \rangle = C(t-t&amp;rsquo;) $.
We evaluate the correlation function of their Fourier transform (note $ x (\omega) $ is really $ \tilde x(\omega)$, the new transformed variable, I&amp;rsquo;ve dropped the tilde only out of laziness):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new twist on the approach</title>
      <link>/2010/10/28/a-new-twist-on-the-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2010 16:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/28/a-new-twist-on-the-approach/</guid>
      <description>Matching the warning signal to different SDE models couldn&amp;rsquo;t retain the simplicity and generality needed, so I intend to work on the transformed data instead. Taking the power spectrum of the data, we have a new curve fitting problem:
(Code). This can be turned into a linear curve fitting problem by taking the log of the inverse Fourrier transform, then the slope is our stability parameter. Can we do this estimation by likelihood instead of least-squares?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals -- Where are we now?</title>
      <link>/2010/10/27/warning-signals-where-are-we-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2010 16:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/27/warning-signals-where-are-we-now/</guid>
      <description>The last few days have involved an investigation into the ability to capture the essential features of the dynamics leading up to a saddle node bifurcation as a linear stochastic differential equation. The warning signals question then becomes a model-choice problem between constant and time-dependent coefficients:
$$ dX_t = \alpha \left(\theta_t - X_t\right) dt + \sigma_t dW_t $$
and
$$ dX_t = \alpha_t (\theta_t - X_t) dt + \sigma_t dW_t $$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correcting for the mean dynamics</title>
      <link>/2010/10/26/correcting-for-the-mean-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2010 16:46:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/26/correcting-for-the-mean-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I began to address concerns of different models that have different mean dynamics, and how this influences the warning signals. This poses several kinds of issues.
 First, if the mean is changing, the model fitting must be appropriate to this &amp;ndash; either by fitting this rate of change or correcting for it.
 Second, the variance is expected to scale with the mean, and scale differently under different noise models (particularly environmental vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrong picture, wrong model: why warning signals don&#39;t look like rare events</title>
      <link>/2010/10/25/wrong-picture-wrong-model-why-warning-signals-dont-look-like-rare-events/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2010 23:24:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/25/wrong-picture-wrong-model-why-warning-signals-dont-look-like-rare-events/</guid>
      <description>Detecting a warning signal of collapse isn&amp;rsquo;t about detecting that a system is non-stationary, but more specifically, that the system is about to do something sudden. The classic saddle-node bifurcation example results in a picture like this:
A visible steady decrease interrupted by a sudden jump. The goal is to distinguish this from the case of a steady decrease that involves no loss of stability &amp;ndash; such as would be created by continually lowering the carrying capacity of logistic-model system at a linear rate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2010/10/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/21/</guid>
      <description>Trying to select clear examples of sufficient and sufficient power in detecting warning signals. Addressing a couple side issues today as well:
 Proper handling of trends
 Best model for eigenvalue change
  Computed an example with steeper nonlinearity to compare rate of change in lambda. Here&amp;rsquo;s an example with Hill coefficient of 5 (see code for details). Note that the plot simply shows whichever root the numerical algorithm converges to at the time, should modify to express all roots.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Warning Signals, power, etc</title>
      <link>/2010/10/21/spatial-warning-signals-power-etc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2010/10/21/spatial-warning-signals-power-etc/</guid>
      <description>Noam gave an interesting presentation in our lab today, prompted me to do a little experimentation. Weakening stability across a set of coupled patches should result in increased autocorrelation. Decided to test this with a little visualization with help of a quick R script. Time progresses across the x-axis, 1-D space (on S1) across the y-axis. Each patch suffers a slow loss of stability, resulting in a clearly visible increase in autocorrelation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>1-2pm
 Discussion of reasons early warning signals fail   Insufficient signal-to-noise ratio for early warning Ensemble vs time average &amp;ndash; satisfying ergodicity assumption? Role of bifurcation type. existing literature focuses mostly on 1D saddle node. Role of chaos (certainly frustrates warning signals, but not required).   How general are warning signals? Normal forms of bifurcations. Fitting a good model vs. general warning signals. Problem of extrapolation. Classification scheme of warning signals &amp;ndash; TREE paper(?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description> Working examples  kendall.R example of kendall&amp;rsquo;s correlation test on standard warning signal indicator being misleading.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Value of information  Reed with uniform large noise, logistic map Reed with uniform large noise Reed with uniform small noise Sethi with uniform small noise, logistic map. Sethi with large noise Doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. hmm.. voi_sethi_parameters.md , running value of information setup but with small noise &amp;amp; logistic map. Whoops, this example solves uniform noise but simulates log-normal noise, which probably explains the positive effect of growth noise once again.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Reading Vasilis&amp;rsquo;s PLoS ONE warning signals methods out, listing different methods and announcing the earlywarings R package: 10.1371/journal.pone.0041010, and another comparing methods on some various data sets 10.1371/journal.pone.0038410, which (like Drake) advocates for a mixed method approach.
Modeling extreme risks in ecology 10.1111/j.1539-6924.2012.01871.x
Which is kinda like Richard Katz&amp;rsquo;s extreme value theory in ecology article.
NSF call for Decision, Risk and Management Science, see previously funded examples.
A paper in Eco Lett suggests model-guided field work 10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Tour of existing files (version stable links)
 managed warning is the current direct test of this, but needs decently ranged input example where detection has a good chance to succeed.
 criticaltransition Statistics across replicate crashes that don&amp;rsquo;t show much promise for detection.
 A heuristic implementation in response to the detection of a signal might use a simple rule like a fraction of the optimal harvest of a stable system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Fallacy with May model runs
 $$ X_{t+1} = X_t \exp\left( r \left(1 - \frac{ X_t }{ K } \right) - \frac{ a * X_t ^ {Q - 1} }{s ^ Q + H ^ Q} \right) $$  Working on unmanaged warning. (see #21)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Two years ago, I scribbled an entry into my notebook entitled Wrong Picture, Wrong Model: Why warning signals don&amp;rsquo;t look like rare events. Months later I made some off-hand remark to Alan (my Ph.D. mentor) about how transitions found in historical records, such as the Climate examples in Dakos et. al. (2008), could actually be selecting for stochastic transitions, and this selection process might make them look like traditional warning signals &amp;ndash; i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>EWS review Composing a simple EWS review highlighting where signals are and are not expected and what this means for the system dynamics. With Alan and Noam. See manuscript repository, cboettig/ews-review.
pdg control  Does the matrix formulation fail to account for the treating profits as a function of realized harvest and true stock size rather than quota and measured size?  notebook  fixing some inline equations 04:34 pm 2012/10/09 Updated Readme 02:57 pm 2012/10/09  scicomp discussions on reproducibility  Asked about longevity of code (re: data managment plan) Replied to best practices for linking code to publications  discussions/tweets  @hylopsar @mwpennell thanks - I always find it tricky to explain conditional probabilities clearly, so that&amp;rsquo;s nice to hear Nice paper by +Matt Pennell, Saver &amp;amp;@lukejharmon on biases in inferring early bursts of evolution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>ENSO EWS Let&amp;rsquo;s just see what happens with the MEI data for PDO:
dat &amp;lt;- read.table(&amp;quot;http://www.carlboettiger.info/assets/data/mei.csv&amp;quot;, header=TRUE)  For the moment let&amp;rsquo;s ignore annual structure and just collapse this into timeseries sampled bimonthly.
require(reshape2) dt &amp;lt;- melt(dat, id=&amp;quot;YEAR&amp;quot;) X &amp;lt;- dt$value Z &amp;lt;- X[!is.na(X)] Z &amp;lt;- data.frame(1:(length(Z)-1), Z[1:(length(Z)-1)])  png(&amp;quot;mei.png&amp;quot;) require(earlywarnings) a &amp;lt;- generic_ews(Z, detrending=&amp;quot;gaussian&amp;quot;)  How about the data from MacDonald (2005)
original data link
dat &amp;lt;- read.table(&amp;quot;http://www.carlboettiger.info/assets/data/pdo-macdonald2005.csv&amp;quot;, header=TRUE)  png(&amp;quot;macdonald2005.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/1/01/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/</guid>
      <description>Progress mid-October through mid-December 80% Time: nonparametric-bayes The bulk of my time has been spent becoming familiar with the literature on Gaussian Processes and their numerical implementation. I have written my own Gaussian process code from scratch to convince myself of my understanding of the methodology, and explored some of the related numerical issues addressing computational speed and stability.
I then developed an algorithm for applying the Gaussian process inference of the state dynamics to stochastic dynamic programming methods for determining an optimal harvesting policy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</guid>
      <description>From 03/31, see below for more!
Outline Title
On the ability to detect leading indicators of catastrophe in unreplicated time series
Introduction Background on Warning Signals
 literature Saddle Node bifurcation Detecting decreasing stabilization &amp;ndash; gradual vs changepoint estimation  Reasons detection can fail:
 Ergodicity: ensembles vs single instances Sufficient statistical power Appropriate dynamics  Methods
 Defining an indicator &amp;ndash; significant Kendall rank correlation coefficient τ as in doi:10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Goals next week: Bob &amp;amp; Brian beetle data: what an analysis would be with complete stochastic description. Compare models with different  Full model: Parameter list from current code:
/* Biological Parameters. eggs and pupa can get canibalized */ double b = 5; /* Birth rate (per day) */ double u_egg = 0, u_larva = 0.001, u_pupa = 0, u_adult = 0.003; /* Mortality rate (per day) */ double a_egg = 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alan Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/alan-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Updates  Likelihood calculation for beetle model. Proposed model and calculations Linear parameter change for warning signal model. Results in a few test cases. Likelihood methods within SDE framework, an outline of methods. Subtle problems, good approximations, powerful approaches.  
Questions  LPA vs ELLPA model Defining state space in individual-based model vs stage based model, setting initial conditions? Conclusion: Means non-Markovian system, so likelihood isn&amp;rsquo;t determined in one step approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Annual Progress Report</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/annual-progress-report/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow will be meeting with my dissertation committee: Alan Hastings, Peter Wainwright, and Brian Moore. This provides a good opportunity to summarize the status of my current projects and my principle accomplishments for the year. Will try a tex&amp;rsquo;d document as I&amp;rsquo;ve done in previous years but here&amp;rsquo;s for some preliminary brainstorming.
 Summary: In the past year, I&amp;rsquo;ve published one paper, given 4 talks (CPB, NIMBioS, Berkeley, IIASA), read 144+ articles and wrote 9000+ lines of code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing to Analytic Dynamics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/comparing-to-analytic-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/comparing-to-analytic-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>Goal for today: implement analytic calculations for warning signals.
 10am-12pm  Abstraction/functionalizing code.
 4pm-7pm  Implement GSL ode solvers for linear noise approximation:
Recall our dynamics are d(n) = *e*n + a
and defining the jump moments (van Kampen) α~1~(n) = b(n) − d(n)
α~2~(n) = b(n) + d(n)

recall that we have a linear Fokker-Planck equation whose solution is Gaussian and specified by the first two moments:  These are implemented in code using GSL ode library.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective warning signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/effective-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/effective-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Predicting variance of variance by direct calculation &amp;ndash; still need to crunch some math for the expected convergence.
 Still, the approach should be able to do more than describe single points as unexpected deviates. Still need to address gradual change vs change point analysis. Essentially the same as the phyolgenentic problem &amp;ndash; one rate vs two rates. Model selection approaches? So far theory is essentially built on a model selection between linear models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry title</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/entry-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/entry-title/</guid>
      <description>OWW was down, notebook embedded from springnote:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/goals/</guid>
      <description>Model choice exercise with sdes general likelihood calculation from simulation  Test Case *dX*~t~ = α~t~(θ − X~t~)*dt* + σ*d*t
*d*α~t~ = − β

Approach  The linear approximation to the warning signals dynamics can be captured by the OU process, look for changing α SDE models will also provide some of the coarser approximations for the structured population dynamics. Formulations of these still to do.  Conditional probability Solution to the time dependent OU process, see Gardiner 4th ed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hastings Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/hastings-meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/hastings-meeting/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of cases where variance decreases before crash &amp;ndash; misleading warning signals. Schreiber 2003 Aaron King and Bill Schaffer JMB Hamiltonian vs Dissipative/gradient systems. Are Hamiltonian systems non-biological? Follow up with Darren  Reasons Warning Signals fail  Present (saddle-node model) but insufficient sensitivity to detect (lack ensembles, lack sampling frequency) dissipative but warning signals are backwards (other higher dimensional bifurcations, limit cycles &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; no potential) Hamiltonian instead of dissipative (centers, stochastically become random walks)  Code Updates Early warning signals code now does ensemble averaging, which works!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing warning signals metrics</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/implementing-warning-signals-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/implementing-warning-signals-metrics/</guid>
      <description>The code now contains implementation of the basic warning signals metrics computed over a given window size into the past.
 mean variance skew lag-1 autocorrelation lag-n autocorrelation  These are implemented through the fixed interval sampler function. Recall that the Gillespie simulation API permits two kinds of events, random events occurring with exponential time distribution and events occurring at fixed (scheduled) times, which can be used for discretizations of deterministic continuous time dynamics (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limits to the detection of early warning signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/limits-to-the-detection-of-early-warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/limits-to-the-detection-of-early-warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Our paper, limits to the detection of early warning signals for critical transitions, has now appeared in the Proceedings of the Royal Interface. An open-access copy is available under CC-by license on the ArXiv. The essence of the paper is to bring a more model-based approach to early warning signals, while seeking to remain as general as possible.
Without a model-based approach, it is difficult to leverage statistically meaningful comparisons to identify what is a real warning signal and what is just noise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting/</guid>
      <description>Basically I want to apply central limit theorem for stationary processes (accounts for covariances), assuming mean zero  where
 Discussion of Freidlin-Wentzell theory in connection to Arrhenius law and the well-defined stochastic tipping point which occurs before the branch point. Kurtz results don&amp;rsquo;t really help in the case of ergodicity, can make statements about the (even non-stationary) ensemble limit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meeting w- Alan</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/meeting-w--alan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/meeting-w--alan/</guid>
      <description>Weekly check-in, following up on last week&amp;rsquo;s meeting.  Goals for meeting  Discuss goals for regime shifts seminar tomorrow Discuss my manuscript outline on detection limits for early warning signals Discuss energy model formulation for analytic approximations to Tribolium model.  Meeting Notes  Early warning signals - starting in simple models, proof of principle. Discuss three challenges to detection:   ergodicity sensitivity complexity   Eventually develop robust tools to give confidence estimates (parametric bootstrap) on potential early warning signals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Prosecutor&#39;s Fallacy paper and other recent warning signals literature</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/my-prosecutors-fallacy-paper-and-other-recent-warning-signals-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/my-prosecutors-fallacy-paper-and-other-recent-warning-signals-literature/</guid>
      <description>My recent paper with Alan Hastings, &amp;ldquo;Early warning signals and the prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s fallacy&amp;rdquo;, is now out in PRSB. An open access preprint can be found on the (arXiv) and accompanying (source code) for the analysis can be found on Github.
Recent papers in early warning signals This invistigation is in a very similar spirit to two other recent papers on the subject. Kéfi et al. addresses a different kind of false positive for early warning signals, arising in systems approaching other transitions or bifurcations than the intended culprit, the saddle-node bifurcation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notes/</guid>
      <description>Prosecutors Fallacy Running the null distribution and add to plots
 generate nulls add to fallacy Questions on plots &amp;ndash; show the full replicates plot? Emphasize the two different distributions that result. Additional replicates narrow the null distribution further. hmm&amp;hellip; run model fit part again modelfallacy.Rmd. Need to add the model fit data analysis section into this script.
 knitr&amp;rsquo;s caching really is the way to go with debugging things that need HPC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notes/</guid>
      <description>pdg-control Working group  send summary briefing for stochastic policy costs paper &amp;ndash; DONE send latex/pdf to group  Value of information  To better get at Jim&amp;rsquo;s question, should compare (profit from growth only noise) - (profit from deterministic) + ((profit from measurement only) - (profit from deterministic)) to (profit from growth+measurement) - (determinsitic), i.e. is (growth+measurement) greater/less than (growth) + (measurement) - deterministic?
 Clarify this! is (profit from growth only) the case in which (a) the manager includes growth noise in the solution when in reality it is absent (hence the deterministic solution is optimal), (b) the case where the manager includes growth noise and it is present (i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project tracking (Ecology)</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/project-tracking-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/project-tracking-ecology/</guid>
      <description>pdg-control Has become a variety of different directions:
Policy Costs  Considering different norms. L1 L2 Assymetric fixed When can policy costs pay for themselves? notes  Additional Noise  Starts with replicating Sethi et al. (2005). Consider the performance of various non-optimal solutions, particularly regarding imperfect implementation These are losely collected in Robustness examples, needs some evaluation of the most interesting.  Approaches to parameter, structural, and state uncertainty  (Morph of) Training problem II from the working group.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosecutor&#39;s fallacy notes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/prosecutors-fallacy-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/prosecutors-fallacy-notes/</guid>
      <description>Mostly getting Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy example to run with large enough sample sizes. Finer sampling or more replicates than current settings seems to crash MPI connections over farm cluster, probably a memory issue. Oh well, looks like I&amp;rsquo;ve got a good enough sample size here.
 Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s Fallacy  Citations on Jekyll No ideal solution here at the moment, a couple options:
 Pandoc: My intended solution, Disadvantages: converts everything to it&amp;rsquo;s own markdown format, which messes up my PHP Markdown tables and YAML frontmatter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/reading/</guid>
      <description>Trying to make this show reading of the day, the script below shows only current reading:
Friendfeed discussion on solving this:
Warning Signals  Implementing likelihood-based methods for early warning signals. Trying three models:  
 Model 3 is intended to be a changepoint analysis, where α(t) is piecewise constant. I solved analytically the transition probability density in Model 2 on User:Carl Boettiger/Notebook/Stochastic Population Dynamics/2010/05/06, see this and the following entry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/research/</guid>
      <description>Reviewed timescales manuscript. Revisiting  Meeting  Basically I want to apply central limit theorem for stationary processes (accounts for covariances), assuming mean zero  where
 Discussion of Freidlin-Wentzell theory in connection to Arrhenius law and the well-defined stochastic tipping point which occurs before the branch point. Kurtz results don&amp;rsquo;t really help in the case of ergodicity, can make statements about the (even non-stationary) ensemble limit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisions on Prosecutors Fallacy</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/revisions-on-prosecutors-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/revisions-on-prosecutors-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>Email Alan re: Prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s fallacy manuscript. Schedule meeting.
 Proof corrections for rfishbase manuscript. Done.
 Fallacy simulations: calibration range for May model: expect small fraction of runs to transition by chance from stable state.
  Here we&amp;rsquo;re getting a bit less than 2% chance transitions in 5000 steps.
&amp;gt; sn &amp;lt;- + sapply(1:1000, function(rep){ + x &amp;lt;- vector(mode=&amp;quot;double&amp;quot;, length=n) + x[1] &amp;lt;- 8 # positive equilibrium + z &amp;lt;- rlnorm(n, 0, .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ergodicity Question- Time averaging vs Ensemble averaging</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/the-ergodicity-question--time-averaging-vs-ensemble-averaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/the-ergodicity-question--time-averaging-vs-ensemble-averaging/</guid>
      <description>11am &amp;ndash; 3pm
 Tried time averaging over the entire time window (set sample_size to 1 less than max time); in close agreement with the ensemble predictions (getting around 1355). Mystery doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to actually be a problem in the method, but just innate variability! Even over reasonable time-averages and ensemble averages there&amp;rsquo;s significant deviation from the expected variance! This variation around the warning signal/leading indicator is exactly what might frustrate the warning signal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lab Notebook Goes Open</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/the-lab-notebook-goes-open/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/the-lab-notebook-goes-open/</guid>
      <description>(Originally posted on OpenWetWare)
 This is the first entry in my lab notebook, but not the beginning of the project. I have been exploring demographic and colored environmental noise since beginning my graduate program at UC Davis. Much of that time has been spent in building the appropriate tool set though, so now it&amp;rsquo;s time to dive in.
 A good starting point is Denis et. al. (2001) Ecological Monographs 71.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Current Puzzles &amp;amp; Goals 1 rep
100 reps
 Kendall&amp;rsquo;s tau unreliable, exploring alternatives. Sliding window for identifying when warning is first detected? Goal is to detect any decrease in stability or distance from critical point? Chasing down data from Scheffer. Climate data reuses the CaCO3 from Dakos. Chasing down data from Dakos   Fig. 1 M Cariaco Basin, data file Vostok deuterium CaCO3 data Tropical Pacific core 1218   Warning signals examples with actual tipping points (Figures left).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Working on implementation of the the TwoRates model looking for changepoint: See for most of code implementation sde_likelihood.R and for the model choice example see warning_example.R  General Code cleanup  Added a saddle-node bifurcation simulation in the format of the metapop/hastings/crowley/beetles models already in the stochastic population dynamics library. Allows for C-based parallelized ensemble simulation using my Gillespie library. R call to all of these models can be found in ind_based_models.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Alternate models  Writing down the change-point model correctly now, starting with the simulation. Done. Implemented in sde_likelihood.R
 Implementing Neyman-Pearson comparisons for all three models.
  Linearizing directly from the saddle node model Dynamics:
Slope (alpha) at equilibrium comes from the derivative:
is the slope evaluated at n equal to equilbrium (which is the root of some messy cubic).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Reworking code to allow standard format for:   evaluating likelihood, &amp;ndash; Done fitting by maximum-likelihood, &amp;ndash; Done simulating, &amp;ndash; Done bootstrapping plotting models and bootstrap results.  changePt.sim, changePt.lik implemented.

Function Behavior notes  R&amp;rsquo;s mle function wants a named list.
 Updated parameter handling of OU.lik to allow parameters in alpha,theta,sigma format or theta1, theta2, theta3 format, as either lists or numerics, named or unnamed. Type handling in each function isn&amp;rsquo;t helping the speed, but optimization will have to wait.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>bootstrapping models implemented improved handling of model classes &amp;ndash; included T, t0, N, and X0 in object def implemented plotting for model bootstrap difficulties with changePt model fit remain. fixed one source of trouble &amp;ndash; no longer passes zero-length data to OU.lik() when t_shift is outside the time interval.  Still giving errors on coercing lists into doubles for the saddle_node bifurcation simulated data set. &amp;ndash;fixed, was getting t_shift as a vector from time(X).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals/</guid>
      <description>Bootstrapping for likelihood ratios! Updated class behavior &amp;ndash; all simulation and fitting routines now return timeseries objects as data with correct range and timestep. updated plotting routines. Likelihood ratio plotting function. Bootstraps of parameters can be plotted using the output from the likelihood ratio fit simulation, avoiding redundancy, just specify which model is desired. Bootstrap likelihood ratio plots includes the original ratio and calculates plot range using this information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals -- still in code development</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals----still-in-code-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals----still-in-code-development/</guid>
      <description>OWW was down, notebook embedded from springnote:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warning Signals with SDEs</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/warning-signals-with-sdes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/warning-signals-with-sdes/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Have a functional likelihood calculation from the full individual-based simulation, see Friday. Accuracy needs more testing, and the computation is probably too slow for optimization routines. Have an implementation of the linear decrease in stability model with analytic conditional probability density. Needed a couple adjustments today. Need to add direct simulation to the warning signals package, currently retunrs only time-averaged/ensemble averaged stats. Can be approximated by setting the window equal to the timestep and ensembles equal to one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>notes</title>
      <link>/1/01/01/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1/01/01/notes/</guid>
      <description>Added results into prosecutors fallacy and sent to Alex, Noam, Marissa. Ran pdf copy and sent Treebase to Duncan README added to knitcitations staticdoc documentation for knitcitations (and filed a few issues on staticdocs) Updated documentaiton on treebase, rfishbase. updated their staticdocs documentation as well. rfishbase 0.0-9 update pushed to CRAN Working on prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s fallacy edits from Alex  Alan meeting Discuss management example with ROC curve instead of hypothesis test</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>