<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reading on Boettiger Group</title>
    <link>/tags/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reading on Boettiger Group</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2014/07/31/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/07/31/notes/</guid>
      <description>Berkeley Collaborative Environment Trying out the Berkeley image (Essentially ubuntu 14.04 XFCE with ipython and RStudio installed, but finely tuned to improve user experience; e.g. solid colors for faster remote window connections.)
Highly recommend their paper for the first explanation I&amp;rsquo;ve actually been able to follow that provides a definition of &amp;ldquo;DevOpts&amp;rdquo; (essentially, using scripts rather than documentation to manage consistent cross-platform installation) and explains the differences and similarities between the various programs operating in this sphere, sometimes as alternatives and simultaneously.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/09/16/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/16/notes/</guid>
      <description>class=&#34;task-list&#34; finish up and push backlog of notebook updates knitcitations slidify (issue 46) recently resolved several further issues/requests with rfishbase  ropensci Have implemented a solution to extending data.frame with metadata that I was tackling the other day. This raises several open questions on how we do the implementation, including whether we restrict this extension to providing the attributeList-level metadata (or a subset thereof), or if we allow higher level nodes of eml to act as extensions of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/06/24/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/24/notes/</guid>
      <description>Exploring XML Schema in R I danced around the room after reading these lines in the excellent XML and Web Technologies for Data Sciences with R book:
 We can generate S4 class definitions corresponding to the data structures that are represented in the XML document. We can programmatically generate R code that will map an XML document adhering to this schema to corresponding R data structures. Similarly, we can automate the creation of code to serialize, or write, an R object of a particular type to a suitable XML format corresponding to the schema</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/06/23/notes-on-leveraging-the-ecological-markup-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/23/notes-on-leveraging-the-ecological-markup-language/</guid>
      <description>This post creates new tag eml for posts discussing the Ecological Markup Langauge or the implementation of an R parser thereof (reml).
Why EML? Jones et al.(2005) give an excellent explanation describing the relative advantage of the descriptive metadata approach over vertically integrated repositories (such as Genbank, TreeBase, or many other repostories that have been the focus of rOpenSci development to date).
In short, the EML approach allows archiving of very heterogeneous data without having to standardize everything into a narrow and pre-defined syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/04/17/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/17/notes/</guid>
      <description>warning-signals  Finishing up edits. Writing PRSB reply  Logistics  In tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s Marc meeting, check in about what to include for the CSTAR report manuscript / analysis updates Comments on recent lit?  ropensci  treebase/#4  Reading  Dai et. al. (2013) , with introductory piece by Carpenter (2013) . In this they look only at the spatial extent of a perturbation. Presumbably one might attempt to compare the spatial extent over time to establish a baseline, or otherwise identify a control system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nonparametric-bayes: framing the issues for the manuscript</title>
      <link>/2013/04/11/nonparametric-bayes-framing-the-issues/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/11/nonparametric-bayes-framing-the-issues/</guid>
      <description>Marc meeting: nonparametric-bayes manuscript Very good meeting today going over some big picture considerations in the presentation of the nonparametric-bayes manuscript with Marc. (Also see new entries in issues log on nonparametric-bayes.) Make it clear that we are making a point rather than providing a tool. Focus on the tipping point context rather than the general management context.
 Comparison against a parametric Bayesian model (40) Comparison against an active learning parametric model facing a tipping point (41)  Parametric Bayesian model Drafting parametric Bayesian case for comparison, following Marc&amp;rsquo;s suggestion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/04/02/monday---tuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/04/02/monday---tuesday/</guid>
      <description>Writing  still working on non-parametric bayes draft today..  Reviewing  review sent to PRSB  Reading  Came across this rather nice summary of big data in Ecology through some buzz in the twittersphereHampton et. al. (2013) .
 More fishery managment controversy with Halpern et. al. (2013) critiquing the &amp;lsquo;ocean food provision index&amp;rsquo; from Nature last year, and a subset of that team replying Halpern et. al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/03/14/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/03/14/notes/</guid>
      <description>Writing  Meeting with Steve over outline Writing on nonparametric-bayes manuscript A few notes on notebook-features draft  Reading  EasyABC by Jabot et. al. (2013). While it&amp;rsquo;s great that MEE publishes this stuff, this is unique in that the authors are updating and improving upon an existing package published by MEE the year before, Brook et. al. (2013). The authors of the recent manuscript have certainly made an important contribution which deserves the traditional recognition provided by a separate publication, but one must wonder why we need another package instead of building on the existing one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/27/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/27/notes/</guid>
      <description>Reviewing arg, reviewing. so much time.
Seminar Kate Richerson gave a fanstastic presentation to mega group yesterday showing her integration of behavior and dispersal in krill dynamics. She derives the krill&amp;rsquo;s behavioral movement patterns through a stochastic dynamic programming solution rather than just dictate it to the dispersal model directly.
Reading .
 Provicative stuff in PNAS Perretti et. al. (2013). It would be nice to see the comparison against the generating model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/21/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/21/notes/</guid>
      <description>Applied Math Club meeting (See reading material from Tuesday.
 Start with stable age distribtution (indep of stock-recrutiment) Consider the Entropy of that probability distribution, as function of mortality, by max age Now consider the same for fecundity: the fraction/density of the population von Bertalanffy growth (fecundity) effective mortality rate - mortality rate in an unfished population, distributed with same entropy as the fished population, Kullback-Leibler distance to measure fishing influence?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/12/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/12/notes/</guid>
      <description>Writing  Working on nonparametric-bayes.  Reading Interesting PNAS comment from Doney &amp;amp; Sailley, (2013) (&amp;ldquo;When an ecological regime shift is really just stochastic noise&amp;rdquo;) on the Di Lorenzo &amp;amp; Ohman, (2013) piece in the same issue, showing that time integrated zooplankton data correlates closely with environmental drivers: in this case, the pacific decadal oscillation (PDO) index, which would be missed by the traditional approach of direct correlations. This refutes the previous explanation of such shifts observed in the krill populations as being driven by nonlinear ecological interactions, rather than merely linearly tracking the environment ((Hare &amp;amp; Mantua, 2000)).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2013/02/04/updates-across-various-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/02/04/updates-across-various-projects/</guid>
      <description>At home after birth of Edward since Jan 19th, leaving little time for research. Assembled notes from a few side projects I&amp;rsquo;ve moved forward in the wee hours. Covers the past several days.
XML and RDFa parsing I have been using the lab notebook to explore technology for scientific communication, including making use of semantic and linked data concepts. To illustrate some of the potential these tools can offer I&amp;rsquo;ve started working on a short post with examples parsing and exploring the XML and RDFa data in the notebook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Prosecutor&#39;s Fallacy paper and other recent warning signals literature</title>
      <link>/2012/10/10/prosecutors-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/10/10/prosecutors-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>My recent paper with Alan Hastings, &amp;ldquo;Early warning signals and the prosecutor&amp;rsquo;s fallacy&amp;rdquo;, is now out in PRSB. An open access preprint can be found on the (arXiv) and accompanying (source code) for the analysis can be found on Github.
Recent papers in early warning signals This invistigation is in a very similar spirit to two other recent papers on the subject. Kéfi et al. addresses a different kind of false positive for early warning signals, arising in systems approaching other transitions or bifurcations than the intended culprit, the saddle-node bifurcation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/2012/07/23/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/23/notes/</guid>
      <description>Reading Vasilis&amp;rsquo;s PLoS ONE warning signals methods out, listing different methods and announcing the earlywarings R package: 10.1371/journal.pone.0041010, and another comparing methods on some various data sets 10.1371/journal.pone.0038410, which (like Drake) advocates for a mixed method approach.
Modeling extreme risks in ecology 10.1111/j.1539-6924.2012.01871.x
Which is kinda like Richard Katz&amp;rsquo;s extreme value theory in ecology article.
NSF call for Decision, Risk and Management Science, see previously funded examples.
A paper in Eco Lett suggests model-guided field work 10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday</title>
      <link>/2012/04/06/friday-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2012 21:01:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/06/friday-8/</guid>
      <description>Fishbase  Revisions based on Duncan&amp;rsquo;s feedback Formatting to Journal of Fish Biology guidelines Updated formatting   fixed footnotes issue in pdf version. Externalize tables in word version.
  knit_hooks$set(chunk = function(x, options) { if (!options$split) return(x) cat(x, file = fig_path(&#39;.md&#39;, options)) }   Consider more intuitive function names rather than function arguments?  TreeBase  Needs additional functions replacing sapply queries and argument queries. Table of functions re-organize presentation  rOpenSci GSOC GSoC applications were due at noon today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust control &amp; uncertainty - reading notes</title>
      <link>/2012/03/22/robust-control-uncertainty-reading-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2012 18:19:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/22/robust-control-uncertainty-reading-notes/</guid>
      <description>Ecologists/TREE (Fischer et. al. 2009), (Polasky et. al. 2011) give a nice overview/introduction to the problem. Perhaps most interestingly, both set up resilience approaches as a foil or alternate approach in contrast to a decision-theoretic problem. Fischer&amp;rsquo;s group does a particularly nice job handling the case that these two are separate approaches &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s easy to dismiss resilience thinking as fuzzy optimization of fuzzy objective functions.
The Polasky piece does a nice job refocusing us on the obvious but brushed-over question of the objective function.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parameter uncertainty in stochastic control problems</title>
      <link>/2012/03/11/parameter-uncertainty-in-stochastic-control-problems-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2012 23:52:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/03/11/parameter-uncertainty-in-stochastic-control-problems-2/</guid>
      <description>Day 3 of my short-term visitor stay before the working group starts.
 Wednesday: Travel
 Thursday: 8:45 Group Meeting: Paul, Michael, Lance, Dan, Jake, Carl.
  Training problem II discussion &amp;ndash; problem taxonomy: stochastic , model uncertainty, parameter uncertainty, state uncertainty. Learning on uncertainty (passive/adaptive active management) in the uncertainty cases, all of which increase the parameter space. Evening with Paul&amp;rsquo;s students.
 Friday Writing up Training problem II with Jake, Michael.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday</title>
      <link>/2012/02/02/thursday-13/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2012 22:14:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/02/thursday-13/</guid>
      <description>rOpenSci  Dryad submission xml parsing example to Scott essentially see (fishbase example , and xpath tutoral ) knitr and latex figure placement (use float package with H to enforce placement). cc0 &amp;amp; OSI &amp;hellip; pmc purchase order, dryad data id approval. &amp;amp; writing writing writing&amp;hellip; Re-formating data for ggplot version of graphs, realized I should be specifying id.vars to melt (example from my Q on SO)  Reading  Great special feature on the data era in TREE ((which I mention despite it&amp;rsquo;s misfortune of being connected to Elsivier right now)) (Page, 2012), (Michener &amp;amp; Jones, 2012), (Porter et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday&#39;s reading</title>
      <link>/2011/11/04/fridays-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2011 13:14:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/11/04/fridays-reading/</guid>
      <description>Reading Catching up on journal table-of-contents/rss readings.
News Australia Researchers unhappy (unknown, 2011)
Climate change and Open Science Nature debate on the Berkeley climate team&amp;rsquo;s (BEST) press release in advance of publication. (unknown, 2011) Editor critiques the stunt:
 Richard Muller, the physicist in charge, even told the BBC: &amp;ldquo;That is the way I practised science for decades; it was the way everyone practised it until some magazines — particularly Science and Nature — forbade it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thursday Reading</title>
      <link>/2011/09/01/thursday-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2011 23:58:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/09/01/thursday-reading/</guid>
      <description>Very interesting article on tipping points that seems to answer a question I put to Vasilis back in 2009 at IIASA: whether critical transitions due to bifurcations could be distinguished from stochastic transitions due to rare events Ditlevsen &amp;amp; Johnsen, 2010. Argues that some of the well-known climate transitions may have been stochastic transitions instead. Will need a closer read to better assess how they are distinguishing between such transitions in the data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Notes, presentation prep treebase error handling</title>
      <link>/2011/04/28/thursday-reading-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2011 13:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2011/04/28/thursday-reading-notes/</guid>
      <description>Reading  Oikos journal recently started a rather nice blog. A journal long responsible for some of the best examples of developing and confronting ecological theory with empirical results, with an commendable emphasis on general principles and synthesis, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to see them enter the Web2.0 ecosystem. Editor Jeremy Fox has a nice introduction to the goals of the blog &amp;ndash; check out the &amp;ldquo;new ideas&amp;rdquo; categories for worthwhile reading.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>